Good morning. Um, welcome back. This is
it. This is the grand finale, the final
day. So, thanks so much for everyone
who've made it this far. Uh, it's been a
very long, arduous journey, but
hopefully it was also enlightening and
inspiring. Um, just to let you know,
we'll probably run over today. We'll
probably finish at 4:00 today. So, if
some of you need to run before then,
it's fine. Okay? But, but I want to give
us time to fully explore Divine Comedy
um and engage in a process of
reflection. Um so, uh we'll probably run
a bit, we'll probably run over. Okay. So
uh before I begin, any questions from
yesterday or comments or ideas or any
dreams you might have had yesterday?
Uh yes. Uh I'm uh like yesterday we
talked about like you said you said
nature doesn't equals to God, right? I'm
still a little bit confused about like
what what it actually means.
Okay. So, nature in Dante's
understanding, it is just natural laws
which includes physics, right? It's the
law of gravity. Um, and these natural
laws create the world that we live in
today. And what these natural laws are
just what,
right? The law, the laws of chemistry,
biology, physics. Um, but that's not
what God is. Okay? God is entirety of
the cosmos. So even though um we think
that the natural laws are the end all be
all, they're not because there's
spiritual planes. Okay? Uh there's our
soul and that's governed by divine laws.
Okay? So you need to be able to
differentiate between natural laws and
spiritual laws. And so maybe in natural
law um
um the earth circles the sun but in
spiritual law uh the sun circles the
circles the earth. Okay. And in uh
natural law maybe God is nowhere but in
spiritual law God is everywhere. Okay.
So there's a major economy between these
two. Okay.
Any more questions?
Uh, yes.
>> This is not from yesterday, but um I'm
wondering
what is Lucifer doing in the last layer
of hell? If he just um stays still,
what's the purpose of he being there?
>> He's there to cry. He's there to feel
eternal regret and remorse for betraying
God. Um so, uh we had a discussion of
the angels and there were a lot of
things I got wrong. Um, and I did more
research and there was a very
interesting comment on YouTube that I
found very helpful. But the idea is
this, God creates both angels and humans
with free will. The difference though is
that angels are perfect from the
beginning. So they know uh so they are
beyond time and space. They know the
past, the present, and the future. And
with their free will, they're able to
make the perfect choice. And once they
make the and but and it's only a
one-time choice. Okay. And the choice is
do you want to be loyal to God or do you
want to disobey God? Uh is humility more
important than than you or is pride more
important than than uh to you? Okay. God
will give you that choice. And Lucifer
and the and some of the angels made the
choice. I rather be uh independent. I
rather be proud. And so God permitted
them the choice. He permit them to
rebel. And this created the war in
heaven. They lost and they were cast
down to um
um uh hell. And once there, they could
only feel eternal regret for what
they've done. And the regret consumed
them so much. Okay. Uh humans are
different. Humans don't have perfection.
So humans are permitted to make mistake
after mistake. Um because humans don't
know better. Okay? So that's the
difference between humans and angels. Um
okay. All right. Any more questions?
Yes, Andy.
>> We discussed a little bit about divine
inspiration and the poet kind of
channeling the divine. Um the divine
being
how do I want to say this? So prior to
the Christian poets then we're dealing
with muses. Do you believe that the
pagan poets are viewing the muses
incorrectly and they're divine or the
muses are divine or they they just
mislabeled? Um or is there no problem
there or is there an evolution?
>> Right? So if you look all the great epic
poems that we have whether it's Homer or
Virgil or Milton
um uh Dante they all believe every one
of them believe they're channeling the
divine. Okay. It's not they they're not
engaged in the act of creation. They are
engaged in the act of revelation.
Right? The act of creation is, you know,
you just take something and you just
build it. Okay? But the act of
revelation is like imagine a um a
big boulder and you already know inside
it is this beautiful angel, right? Okay.
So, the act of revolution is all you're
doing is you're basically just breaking
down the border so that it reveals
itself to the world. Okay. So, all all
the great poets believe this uh and
there's no uh differentiation between
them. Okay. All right. Any more
questions? Yes, Julian.
>> Well, I had a dream that I could talk
about.
>> Yeah. Great. We love dreams here. Yes.
It's great that you guys are dreaming
more. Yes. [laughter]
Um yeah, so I have to say it was a
really confusing dream for me. Um and I
don't know how I can really connect it
to Dante, but um so
um I think it started with me wanting to
have dinner with my father and my best
friend and we wanted to set up dinner
and then there was like an electric
cable missing for the grill or
something. So, I went and tried to find
it and then after a while I ended up in
a forest and
um I had a rope in my hand and it kind
of it got stuck in a tree or something
and I wanted to get the rope and so I
got back to the house and tried to get a
letter
to get to the to the rope and then some
some guy from I think a TV series he
kind of distracted me and talked to me
and um said, "Hey, I have a bigger
letter. Come with me." And then I think
that's where it kind of ended. So, it
was a lot about um
I think just being distracted from the
actual end goal by
things, but I was the one who let myself
get distracted. But I don't know how
Yeah. divine it could be.
>> Okay. All right. So, um, with dreams, we
shouldn't put too much emphasis on the
vision. Okay. What's really important
about the dream is the emotion you felt
during the dream. This is how really for
Dante, the cosmos interacts with us
through our emotions. Okay.
um it channels
um a an emotion into us and our soul
feels it, our soul reflects it and then
our soul tries to interpret it with um
time and space and that's why we have
these visions. What's really important
is the emotion that you felt in this
dream. Do you remember the emotion?
>> Yeah, I would say anxious probably the
most. like I was really anxious that I
would get lost that I wouldn't be able
to get the ladder or get the rope from
the tree. So I will I would say probably
anxiety was kind of the most
>> okay and that's probably uh the emotion
that is most raw in you right now. And
once you have this emotion, then you
have to
um continue to reflect on why you have
this emotion and where this emotion
might take you. Did Did you want to say
something? Yeah.
>> I I want to ask, do you remember which
TV character?
>> I think it's the I think his name is
Phil from Modern Family or something.
>> Phil from Modern Family. What what does
he signify to you?
>> I don't know. I I only see him on when I
watch YouTube shorts. So,
>> I I actually think the ladder and the
rope seem very symbolic to me because
what you said reminded me of Jacob's
ladder story and Mark Shagal actually
has a painting, very beautiful, colorful
painting of that. Um, maybe seeing that
painting may relieve
what anxiety you have. Um, you know,
just going a step further, but I
actually think I I I find the latter to
be very positive because it's as if
you're at the beginning of purgatory.
You're embarking on your journey. I
mean, it's it's normal to be anxious.
>> Yeah. No, I actually think it's healthy
to be anxious at at your age. I mean,
it's just your it's just your age,
right? It's like, you know, you're
you're you you're beginning to leave
your family and embark on your own
independent journey. So, you're anxious
and it's just normal and healthy to be
anxious at at your age. Um, okay. Uh,
any more questions or
thoughts or dreams before we begin?
>> Yes, Fred,
>> just one quick question. I was reading
some translation notes in a um version
of the comedy last night and they were
talking about how Dante kind of moves
away from Plato's tripartite soul and
takes more of the arisatilian soul where
it's one soul with three natures inside
and I just wondered if you could explain
a little bit more about it because I
>> didn't really I couldn't grasp how I
obviously he doesn't talk about three
souls in this one, but I didn't I don't
really understand how to interpret that.
>> Okay. So, um what you read is a very
popular scholarship consensus on Dante,
which is he's heavily influenced by
Aristotle, especially Aristotle's um
ideal of the mean, where um the ideal
path is the path that balance is two
extremes. is something that Andy talked
about uh previously. Uh so Aristotle has
a huge influence on Dante and Aristotle
actually is really influential at this
point in history uh because uh Thomas
Aquinus is a heavy aristo to he's a
heavy promoter of the ideals of
Aristotle.
I don't know if people how well people
knew Plato at this time in history. Um
and
um what Dante
alludes to a lot in vine comedy is
Plato's theory that the soul is uh in
immortal. Um and as to how the soul is
divided up,
um I don't think it's really clear in
Divine Comedy. Um I I think it's maybe
schol scholars trying to basically
impose a debate that for Dante didn't
really exist in his mind. And so a point
that that that I will make uh that's
very important is like we just assume
that Dante read a lot and then he
synthesize a lot of this information to
come up with his own understanding which
then becomes
visualized and not in calmly. That's
that's that's how we think the creative
process works. But what we discussed
yesterday is like that's not that's
actually true. It's entirely possible
that he never read Aristotle. He never
read Plato, but he was um channeling
them and their in their ideas because he
had access to the cosmos. Okay, does
that make sense? And and that's a
mistake that a lot of scholars make.
Actually, all scholars make this mistake
where they see an idea and like, oh, it
must be because he read Plato or it must
be because he read Aristotle. And it
could not be and and maybe or maybe not.
Okay. And I mean it's entirely possible
that he is just ch channeling the
cosmos, channel the vine and the idea is
already embedded in them. And and I mean
like because if you actually read the
divine comedy, there's no way anyone has
a time to read all everything
that um D refers to. Okay. It's just his
knowledge is like a like an infinite
cosmos. And you're like, okay, did he
really read an infinite cosmos or was he
able to access an infinite cosmos? And I
would think the latter makes more
logical sense. It may not make like
scholar scholarly sense, but I think it
makes much more intuitive sense. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Oh, yeah. No, no, I'm finished. I'm
finished. Yeah.
which um I would love to um hear from
you on our last day at some point um
kind of how you think Dante has
influenced and ushered in the
Renaissance because um you know if I I
by the way I'm very touched by you
sharing your creative process and also
um what you think would be the creative
process for Dante and so how has this
influenced
the Renaissance if it's not a synthesis
of the past. Um so I'd be very curious
of that. I want I also want to just
mention a few mayulpas. Um one is um I
if if any homosexuals or overweight
people or people who are part of the
history of slavery feel um
uh uncomfortable.
um we are kind of solely couching this
in um a certain place and time and it's
within Dante's world.
>> Yes.
>> So um I want to mention that also the
Last Supper painting um I may not have
seen I may have seen it as a copy in the
Vatican and it's actually in Milan. Yes.
>> Not Florence. Um, but I want to mention
that because
um, I think part of what Dante has
inspired all of us or inspired me at
least is that we're not that different.
We're not that different. And what has
really captured me are the concepts of
free will and the democratic principle
that um everyone no matter what um and
at any point in time you have access
right to the divine
>> right that's the answer is divine okay
so um there are about a million ways in
which Dante influenced the Renaissance
or create the Renaissance okay but but I
I'll just point out the major ones okay
first of all he taught us to stop
looking downwards and start looking
upwards, right? That's especi especially
relevant in our age when AI is so
dominant when we've been taught that AI
is going to liberate us from work when
AI will be the panacea for all society
ills AI is going to solve cancer AI is
going to solve climate change AI is
going to solve poverty so just focus on
AI and we'll be saved okay and D will be
horrified disgusted by this idea because
he's telling us that what matters what
makes us human is our access to the
vine. Okay. AI can never replace us. AI
can enslave us, right? But AI can never
liberate us. AI can never replace us.
And so if we start if we stop just
focusing on the here and now and start
thinking about the divine, lift our head
upwards to the heavens, then this is a
path forward. Uh yeah, Julian, did you
want did you have a point? So we live
more in an Aristotleian
Aristotilian
world than a Platonic world because you
know from the famous painting Aristotle
points downwards and Plato points
upwards.
>> You're completely right. Exactly right.
So um Aristotle told us what matters is
cause and effect. What matters is what
happens here. Don't worry about what
happens there. Plato's the opposite.
Right? So so yeah. So right now we live
in very much an Aristotleian framework.
We need to to return to much more
platonic framework. Okay. I mean it is
just horrible how today we're like go to
college and study
computer programming. That's a future.
Ignore liberal arts. Ignore philosophy.
Ignore art art history. Ignore the great
books. That's the past. And like if you
are truly enlightened, okay, I'm telling
you right now, if you're going to
university, ignore that stuff. Ignore
computer program, ignore STEM. Just read
the great books, read philosophy. That
is the future. The future will be
determined not by those who can computer
program, but by those who can read and
think for themselves. Okay. This has
always been true. Did did you
>> I want to add that I have been
completely horrified by certain
universities cancelling for example um
art history survey course because it
overly focuses on for example western
civilization but I think the solution is
really to add to it um play you know
works and um access to the divine from
other cultures rather than completely
cancelling
Right. And I would also also add that
you should teach what you know best,
right? Because you have a responsibility
to give students the best education. So
you know western civilization really
well, then teach it. And the idea and
what Donna would say is once the spark
of learning is embedded in the student,
the student is naturally going to go
overseas and want to learn more, right?
And this is going to expand the
imagination of the cosmos. So um so
yeah, I mean we we can go on for like
hours about universities. Okay, but but
that's the first one. Okay, like Dante
taught people to look upwards and like
just um that's point one. Point two is
um Dante was first and foremost a
Democrat a as as you said which is and
this is really key and this is why um I
don't like the meritocracy. I I'm very
thankful for Yale for for the education
that that we got, but I think everyone
should have access to to this education
because we don't know who can have the
next um great idea, right? Look at the
Renaissance. It was very democratic.
Before it was only the extremely wealthy
who could write poetry. But during the
Renaissance, look at people like
Leonardo da Vinci. He gave him nothing,
right? The guy was just a commoner. uh
and all the great artists of the
Renaissance were just commoners. And so
it's really about access. It's really
about democracy, right? And and I think
this is why uh I'm so thankful for for
for Carol for giving us this platform
because but because if we really want to
save the world, if we really want to
have impact, we want to make we want to
make sure that anyone everyone can have
access to a great education. Okay,
that's really one of the major goals of
being here today. uh to make sure that
as many people as possible have access
to great education and stop the idea of
only the select only the left can access
a good education. Okay. Uh D mean did
you have a question or
>> um won't AI give more people access to
information and education?
>> Not if they don't have any jobs,
right? Not if they're unemployed.
Not I mean I mean you ask yourself what
is AI doing? Is a AI really liberalizing
education or is it censoring knowledge?
>> Okay. So so so you're right in that you
know that's a propaganda. Yes. AI will
liberate knowledge and give it to
everyone. But what I'm seeing is that AI
is heavily censoring knowledge and
access and it and it is trying to
basically uh reduce humans into human
slaves. Right? Right? We have this gig
economy where most more more and more
people are now working as delivery
workers. You're working as a delivery
worker. Do you have time to go get an
education? Okay. So that's point uh two.
Uh Dante made elite education accessible
to everyone, right? Because remember he
wrote this in Tuskin, not Latin. Latin
you need a very specialized education.
Tuskin is just what you speak every day.
So how they were learning the Divine
Comedy is just reading groups, right?
Someone would just read the Divine
Comedy and everyone would would just
hear it and then people would just
memorize it. So So that's the key. If we
really want to save the world, promote
new um ideas, we need to make sure
everyone can participate in the process.
The more the marrier.
Okay? And that and you know the
diversity of this group shows how
powerful the divine comedy because you
all come from different age groups,
different cultures
um and different ethnicities but the
divine come is universal. Okay, the
second point the third point is uh what
Donn did with divine comedy is expand
the boundaries of the cosmos. Right? He
shows you what hell looks like. He shows
you what purgatory looks like. He shows
you what heaven looks like. And before
this is all this is all considered um
sacred spaces you cannot access. And
once you enter these spaces then you're
allowed your imagination is allowed to
just roam. Look just Google the amount
of paintings that were inspired by that
comedy. It's infinite. Okay. Just one
line and you could have like dozens of
of paintings. Um and and and so that's
really the power of divine comedy, how
it it it is a cosmos onto itself and
expands the cosmos that we live in and
it ignites the imagination. So So I
could go on and on, okay? But I I'd say
those are the three major things. Okay.
Uh Andy, what would you say to
detractors who might say
Einstein had to face the Nazis, Dante
writes his paradisio while he's exiled?
What would you say to people who are
like a gig economy and a late state
capitalism is just our form of suffering
right now for us to
get forged in the fires and and rise
above. I
>> I would completely agree. I I I'm not
pessimistic about our world even though
never before in human history has there
been so much human suffering, right? The
level of corruption, the level of of
inequality,
um the level of materialism, this is
unprecedented in human history. But as
you point out, all the great artists,
all the great ideas came through the
forge of pain and suffering and tragedy.
And that's why I'm so hopeful. I mean,
being with you these past two weeks has
made me extremely hopeful about the
future because I see the spark in you
and I see that once given the right
opportunity, once given the right
education, the spark will just glow and
glow and it will illuminate all of
humanity. Um so so so that's why I think
for the next this 50 years okay it's
going to be like pretty bad for
humanity. It's it's going to be war.
It's going to be uh revolution. It'll be
complete chaos. But this also gives an
opportunity for each and one of you to
make a difference in the world that you
couldn't like maybe 40 50 years ago when
times were a lot more um um hopeful.
Okay. So again what Dr. D would say is
that the hope is not what's given to
you. Hope is what you create yourself.
Okay. So, so thanks for that. Uh any
more comments? Uh uh Anna,
I have two points as an educator to make
about this eliticism or elitism. Um it's
I think it's at the end it's about the
distribution of resources which is a
limited like educational resources like
going to Yale or IV league it's a very
limited resources to understand spend it
on the general public right like Naldo
da Vinci who can be a genius which is 1%
out of all the common people back in you
know society or would you want to focus
it on the people who have you know more
elite I
So I I think about this educational
equality to all the time being one of
the teachers at one of the best
international departments in Beijing. So
yeah I I'm not sure about you know I
think AI and online broadcasting have
brought Yale to everyone but is Yale
essentially for everyone and should be
only for everyone? I have a doubt in
that because it's a use of limited
educational resources. So there will
always definitely be a conflict.
>> I I love your question and I would say
um with the Yale hat um and and prior to
these live streamings we've had open
Yale courses and also right now Yale
college education is entirely free for
anyone's whose family's income is under
$200,000 US. And so there is that
democratic principle but of course we're
constrained by physical space and so
that's why we go virtual
>> which is great. Yeah.
>> So I would also say um is that education
is not about degrees and credentials. It
shouldn't matter if you're a Yale
graduate or not. Um I'm I like look,
Professor David Brahmage
um was here on Thursday and he was
extremely impressed by everyone. The you
guys aren't at Yale, right? So it's so a
great education, it's not about
uh if you're at Yale or Harvard, it's
about how much you want to learn. And I
would also say that okay, maybe a
education is limited, but Dante is not
limited to you. Look, look at this
website that that we have. It's all free
and the resources there are incredible,
right? So, with the age of the internet,
you can read Homer, Virgil, Plato, Dante
for free. Uh, and it's just a question
of will and desire. And I see my mission
and I and I think Yel's mission is to
encourage you, inspire you, and give you
the resources to participate in the
great books yourself. Okay. So um I I
think that what's really important is we
get out the mentality that only if you
want go to Yale are you educated. I
would say that only if you ask questions
only are you willing to um admit you're
wrong. Only if you're willing to um push
past your comfort zone are you educated.
That's what I think an an ed educated
person is. And and I'll be honest with
you, um you know, we're both at Yale and
there were lots of people there who were
not that educated. Okay. Sorry. I mean
like like I I don't work for Yale. I
don't you know, but but yeah, I mean
like so just because you go to Yale does
not mean you're educated. It's one of
attitude. Yes.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Uh any more uh uh Bruce?
>> Okay. So yeah, I think my question is
just is that uh what about future
because as we know the AI technology
right now is being uh you know it's
spread everywhere. So people just worry
about themselves at the present but what
about the future? uh do you think that
in the future people really can go to
Mars and go to some outer space so that
they don't need any kind of the dantings
or classical original idea but instead
they want to create a new culture but we
can call novelty or or do you think such
novelties really can abide by the law of
dings it means that there's well there's
a way so yeah this is my confusion and
this is my question
>> look um my attitude about technology
it's really really clear and it's been
consistent for the past few I think
people like Ellen Musk, San Altman, Mark
Zuckerberg, Peter Theo, uh Steve Jobs,
they're all hustlers. They're all scam
artists. The idea of us going to Mars,
it's impossible. We will never get
there. Okay. Uh there's no evidence that
we have the technology to get to the
moon. All right.
I I mean like like you actually do your
research, the evidence. Yes, Anna.
>> Imagination. If he Ellas has an
imagination that we will one day live
because if we read the space odyssey and
all kinds of science fiction about the
Martian chronicle by Ray Bradberry like
it's all about imagining you know the
impossible I guess right on Nike right
>> I would argue that that um LM his real
desire is not to get to Mars his real
desire is to make a trillion dollars
right there's a difference right I mean
if you were really committed to like
let's get to Mars. That'd be one thing,
but like is he really committed to going
to Mars or is he really committed to
like like making $10 trillion for
himself? And all his actions suggest
that money is actually more more
important to to him. So, um I I am very
skeptical about these people. Like when
I read Dante, I see genius. When I hear
Elmas talk, I think he's a Okay?
I I I do. And Sen Altman, I I think he's
just a complete hustler. If you just do
any research on these people um they are
first and foremost concerned about
making as much money as possible for
themselves. The technology comes um
later. One thing that they are really
serious about is immortality.
They want to live as long as possible.
Okay. So I would say that these people
um the idea of going to Mars, the idea
of of um um creating AI, I don't think
they're that serious about it. But there
are certain things that are serious
about which is one making as much money
as possible. Two, living forever. Three,
creating an I AI surveillance state.
Creating control grid where all humanity
is controlled and they are like Plato's
philosopher kings, right? Where they can
dictate everything and we just we just
do what they say because that's what's
best for us because they know better
than we are because they are elite and
we are we are just sheep. Okay? So
that's what I see and I could be wrong.
Okay? I I hope I'm wrong, but um but I'm
not convinced they know what they're
doing.
All right. Any more comments or or
questions? Uh
>> yeah, I want to add a comment. So, um
they're saying that uh for for a
billionaire to win to heaven is uh is
harder for it's is even harder um how to
say it's harder than a camel to win
through the needle. I think that's why
they are so afraid to death. So, they
want to live forever.
>> Yeah, I I think so. Right. It's like I'm
not afraid to die because well, I don't
have anything to fear. But if you're a
billionaire, you know in your heart what
what you've done to get that that
billion dollars, right? And you're
you're afraid of God's judgment. Um
yeah, I I they're very very passionate
about living forever. Okay. They put a
lot of money into living forever. Um
that's where I think all all the
research, all the money is is really
going. Uh longevity. Okay. Uh anymore?
Okay. Let's let's um let's So today we
finished the vine comedy. Okay. And
[clears throat] to set it up, I want us
again to do a thought experiment, which
is say we're writing Divine Comedy and
we're running now the end of purgatory.
And um
as we said, Dante is on a journey, a
pilgrimage through in purgatory from one
of sin to one of virtue, from Virgil to
Beatatrice. And obviously at the end of
purgatory, Dante will meet Beatric. We
also know that in real life, Dante never
really knew Beatric that well. Beatric
died in childbirth when she was 24. They
met a couple times when they're young.
So they never really uh knew each other
in real life. And we also know that um
when this journey starts, Dante is not
really thinking about Beatric. He's
concerned about his own fame, right? His
shadow literally. Uh he's he loves his
own shadow. And um um over time he
learns to appreciate his love for
Beatric more. He rekindles his love for
Beatric. So now, okay, we are finally
uh Dante is now finally with Beatric and
this is a top of purgatory and they're
going to heaven. So they could be
together for all eternity. Okay. So
Donnie has really fulfilled achieved his
greatest hope which is to be with
Beatatrice. So if you were the ones
writing this ending, okay, how would you
do it? Let's let's again we we did this
with um Inferno and we discussed what
would happen at the Inferno. Of course,
we were completely wrong, okay? But it
helped us better understand why Donnie
did what he did. Um, so whatever we do
is going to be completely wrong. Just
let you know. Okay, you might have read
the end of purgatory. Um, also the the
end of the the end of purgatory, like
the last three ktos, it has confused
scholars for like forever. Okay, you
read the commentary on the last three
ktos about where Dante meets Beatric. No
one knows what's going on. It's
confusing because it's not doesn't fit
into any in into any tradition and
people can be confused by by it. So what
I want to do first is
um discuss or basically brainstorm on
how we think it should end and what we
did and figure out why the ending is the
way it is. Okay, just as what we did
with Inferno. So, let's start. How how
do you how would we structure the ending
of Pertoy where Yeah. Yes. Uh, France.
>> Uh, I think Virgil will will start like
acting super weird cuz like he's close
to heaven and he's he knows he's not
supposed to be here or something and so
Dantel will just lose the trust that
built through uh Inferno and then he's
like seeking someone else and then like
Beatrice comes in and he just transfers
his trust from Virgil to Beatric.
>> Right. Okay. So this is what called an
epiphany, right? where
uh in the ending you want an epiphany, a
realization that oh wow uh Virgil was
wrong for me. The right person is
Beatric. Okay. And then Virgil becomes a
central character because Dante needs to
make a choice between Virgil and Beatric
and ultimately he decides Beatric. Yeah,
that's a great Yeah. plot line. Yes.
Anyone else? Uh Andy.
>> So I'm thinking like learning doesn't
have an endpoint. Virtue doesn't have an
endpoint. And so it's not like it's not
like we go through purgatory and then we
know everything and we're perfect.
That's God.
>> So I feel like imagine I I won the
Olympics then I've got to essentially do
it again but I do it from maybe a place
of glory or something like that. So um I
I would see heaven at like the top of
purgatory and getting into heaven is
just more just from a place of
enlightenment.
>> Right. But but how's Dante feel feeling
at at this point?
>> How's my what? How is Dante feeling at
this point?
>> I mean, you're feeling accomplished, but
yeah,
>> you're feeling like you've got another
mountain to climb,
>> right? Dante is feels um well, he's
pretty ecstatic because he's seen
features again, but he's also like very
feels very accomplished, right? He's
done the impossible, right? He's climbed
Mount Purgatory as as as a human.
>> You don't you don't love your wife the
most on your wedding day and then you're
like, I did it all.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Right. But but but you would say there'd
be a wedding. Would there be a wedding
between Dante and Beatric? Maybe an
allegorical wedding. Okay. Yeah. A
wedding, right?
Exactly. Right. So you would expect a
wedding of some sort between Dante and
Beatric. Sure. Okay. Great. Anyone else?
Let's let's let's expand. Yes. Yeah.
Carol,
>> just like Stacius. Um when he was ready
for heaven, the earth shook and
everything.
>> Yes.
>> So um you know just something that's
like you know joyful. It may not be an
earthquake but you know something that's
equivalent.
>> Yeah. Exactly. That's beautiful.
Exactly. Cosmos celebrating of some
sort, right? A cosmic cosmos cosmic
celebration. And it could be the heavens
open up and there's pure light. It could
be another earthquake, right? It could
be raining or something. Okay. But like
the heavens are celebrating that the two
are together just as you know at the end
towards the end of paradise the heavens
are having sex as the two are together.
Okay. Um uh Fred
I'm not sure how I would predict the
ending because Dante isn't dead. So, is
he going to enter heaven forever or is
he going to wake up like
>> like it was all a dream and then his
life is changed until he dies,
>> right? No, what we're we're talking
about the end of purgatory. And so, we
know heaven's coming, but because Peter
will take uh Dante to heaven, but I'm
saying like how do you how would you
transition this? How do you end
purgatory?
>> Yeah. Well, I I guess
just thinking
um as a counterpoint to him making a
choice between Virgil and and Betrice
like there'll be I suppose there'll be a
clever way in which he doesn't really
have to make a choice that the leap of
faith just happens and that he's so
changed that
>> it just seems a bit confusing that he
would get to a crossroads and then have
to make a choice I think or he would
like flow into be.
>> So So maybe just an embrace, right?
Dante sees Beatric and they hug each
other, right? It's a hug. It's an
embrace. Okay. Yeah, sure. Uh Oang.
>> Um I think just like Inferno, um maybe
um Dante will be um out of conscious
again and be born again.
>> Okay. Maybe he'll just faint, right?
Maybe he'll just faint.
Um, okay. And this will signify a
rebirth. Yeah, sure. Okay. Um, uh,
Edward,
>> could there be a final big conflict with
Virgil and Virgil really reveals his his
true [clears throat] colors?
>> Okay. Yeah, maybe a fight, right? A
conflict,
right, where Virgil turns into Lucifer
or something. Yeah. Okay. Possibly.
Okay. We we're just using our
imagination. Uh do
>> uh maybe Dante will feel a bit ashamed
because during this journey he's been
kind of like passive uh passive like
traveler through purgatory and hell uh
and um wardrobe being his guide and
during this journey Dante Dante himself
been has been um like uh he has lost his
uh face in Beatus and lost his direction
like multiple times. Right. I'll I'll
say if I haven't done it, I'll I'll feel
like a little bit ashamed to be.
>> Okay. May maybe he's anxious. Okay.
Maybe he's anxious. Uh maybe he's
afraid. Okay. Possibly. Sure.
>> Right. Uh Crystal.
>> Yeah. So, I was wondering I think maybe
Virgil will try to create conflict
between Dante and Beatatric cuz as you
mentioned originally, maybe because
Beatatric is pretty pretty and then like
Virgil's like sure fine. I'll be his
guide. And then now like Dante's
ascending to heaven and then maybe he's
kind of like jealous and whatever. And
also I feel like cuz like in Inferno we
were assuming if it were a Hollywood
movie. I'm thinking if um we are doing a
Hollywood movie right now, there might
be a slow-mo that is kind of like the
creation of Adam where like Beatatrice
has her hand and like like this and then
like Dante's kind of like as to have it
in a slow
>> that's beautiful. Yeah. Like a slow
motion embrace, right? And they're not
really embracing but they're just
touching each other a bit. Yes. Okay,
great. So, first of all, um Virgil
refused to let go of Dante, right?
Because
Virgil's like, I spent all this time
investing in you, right? Building you
up, giving you birth. You're still mine.
So, it's very hard for Virg to let go.
Um also the um I would say cinematic
cinematic embrace between
ver between Beatatrice and Donnie.
Right? This is what the moment we've
been looking for, right? The final
consummation between Beatrice and Dante.
Uh Anna,
>> I feel like he's going to be maybe
lighter like he came out of the hell
being dusty and dirty. Then maybe he
will come translucent
>> like glowing or whatever like a pearl
like you know so something light.
>> So maybe a transformation right?
>> Yeah. of some sort whereas you say he
was once a beggar and now he's a prince.
>> Yeah. But I also think that this has
happened before where we guess all this
cinematic Hollywood version but it
didn't happen.
Okay. That's what I think.
>> Right. Okay. It's impossible. It's
impossible to predict what's actually
going to happen. But I think the idea of
a metamorphosis
for Dante is very important. Right. Who
he becomes a butterfly,
right? We're expecting a metamorphosis
cuz he's been through
uh these seven terraces and now he is
cocoon and he's about to fly, right? So,
we should expect him to become a
butterfly. Yes. Uh Julian,
um I feel like he would distract himself
one last time. Um because, you know,
throughout Purgatory, he always, you
know, got distracted a little bit. Um
especially in the first circle from his
fame. So I feel like there would be some
something that would distract himself
from actually entering heaven,
>> right? Okay. Yeah. So maybe one final
doubt, right? One something something to
actually keep him back. So maybe, you
know, if we if we're actually writing
the Hollywood movie and we're actually
filming it, then you know Beatress comes
from the heavens like an angel, okay?
She just descends from the heavens and
the heavens open up. It's pure bliss,
pure light. Um, the sun is singing. Um,
there's a rainbow, okay? Birds are
flying, okay? It's just pure bliss. And
Dante wants to go to Beatric, but for
whatever reason, he turns away. Okay.
Yeah, sure.
Uh, Fred,
>> do you think that if it was a Hollywood
movie, there would be like once Dante
and Betrich are reunited, like Virgil
does a fourth wall break and like winks
to the audience or something like like
raises his eyebrow to the audience.
>> Okay, maybe
>> he's the last one left with the re
Hollywood movie, we would expect a
transformation for Virgil as well,
right? Okay. So, not just Donnie, but
also Virgil because honestly, regardless
of how we feel about Virgil, uh he has
come across as heroic in the Divine
Comedy, right? He has taken Dante Fu
hell and purgatory. Uh he took Dante on
his back and climbed up um Lucifer. So,
he is extremely courageous, heroic
individual. Yeah. I think Virgil will
become the ultimate uh in the Greek
sense the tragic hero the great person
with that dramatic flaw that's going to
cause right so then we're supposed to
sympathize with him or feel bad for him
that he you know yeah either do the
sedupion of the emperor making him you
know writing poetry for empire or it's
also his conscious choice but you know
there's this sense of inescapable fate
for him that he is ought to be the tool
for the empire in Spy. Okay. You know.
>> So, yeah. So, it's possible he it's it's
it's either or. Okay. He either rises or
he falls. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
>> Um Crystal, did did you have a
>> I was saying maybe like um there will be
a scene where God is asking Virgil, are
you sure you want to return to hell? And
then he is like, yeah. And then he walks
away.
>> Yeah. Okay, great. Okay. Yeah. So, we
need we need a resolution. Okay. for the
virtual storyline, right? The resolution
is Petra says, "Virgil, I want to thank
you so much for doing this. You've
accomplished your mission and we would
like to give you entryway to heaven as a
reward." And Virgil's like, "Nah, no,
thank you." He walks away. Okay. And and
and this would really reveal the true
character of Virgil, right? Yes.
Um, Ivy.
Okay. Maybe another dream. Exactly.
Right.
Okay. Um,
maybe another dream
to
um Yes. Okay. to to leave more imiguity,
more possibility for the reader. Okay.
Any other
uh Yeah, David. I think the uh uh
Hollywood uh would be a result of u
dentist uh creative presence. So uh if I
look from the Hollywood point of view I
would it would be like a reverse
engineering to find the roots of the
Hollywood paradigms. So I think uh if uh
it's uh the original scheme which should
be a much um uh implicit and much
grander scheme. So I would also look for
elements in the Greek um climate
solution. So there should be some kind
of uh
element uh some kind of uh microscopic
superpowers play in every small part of
dentist
um you know act. So I expect some small
drama there but I don't know how it
goes.
>> Yeah. Okay. Right. So we expect one
final climax right of climax. Right. And
the climax could be, you know, uh,
Virgil and Beatric fighting over Dante.
It could be Dante turning away from
Beatric. Yeah. But there'll be a climax
to this, right? Okay. Anyone else? Uh,
yes. Thank you. Oh, sorry. What's your
name?
>> Solomon. Okay. Yes.
like Dante to utter words of like poetry
like poetry within poetry or words of
praise towards God or Beatatric.
>> Yeah, exactly. Thank you so much. That's
a great Yes. Okay. So, this is the
climatic uh poetry. Okay. So we can
expect Dante because he's cleansed
himself of his sins. He is now at the
height of his poetic powers and now he
is going to just create this beautiful
poetry praising Beatric right to as a
consummation of their love. Yeah, that's
a great suggestion. Yes, in the
Hollywood movie they would definitely do
that, right? where Dante is now
transformed. He's now a prince, he's now
a butterfly, and now he is at his poetic
genius, at his poetic height because
he's climbed so far. Uh yeah, Bruce.
>> Yeah, maybe like uh you know, Gatsby
because you know when Gatsby just faced
to death, he's not just only about to
think about his sin, but he just think
about his lover. So maybe uh Danting
just like Gatsby, you know, just he can
see the green light and we just call him
to go to the heaven. So yeah, maybe that
is for sure.
>> Yeah. So yeah. So exactly. Okay. Uh
anyone else? Okay. So that's great.
Okay. This is fantastic. And um this
would be a fantastic ending to
purgatory. And um spoiler alert, we're
completely wrong. Okay. None of this
happens. None of this happens. Okay? Not
one of these things happens. And this is
what confuses scholars. And quite
honestly, when I read the the end of
purgatory, I didn't had no idea what's
going on. Okay? It's just completely
confusing. And so, in the final class,
uh what we're going to do is as a group,
we're going to co-create. Okay? We are
going to really try to appreciate why
Dante is doing what he's doing. And you
can't say, "Oh, he's just because he's
just tired, you know, he's he's he's
written like, you know, like 60 ktos or
70 ktos. He's just exhausted and he's
like, I really need to get to heaven."
Okay. So, he's just being he's just
being lazy. That's not the answer. Okay.
All right. So, let's uh start off with
Kanto 26 of purgatory.
>> All right.
While we moved at the edge, one first,
one after, and I could often hear my
gentle master saying, "Take care and do
not waste my warning." The sun, its ray,
already altering the coloring of all the
west from azure to white, was striking
me on my right shoulder. And where my
shadow fell, it made the flame seem more
inflamed. And I saw many shades walking
intent upon a sight so strange. This was
the reason that first prompted them to
speak to me among themselves. They said,
"He does not seem to have a fictive
body. The uncertain of them came as
close to me as they were able to, while
cautiously they never left the
boundaries of their burning. Oh, you who
move behind the others, not because of
sloth, but reverence perhaps, give me
who burn and thirst and fire your
answer. I'm not alone in needing your
response, for all these shades thirst so
for it more than an Indian or Ethiopian
thirst for cool water. Tell us how you
can, as if you're not yet caught within
death's net, make of yourself a wall
against the sun." Thus one of them had
spoken to me. I should now have answered
clearly had I not been fixed on
something strangely evident. For in the
middle of the burning path came people
moving opposite to these, and I, since
they moved left, stared in suspense.
There on all sides I can see every shade
move quickly to embrace another shade,
content they did not pause with their
brief greeting. Okay. Stop. Okay. All
right. So, um, in writing, we're very
concerned about character arc, right? We
want to show how Donn has changed as a
person. So, explain me how this scene
uh, shows that Donna has changed as a
person.
Okay. So, so what's happening is is like
they are now in a terrace of lust, the
very last terrorist. And um Donn is
walking and these shades who are about
to enter the terrace of lust. They see
him and they know he is a he is not
dead. He's not a shade. So they're like,
"Wait a minute. How did you get here
before? What would Donnie do when he was
in any purgatory? What would he do?"
Yes, Crystal.
>> Um he stops and enjoys their praise.
>> Exactly. Right. He stops. He talks with
them because it's like a fan asking for
autograph.
What does he do here?
What does he do here? Yeah. Fred,
>> he's looking at how they're like hugging
each other quickly and then although
they're both burning, he just is really
amazed that they're just quickly hugging
and then moving. Quickly hugging and
then moving.
>> And so why is he doing that?
>> Because one I maybe he doesn't
understand how shades can touch each
other. um or interact in that way. He's
never really seen it before other than
with the blind people who have to rely
on each other. And he's probably
thinking if this is the circle of lust,
what does it really mean for their
punishment? And also, why are they happy
and sort of friendly with one another?
>> Right. He's trying to figure out what's
going on, right? And how's that
different from before?
>> Yeah. He was more just amazed and
was just like thinking about himself and
looking at their punishment. But I guess
it seemed quite apparent to him what was
going on before like the punishments
were more clearly linked.
>> No, no, no. I'm saying in
anti-purgatory,
right? So the difference is before Donna
was focuses on his shadow, right? Now
he's focused on knowledge. And this goes
back to Plato's alley of the cave,
right? Where you're you're trapped in a
cave because you focus on the shadows.
If you want to go into the light light,
you have to focus on knowledge. It does
that make sense? Okay. So, this is a um
this shows us the character arc how uh
Dante is now changing as a person. He's
much more focused on his mission. He's
most much more focused on the light on
gaining knowledge. Okay? And so in his
mind, he keeps on observing, asking
questions and uh debating with himself.
Okay? Keep on going.
>> Line 34. As ants in their dark company
will touch their muzzles each to each,
perhaps to seek news of their fortunes
and their journeyings. No sooner is
their friendly greeting done than each
side tries to outcry all the rest even
before he starts to move ahead. The new
group shouting Sodom and Gomorrah the
other that the bull may hurry toward her
lust. Pacifi hides in the cow. Then just
like cranes of whom apart to flee the
sun fly north to riffian mountains while
the rest to flee the frost fly toward
the sands. One group moves with the
other opposite us and they return with
tears to their first chance and to the
shout appropriate to each and those who
had intreated me came close again in the
same way they done before. Their faces
showed how keen they were to listen. I
seeing their desire once again began. Oh
souls who can be sure of gaining the
state of peace whenever that may be. My
limbs mature or green have not been left
within the world beyond. They're here
with me together with their blood and
with their bones. That I be blind no
longer. Through this place I pass above
a lady has gained grace for me.
Therefore I bear my mortal body across
your world. So may your deepest longing
soon be appeased and you be lost within
the heaven that's most full of love most
spacious. Please tell me so that I may
yet transcribe it upon my pages who you
are and what crowd moves in the
direction opposite.
Each shade displayed no less
astonishment or less confusion than a
mountaineer who even as he stares about
fall silent when rough and rustic he
comes to the city. But when they set
aside astonishment that soon subdued in
noble hearts, he who had questioned me
before began again. Blessed are we who
would in order to die better store
experience of our lands. The people
moving opposite us share the sin for
which once while in triumph Caesar heard
queen called out against him. That is
why and as they move off from us they
cry cry out Sodom reproaching their own
selves as you have heard and through
their shame I bet the fire's work.
>> Okay. So sorry. So um this is not open
interpretation. Clearly these people are
homosexuals. Okay. And there are they
have to atone for the sin of lust. Okay.
And there's two pieces of evidence.
First of all, when Caesar is in his
triumph, people shout at him queen.
Okay. That's clearly a reference to
homosexuality, saying that Caesar is
gay. He's had sex with a lot of men.
Also,
um when when they are moving towards the
fire, they call sodom. Okay? which gives
us the word salami which means
homosexual. Okay. So um I I know there
are a lot of scholars concern is uh
Dante antihomosexual.
Um I don't think he's any homosexual but
clearly this is a reference to
homosexuals.
Okay. All right. And why would Dante
be concerned about homosexuality? I
don't think he's any homosexual but he's
concerned about homosexuality. Why?
What's his main concern? Uh, OA u maybe
I think he he thinks that homosexuality
as a sign of complacent.
>> A sign of what?
>> Complacent.
>> Okay. We are in a terrace of lust, guys.
Lust,
>> right? Yes. Fred. Well, a kind of simple
interpretation is that it's pure lust
and pure admiration and want to possess
beauty because you're not in love with
somebody for a procreative purpose. And
in a way, it allows you to be in love
with yourself. Okay. Uh Crystal
>> um I'm not trying to express my own view
but just recalling to what we mentioned
before like homosexuals tend to um seek
for those sort of intimate relationship
more than heterosexuals. So maybe that
is why he is concerned just like what we
discussed in the previous seminar
>> right but it's not intimacy right uh
Anna
>> I think homosexuality ultimately
represents this elitism or narcissistic
or you know exclusiveness like we only
want to hang out with our own kind and
he thinks that that is the issue other
than procreation obviously
>> yeah the key is procreation right
because when you are enter into a
relationship with a woman you're going
to have a baby okay and that is you're
you're kind of like forced to uh devote
yourself to the family whereas
homosexuals well you can just go from
relationship to relationship to
relationship doesn't really matter.
Okay. So so that's that's uh Donny's
concern. All right. Uh Andy so I've been
I've been actually researching this
since we were in Inferno. And an
important thing to to know is that the
sodomites and inferno are in the realm
of violence in the realm of lust. And
there's this actually there's this quote
in uh inferno 16 106 to 108 in brief I
know that my company have has clerics
and mens of letter and fame and they
were stained by by the same set and what
I've come to to read and this is one
interpretation it's not not the way to
to look at it only is that these are in
in academia in the religious sex and
stuff like this there's going to be only
men there at this time. You don't have
women in there.
>> And so you have male teachers and
priests who are taking advantage of the
youthful and freshary
>> young men.
>> And so it's sodomy because there's no
young women there. We're not talking
about lesb lesbians at all because
there's no and he doesn't bring it up.
We don't have oh these women behind
closed doors are doing these other
things.
>> And so there's
we're often told it's it's oh it's
violence against nature. But in in hell
it seems to be you're taking away either
duties like academia for Aristotle or
Plato or duties of of Christ in the in
the church and you're and you're doing
that or you could be doing rape which
would be violence there. And here I
think it's really
progressive a life
realm changing that he's got you can you
can be a gay person and still get to
heaven
>> because these are consensual adults.
It's just you cannot rape people and you
cannot take advantage of your position
of power on a young boy.
>> Yeah, that's that's Thank you so much
Andy. Thank you so much. Yes, exactly.
Okay. So, I would also add that at this
time in history, people want the
Inquisition to happen. Okay. There's
popular support for the Inquisition.
Today, we learned the Inquisition, it's
about sending out heresy. The major
complaint
uh that people were filing uh in during
the Inquisition was exactly this like my
young boy who I trusted to the priest is
getting is you know, right? So, so this
is a huge issue at this time in history.
Okay. And that's why the Inquisition was
actually pretty popular among the common
people because it was the only way to
redress this issue um that was pretty
common back then. So, thanks Andy. That
that that's great. Okay, let's let's
continue, please.
>> Line 82. Our sin was with the other sex.
But since we did not keep the bounds of
human law, but served our appetites like
beasts when we part from the other
ranks, we then repeat to our disgrace
the name of one who in the beastial
planks became herself a beast. You now
know why we act so and you know what our
sins were. If you would know our names,
time is too short and I don't know them
all. But with regard to me, I'll satisfy
your wish to know. I'm Guido Gwin
Guinazelli, purged here because I
grieved before my end. Okay. So, Guidi
Grenazilli and Donna are very good
friends. In fact, um Guido Grizzilli is
probably the most famous uh Florentine
poet at this time in history. Okay. And
this is someone that Dante really
admires. So, a lot of this journey right
through purgatory is really to find his
poetic voice to sort of stand out from
the crowd and that's why it's so
populated by poets, right? Remember how
in any pur we met Sordello and then we
met Statius and now we're meeting Guo
Gazelli and Virgil is is Donny's guide.
So um you know something that Donn is
really concerned about is how do I set
up from this crowd right how do I have
my own create my own unique poetic voice
and this something that uh haunts Dante.
Okay uh keep keep on going. Line 94. As
after the sad raging of the Kirgas, two
sons finding their mother had embraced
her, so I desired to do but dare not to.
When I heard him declare his name, the
father of me and of the others, those my
betters, whoever used sweet, gracious
rhymes of love, and without hearing,
speaking pensive, I walked on, still
gazing at him a long time, prevented by
the fire from drawing closer. When I had
fed my sight on him, I offered myself
with such a pledge that others must
believe completely ready for his
service. And he to me, because of what I
hear, you leave a trace within me, one
so clear, leaf itself can't blur or
cancel it. But if your words have now
sworn truthfully, do tell me why it is
that you have shown in speech and gaze
that I am dear to you. And I, to him,
it's your sweet lines that for as long
as modern usage lasts will still make
dear their very angst. brother. He said,
he there whom I point out to you, he
showed as one who walked ahead. He was a
better artisan of the mother tongue,
surpassing all those who wrote their
poems of love or pros romances. Let the
stupid ones contend who think that from
the mo there came the best. They credit
rather than the truth, allowing their
opinion to be set before they hear what
art or reason says. So many of our
fathers once persisted voice after voice
in giving to Guon the prize. But then
with most the truth prevailed. Now if
you're so amply privileged that you'll
be admitted to the cloister where Christ
is abbot of the college then pray say
for me to him a pastor nost that is as
much of it as those in this place need
since we have lost the power to sin then
to make place perhaps for those behind
him he disappeared into the fire just as
a fish through water plunges toward the
bottom. saying that my desire was making
ready a place welcome for his name. I
moved ahead a little toward the one who
had been pointed out to me and he spoke
freely. So does your courteous request
please me. I neither could nor would
conceal myself from you. I'm Arno who
going weep and saying with grief I see
my former folly with joy. I see the hope
for day draw near now by the power then
conducts you to the summit of the
stairway. I pray you remember a time
opportune in my pain. Then in the fire
that refineses he hid.
>> Wait. So so sorry I made a mistake.
Actually Donnie did not know uh Guyaido,
but he's obviously a huge fan of
Guyaido. Okay. And so uh Donnie here
meets two really famous poets and Donna
is humbled by the fact that you know
Donnie is trying to pay homage to them
and they don't care because all they're
concerned about is redemption. Like like
I don't care about my former fame. I'm
just focused on my own personal
salvation, redemption. All right. Uh
let's go on.
Kanto 27.
Just as there were m its maker shed his
blood, the sun shed its first rays, and
Ebro lay beneath high Libra, and the
ninth hour's rays were scorching Gang
Jesus's waves. So here the sun stood at
the point of day's departure when God's
angel happy showed himself to us. He
stood along the edge beyond the flame
singing bayati mundo cord in a voice
that had more life than ours can claim.
Then, holy souls, you cannot move ahead
unless the fire has stung you first.
Enter the flames and don't be deaf to
song you'll hear beyond. He said when we
were close to him, and when I heard him
say this, I became like the one who has
been laid within the grave. I joined my
hands and stretched them out to fend the
flames, watching the fire, imagining
clearly the human bodies I'd once seen
burning. My gentle escorts turned to me,
and Veril said, "My son, though there
may be suffering there, there's no
death. Remember, remember if I guided
you to safety, even beyond the back of
Gurion, than now closer to God, what
shall I do?" Be sure, although you were
to spend a full 10,000 years within this
fire center, your head would not be
baler by one hair. And if you think I am
deceiving you, draw closer to the
flames. Let your hands try out within
the fire your clothing hem. Put down by
now put down your every fear. Turn
toward the fire and enter confident. But
I was stubborn, said against my
conscience, when he saw me still halting
obstinate, he said somewhat perplexed.
Now see, son, this wall stands between
you and your beatress.
As at the name of this be promised about
to die, opened his eye and saw her. when
then the malbury became blood red. So
when my stubbornness had softened, I
hearing the name that's always flowering
within my mind, turned to my knowing
guide, at which he shook his head and
said, "And would you have us stay along
this side?" Then smiled as one smiles at
a child fruit has beguiled. Then he
ahead of me entered the fire, and he
asked us, who had walked between us
before, dividing us to go behind. No
sooner was I in that fire than I'd throw
myself in molten glass to find coolness
because those flames were so intense. My
gentle father, who would comfort me,
kept talking as we walked of Beatric,
saying, "I seem to see her eyes
already."
>> Okay, stop. Okay. Again, again, the idea
of a character arc, right? Uh how Donnie
is changing as a person. And um
so there's a wall of fire
and Dante is scared, right? Because it's
a mental leap, you know, like I'm going
to walk into a into fire and like I'm a
body. I'm going to burn to death. And
Virgil's like, "No, it's nothing. Uh
trust me." Right? And how does Stan
respond?
>> He doubts.
>> He doubts. Okay? Do you understand? And
this is really the first time
that Dante
doubts Virgil right before Ver Dante put
his complete faith in
uh Virgil and they were all doing sort
of like really crazy things like climb
out Lucifer like D's like wait a minute
here he's Lucifer isn't he going to kill
us and like and Virgil's like no just
trust me and like literally Donnie would
put uh himself on Virgil's back and
allow put his complete faith in Virgil
Right. But for the first time at this
critical junction when when the only set
in between him and the end is a is a
wall of flame, Dante doubts Virgil.
Okay. And again, this shows you the
character arc, right? The change in
Dante, the the epiphany, the realization
in Dante that Virgil can't really be
trusted. And so, how does Virgil get
Dante to to cross that wall wall of
fire?
How how how does he get uh Julian?
>> Well, yeah. Um he reminds him of Beatric
on the other side of this wall.
>> Yes. Okay. Virgil
uh reminds Dante our real goal is
Beatrice. And then this
reassures Dante and allows Dante to
cross now. Okay. You see how this is a
journey right from Virgil to Beatatric.
Okay. And we Yes.
I I can't get my head around how Virgil
is so like confident in even though he's
from hell, how does he like know
or how can be so confident in like
trying to convince Dante if he himself
wouldn't be able to do this? If he
himself is from hell, from the depths of
hell,
>> right? And this is something we've
discussed before, right? How does Virgil
know all this? How does he know that
this wall of fire is actually innocuous?
It's harmless. And he has complete faith
that if I just walk into it, I'll be
fine. And he himself
um is from limbo.
And so
he's not worthy enough to
uh be in this wall fire. How would he
know this stuff?
Yes. Yes. Where
>> I think it alongside the divine fire and
the idea of he's been given the whole
truth as a wonderful poet.
>> He knows that the fire is about
revealing truth and lust is probably one
of the most hard things to let go of
because you think I'm reducing the
extent of my love. I have such great
love. To let go of lust, I'm not sure
how much love will be left. But D Virgil
knows that Dante only has one P left and
that it's really the right thing for him
to do. So in this case, even though he's
dangling the eyes of Beriche before
Dante, I think he's being the most
honest about just relax. This is the
right thing to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Because he knows that fire reveals truth
and fires.
>> So So Julian, yes.
>> So but is Virgil is also going through
this fire, right? So is he himself
cleansing of his of his sins?
>> So so so this is something that that you
you need you need to appreciate. At any
time
Virgil can go to heaven. Do you
understand this? At any time there's
nothing stopping him from going to
heaven. Nothing. Do you understand? He
has all the knowledge. He has all the
ability. What he lacks is the will. Do
you understand? Okay. This is this is
what what's telling us. He knows he
knows how to do this. Okay. He knows how
to get to the uh Garden of Eden. He
knows how to climb to the Mount
Purgatory. At any time, heaven is open
to him. He just chooses not to do it.
Okay?
And you have to ask yourself, why does
he not go to heaven? And it and the
answer, yes, but but he still goes
through the fire with Dante, right?
Right. Because he he knows because he
knows how to do it.
So he's doing it but without without the
faith but he's still doing it or
>> okay so u this is hard hard to
appreciate okay but everything in D's
cosmos is choice it's all about free
will you understand okay so even if you
have the capacity to go to heaven okay
even if the door is open to you still
have to choose whether or not to walk
into the door
>> it's an allegory of the education and
elitism that we talked about earlier.
>> Yes,
>> it's all there for you.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> These are all low hanging fruits.
>> Yes.
>> It's more whether you limit your own
yourself.
>> Uh Oang, I have a question. So, I'm
wondering what's your uh take on
um Dante's attitude towards um Virgil
when he first met Virgil and to this
point. Uh, is he viewing Virgil as a
tutor or a competit competitor or
look look it's entirely one of love, you
understand? Nothing else. Just pure love
for Virgil. It's it's like you love your
father. Do you understand? It's that
nothing else. There are some other
things in place, but at the heart, okay,
Darn just loves Virgil completely. All
right. All right. Uh let's let's let's
let's
continue.
>> Line 55. A voice that sang beyond us was
our guide, and we attended to that voice
emerged just at the point where it began
to thine. Venite Benedict May. It sang
within a light that overcame me. I could
not look at such intensity. The sun
departs, it added. Evening comes. Don't
stay your steps, but hurry on before the
west grows dark. The path we took
climbed straight within the rock and its
direction was such that in front of me
my body blocked the rays of sun already
low be behind us and we had only tried a
few steps when I and my sage's sense the
sun had set because the shadow I had
cast was spent before one color come to
occupy that sky and all of its immens
immensity and night was free to summon
all its darkness. Each of us made one of
those stairs his bed. The
power and desire to climb ahead. Like
goats that when they graced were swift
and tameless along the mountain peaks,
but now are sated and rest and ruminate
while the sun blazes untroubled in the
shadow silently watch over by the
herdsmen as he leans upon his staff and
oversees their peace. Or like the
herdsmen in the open field spending the
night beside his quiet quiet flock,
watching to see that no beast drives
them off. Off. Such were all three of us
at that point. They were like the
herdsmen. I was like a goat. Upon each
side of us, high rock walls rose.
From there, one saw but little little of
the sky. But in that little I could see
the stars brighter and larger than they
usually are. But while I watched the
stars and revery, sleep overcame me. Ste
sleep which often sees before it happens
what is yet to be. It was the hour, I
think, when Cithria, who always seems a
flame with fires of love, first shines
upon the mountains from the east, that
in my dream I seem to see a woman, both
young and fair. Along a plain she
gathered flowers, and even as she sang,
she said, "Whoever asks my name know
that I'm Leah, and I apply my lovely
hands to fashion a garland of the
flowers I've gathered, to find delight
within this mirror, I adore myself.
Whereas my sister Rachel never deserts
her mirror, there she sits all day. She
longs to see her fair eyes gazing as I
to see my h hands adorning long she's
content with seeing I would labor and
now
>> Okay. Okay. So this is the third and
final dream that D has in uh the Divine
Comedy and the dream is this. There's
Leah and Rachel. Do you guys know the
story of Leah and Rachel?
>> Uh Jacob. Um, okay.
>> Oh, you
>> Oh, it's the older sister that Jacob
didn't want to marry, but he married her
uh after the wedding night. Oh, too bad.
It's the wrong girl. And then he worked
another seven years for Rachel, who's
way more beautiful, and waited for him
also faithfully. And yeah.
>> Okay. All right. So, uh the story, it's
really important for you guys to
appreciate the story. Okay. Otherwise,
it's it's impossible to interpret the
dream. But uh Jacob who is um the
founder of Israel, okay, the the
patriarch of Israel, he gets into a
fight with his brother Esu. And Jacob is
forced to run away and he goes to far
away and he meets um a relative of his
name, Laban. Laban says, "You're a
relative and I want you to stay and work
for me and I'll give you shelter." And
Labon sees that um Jacob has already
fall in love with Rachel.
And um and then Jacob says, "I will work
for you, but I would like your daughter
Rachel for marriage." And Leah's well,
you're a relative. It's better for me to
give it to you. Give her to you than a
stranger, but you will have to work for
me for seven years and then I will give
Rachel to you. And that's the agreement.
And for these seven years, what's
happening is that Jacob is working
really hard and Rachel is looking at him
from afar with longing eyes. Okay,
that's what it literally says in the
Bible, with longing eyes. So, she is
just waiting and waiting for the day to
end uh for the seven years to end so
that she could consummate their love
together.
And Jacob is just busy working and
working really hard to prove he's worthy
of Rachel. Okay, the wedding night comes
and there's a huge celebration.
Um, Jacob is drunk. He goes into the
tent and he has sex. He wakes up and
it's not Rachel,
it is Leah who is the older sister. And
again, um, you have to read the Bible to
appreciate the beauty of the story.
Okay, it's written magnificently. is
pure poetry. And then Jacob's just
really angry and says to Laban, "You
cheated me." And then Laban says, "It is
not the custom of our land to marry the
younger sister before the older sister.
So I will make you a deal. I will give
you Rachel as well,
but you have to work for me for another
seven years." And then Jacob's like,
"I'll do it." Okay. At this point,
Rachel has a choice, right? She going to
say she can say I've been cheated as
well and just run away, but instead she
chooses to
um
marry Jacob
and the three of them are stuck
together. Okay? And obviously Leah and
Rachel hate each other, right? It
doesn't say in the Bible, but you
actually read the story. Leah and Rachel
hate each other. Leah Leah hates the
fact that Rachel is going to marry
before she does. And so Leah plots with
her father to screw Jacob and Rachel
over. Okay. So knowing the story of
Jacob, Leah, [clears throat] and Rachel,
tell me what the dream is about.
Ra, it's it's it's a very simple dream
where Donnie meets Leah and Leah is
crafting a garden of flowers
and Rachel is just looking at at her
mirror and she's she's looking at there
all day long. What's this dream about?
She content with seeing I with labor.
What's this dream about?
I I think Leah doesn't think she's as
pretty as Rachel. So, she thinks she
needs a garland while Rachel is
confident with God's creation of her and
is able to
>> Why would Donna care about Leon Leon
Leo? Leo and Rachel.
>> Rachel is in one of the highest places.
>> He doesn't know that yet. Oh, yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So Leah, since she didn't
get her husband's love, she tried to
gave birth to as many sons as possible.
And that's what made Rachel really mad.
It's like, wow, God, you side with them
to give them so many sons. And so Leah
obviously is kind of elevated in that
patriarchical society. Um, but so I
think maybe the garden or the flower has
to do with planting seeds and having I
don't know. And then Rachel is like,
"Oh, I'm just beautiful. I look at
myself, you know, because I'm pretty so
my husband's going to love me anyways."
and but she was upset until she has
Benjamin. But yeah.
>> Okay. Anyone else?
Uh Damian,
>> may maybe it's like revenge because um
Jacob had to work in the fields. Now um
Leia has to pick up flowers and racial
justice.
>> Okay, we have to connect this with the
reality D is living in. Okay, remember
how there are three dreams. The first
dream is of the eagle carrying him,
snatching him. Um,
uh, the second dream is the siren,
right? And then Virgil comes in and rips
off her clothes. The third dream, the
last dream, the most important dream is
Leah and Rachel together. Why would
Donnie have these dreams? Okay, we have
we have to we have to remember we don't
we can't take these dreams as
independent visions. They're not
independent visions. They are
manifestations of his desires, right?
They are manifestations of his emotions.
So what is his emotion and what and why
he started having this dream?
Yeah, I
>> think he's stealing himself for the
final push to get to bee where the the
labor of getting through purgatory is
like the labor that would earn him Leah,
but he has to do a double layer in order
to reach Betrice who's a who's more like
Rachel in this case where she's like
because Bri is the ultimate goal. It's
almost like the monad reflecting itself
and to get to that final center, you
need to do the work, get tricked, and
then just do it all again just for the
love.
>> Um, okay. But let's go into Damon. Okay.
He's been through hell. He's been for
Poratory. What is he thinking now? I
mean, he doesn't say it. He doesn't
think it, but he feels it. What What's
he thinking? What's he feeling now?
>> Will he be tricked again or
>> um
I'm sure it's worth it, but I maybe have
a millisecond of doubt sometimes.
I think he's really excited. Right.
Right. He's been through hell. He's been
through purgatory. He's done everything
that is required of him. And what is
next for him?
>> Heaven. Right. Beatric. Beatric is
waiting for him. So what what what's he
he's expecting
>> to see Beatatrice?
>> But what's he expecting when when he
sees Beatatrice?
>> Wedding with
>> he's a wedding, right? That's why Leah
and Rachel are here because Lee and
Rachel married Jacob and he sees he's he
sees himself as a new Jacob. It's like,
okay, you know, I'm going to get married
now. Okay, do you understand? Okay, so
it's not really about the vision that
matters. It's about the emotion in the
with embedded within the um um vision.
So this is one of longing, right?
>> Would you say Leia could be Virgil?
>> Uh I think that's
>> No, I I don't think Virgil is is here. I
I think um I I I think you know the
focus on Rachel, right? Rachel never
deserts her mirror. There she says all
day she longs to see her fair eyes
gazing uh to see my hands adorning long.
She is content with seeing I with labor.
Okay. So it's it seems Rachel is in the
process of waiting to be with Jacob.
Okay. All right. Great. Does that make
sense? Okay. But why is Rachel looking
in the mirror?
>> And she never deserts her mirror.
>> Yeah. I mean, like, okay, all this makes
sense, right?
Dante.
Uh, yes.
>> I think it's this contrast kind of like
Mary and Meline. So like Rachel is
content with seeing, I with labor. It's
almost like Rachel is natural beauty and
Leah is like plastic surgery. It's like
she's laboring like she's putting
flowers all over herself to make her
worthy of the wedding to plot the
wedding while Rachel is just like I am.
>> Okay. All right. So um something for us
to appreciate is
um what dreams are, what visions are is
that you take a particular story that is
common, okay, that is commonly accepted
and you change in a way because you're
embedding your emotions into it.
Okay? So never in the Bible says that
Rachel looks in the mirror. Okay? Never
does it say that.
>> It's narcissism.
>> It's narcissistic. Do you understand?
Okay. So, there's there's a conflict.
There's a paradox here in that Dante
um wants to be with Beatric like like
he's like this is going to be a wedding,
right? And but
that's why and that's why he dreams
Rachel and Leah, but there's this
narcissism that is embedded in the
story, right? where Rachel, his true
love, is looking at herself. Okay. So,
what was this narcissism doing in this
dream?
Okay. And um I'm married. So, so I'll
tell you the answer. Okay. I I I know
what the answer is.
What when when Dante meets Beatatrice,
what is he expecting Beatric to do?
And he's like, he she will definitely do
this because we're getting married. Yes.
>> Um,
positive and negative appraisal. She's
like, "Oh my god, you're so handsome. I
can't believe you're here. I love you so
much." And then like look him up and
down,
you know?
>> No, I know. I like No, no. Like I'm
married, okay? So, I'll tell you exactly
what I'm expecting. I'm expecting my
wife to praise me every single day,
okay? I don't care. Okay? Like like like
that's why I'm getting married because I
my wife faces me every single day. Do
you understand? Okay. And that's the
beauty and the paradox of divine comedy
where Dy's telling you I'm expecting me
to meet Beatatrice but I want I mean
like yeah but what I really want is for
her to say Dante you work so hard to get
here. Okay. She it's narcissistic.
So it's not too love. Do you understand?
And that's a paradox here where Donnie
thinks that oh I'm going to meet
Beatatric and this shows my true love to
Beatatrice but this dream reveals to us
that no there's a hidden agenda there's
a hidden emotion which is narcissism
right what he really wants is Beatatrice
to praise him to the sky and this is
something that that we discuss right we
think that the what the ending is is
where Beatatrice praises him and they
touch each other they embrace Okay.
>> Okay. And yes,
>> it's extremely realistic.
>> Like on the wedding day, my husband got
mad at me for not attending to him even
a little bit.
>> Yes.
>> And I was like, man, I'm the bride.
Nobody looks at the groom. Okay. You
wear something. Nobody cares what you
wear. And he's like, "Oh my god, on the
wedding day, you don't care about me."
And you know, but it's very human
nature, I guess. Even on the wedding
day, right? Like Yeah.
>> Yeah. And look, I've been married for 10
years and every time my wife says
something nice about another guy, I get
really upset. Okay, it's really strange
because look, I mean, she's like, you
know, Jack M's a really smart guy. I'm
like, who the hell is Jack Ma? You know,
like like I get really upset like I'm
better than Jack Ma, right? So, so this
is such um this is so beautiful
depiction of human of true human nature.
Okay. I get very upset when when my wife
uh praises another man, even though
like, you know, it makes no sense. Okay.
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> Line 109. And now with the reflected
lights that glow before the dawn and
rising are most welcome to pilgrims as
returning their near home. The shadows
fled upon all sides. My sleep fled with
them. And at this I woke and saw that
the great teachers had already risen.
Today your hungerings will find their
peace through that sweet fruit the care
of mortals seeks among so many branches.
This the speech the psalm words that
Virgil spoke to me and there were never
tidings to compare and offering delight
to me with ease. My will on will to
climb above was such that at each step I
took I felt the force within my wings
was growing for the flight. When all the
staircase lay beneath us and we'd
reached the highest step, then Virgil
set his eyes insistently on me and said,
"My son, you have seen the temporary
fire and the eternal fire. You have
reached the place past which my powers
cannot see. I brought you here through
intellect and art. From now on, let your
pleasure be your guide. Your past is
steep and past narrow past. Look at the
sun that shines upon your brow. Look at
the grasses, flowers, and the shrubs
born here spontaneously of the earth.
Among [snorts] them, you can rest or
walk until the coming of the glad and
lovely eyes. Those eyes that weeping
sent me to your side. Await no further
word or sign for me. Your will is free,
erect and whole. To act against that
will will be to therefore I crown and
miter you over yourself.
>> Okay. All right. So this is the very
last these are the very last words that
Virgil will speak to Dante. Okay. What
Virgil says to Dante is um
I've brought you here but now you are
you are now on your own. You are now
completely in control of yourself. You
don't need me anymore. So what is Virgil
saying to Dante here? What is this?
What's what's what's Virgil really
saying to Dante?
It's goodbye. Okay, this is it.
Right. Does not do I know this? Does he
know it's goodbye? No. Why not?
He doesn't know it's goodbye. He doesn't
think it's goodbye. Why not?
>> Well, I remember in parody. So, doesn't
he miss he misses Virgil? Like he
>> No, but I'm saying like like what does
what Donnie hears this and what and what
does Donnie think? Why doesn't Donnie
know this is goodbye? This is clearly
goodbye to us, right? But it's not to
Dante. Yes.
>> Because it's hard for him to perceive
that the mentor, the prophet, the
father, you know, the all knowing guide
now is going to leave him because it's
unacceptable. It's like you know all the
truth more than me, more than I do. What
is expecting? What is expecting?
>> Let's go together,
>> Andy.
>> Yeah. Yeah, this is the moment that the
student becomes the master, right? So,
um he doesn't realize that Virgil
doesn't have the will to get into
heaven. He assumes the best and there's
some reality here.
>> So, so but but what is finally expecting
to happen?
>> Them to go together.
>> They're going to go to heaven together.
Do you understand? Right. Status is
going to heaven. I'm going to heaven
first go to heaven too, right? In his
mind, he's he's already seen all this.
He's seen a wedding with Beatatrice
where Beatatrice praises him to the sky
and says like, "You did it, Dante.
You're my hero. Okay, you're the
greatest in the world." And he's
expecting Virgil to be
um to to give to preside over this
marriage and then they'll all go to
heaven together and live happily ever
after as a family. That's like literally
what what what he's expecting and what
he's decided will happen. Okay, does it
make sense? All right, let's let's
continue to count 28.
>> Council of 28. Now keen to search within
to search around that forest dense a
life of green the vine which tempered
the new day before my eyes without delay
I left behind the rise and took the
plane advancing slowly slowly across the
ground where every part was fragrant. A
gentle breeze which did not seem to vary
within itself was striking at my brow,
but with no greater force than the kind
winds, a wind that made the trembling
boughs, they all bent eagerly to find in
the direction of morning shadows of the
holy mouth. But they were not deflected
with such force as to disturb the little
birds upon the branches and the practice
of their arts. For to the leaves with
song, birds welcome those first hours of
the morning joyously and leaves the
flight of bird into their eyes. Just
like the wind that sounds from branch to
branch along the shore of Class through
the pines when aololis has set soo
loose. Now though my steps were slow,
I'd gone so far to the ancient forest
that I could no longer see where I had
made my entry. And there I came upon a
stream that blocks the path of my
advance. Its little waves bent to the
left, the grass along its banks. All of
the purest waters here on earth will
lash against that stream would seem to
be touched by impurity. It hides no
thing. That stream, although it moves
dark, dark beneath with neverending
shadows, which allow no ray of sun or
moon to reach those waters. I halted,
and I set my eyes upon the farther bank
to look at the abundant variety of newly
flowered boughs. And there, just like a
thing that in appearing most suddenly
repels all other thoughts, so great is
the astonishment it brings. I saw a
solitary woman moving, singing, and
gathering up flower and flower. The
flowers had colored all of her pathway.
I pray you lovely lady, you who warm
yourself with grace of love, if I may
trust your looks, which often evidence
the heart, may it please you, I ask of
her, to move ahead and closer to this
river, so that I may understand what
you're singing. You have reminded me of
where and what, just when her mother was
deprived of her, and she deprived her
spring. Proerena was as when she turns a
woman dancing keeps her souls close to
the ground and to each other and
scarcely lets one foot precede the
other. So did she turn upon the little
red and yellow flowers to me knew
different with aversion lowering chase
eyes. I have besieged and I was
satisfied for she so close that the
sweet sand that reached me then became
intelligible. No sooner had she reached
the point where that fair river's waves
would barely bathe the grass, then she
gave me this gift, lifting her eyes. I
do not think a light so bright had shown
beneath the lids of Venus when her son
pierced her in extraordinary fashion,
erect along the father bank, she smiled,
her hands entwining very colored flowers
which that highland needing no seed and
genders. The river kept us just three
steps apart. But even hellspawn, where
Cersei's crossed, a case that still
curves all men's arrogance, did not
provoke more hatred in Leander, when
rough seas ran from abidos to sestos
than hatred I bestowed upon that river
when it refused to open. She began,
"You're new here and may because I smile
in this place chosen to be mankind's
nest. Wonder perplexed, unable to detect
the cause, but like to clear your
intellect is in the song beginning.
And you who have stepped forward, who
beseeched me, tell me if you'd care
more. I've come ready for all your
questions till you're satisfied. I said,
the water in the murmuring forest
content in me against the recent
credence I gave towards the existence.
At this she said, "I'll tell you how the
source of your amazement has its special
cause. I'll clear the cloud that left
that's left you so distraught. The
highest good whose sole joy is himself
made man to be unto nect good. He gave
man this place as pledge of endless
peace. Man's fault made grief his day
here, and man's fault made him exchange
frank laughter and sweet sport for
lamentation and for anxiousness.
Below this mountain land and water
vapors which follow heat as far as they
are able produce their perforations to
prevent them from molesting men placed
[clears throat] here. This mountain rose
up this close to heaven from the point
where gate where its gate blocks it's
free of such disturbance.
Now since all of the atmosphere revolves
within a circle moved by the first
circling unless its round is broken at
some point against this height which
stands completely free within the living
air that motion strikes and since these
woods are dense they echo it. And when a
plant is struck its power such that it
impregnates air with seeding force. The
air revolving past the seed abroad. The
other hemisphere, depending on nature,
its land and sky, conceives and bears
from diverse power powers diverse trees.
If what I've said were known, you would
not need to be amazed on earth when
growing things to root, but have no seed
that can be seen. And you must know the
holy plane on which you find yourself is
full of every seed, and it has fruit
that there cannot be gathered. The water
that ye see does not spring from a vein
that vapor cold condensed restores. Like
rivers that acquire or lose their force.
It issues from a pure and changed
fountain which by the will of God
regains as much as on two sides. It
pours and it divides. On this side it
descends with power to end one's memory
of sin. And on the other it can restore
recall of each good deed. To one side it
is leaf, on the other you know it.
Neither stream is efficacious unless the
other's waters have been tasted. Their
savor is above all other sweetness.
Although your thirst might well be
satisfied even if I revealed no more to
you. I give you freely to a corollary.
Nor do I think my words will be less
welcome to you if they extend beyond my
promise. Those ancients who in poetry
presented the golden age, who sang its
happy state perhaps in their harnesses,
dreamt this place. Here mankind's root
was innocent. And here were every fruit
and never ending spring, these dreams,
the nectar of which poets sang. Then I
turned around completely and I faced my
poets. I could see that they had heard
with smiles this final corollary spoken.
that done, my eyes returned to that
farewell.
>> Okay, so here he's met Matilda,
who is the guardian of the Garden of
Eden. Okay, this is the Garden of Eden.
Um, and it's an inversion, right? Where
uh in the Bible, the Garden of Eden is
where we were banished from paradise.
And here, the Garden of Eden is where we
will enter paradise. Okay? This is where
uh Beatatros will descend from heaven
and pick Donnie up to bring him to uh
heaven. Okay? Okay. And within the
garden of Eden, there are two rivers.
[clears throat]
Okay. Um, this goes against the biblical
tradition. What are the two rivers of
the Garden of Eden in the Bible?
The Tigers and Euphrates. Right here,
it's the leaf
and the youo.
The youo
is from Greek tradition, the river where
you forget everything. Okay? You drink
from it, you forget everything. Okay.
But in Donny's conception, it is a place
where you forget sin.
Uh the you know is is something that
Donnie it's a word that he makes up.
Okay. Uh Donnie like Shakespeare does
this a lot. He they make up new words.
You know is Greek. This means good. This
means mind. Okay. So um the leaf makes
you forget sin and then what the yo does
is make you remember
[clears throat]
your goodness. Okay. So the idea is like
after you drink from these two rivers
and you must drink from both rivers in
order to access heaven, you'll forget
all the bad things you've done but you
will remember all the good things you've
done.
Why would things be constructed in this
way? Right?
To enter heaven, [clears throat]
you must forget all the evil you've done
and remember only the good you've done.
Why would that why would that be the
case? Uh yes, France. Um I think it's a
way to protect heaven from evil cuz like
even if you think of evil cuz our souls
reflect what are we are thinking and our
actions then just the thought of it or
like some micro action that's negative
would impact heaven and create u
dissonance or like chaos in heaven. So
you really need to take that off and
then just like remember greatness. It's
in the same way you reflect what you've
done well and then the more people
reflect positive then it just grows
inside.
>> Yeah. That's brilliant. Exactly. Right.
Yes. Okay. So, yeah. So, um think of
pollution, right? You can't go in being
with with any remember your sin because
you might pollute everyone else. Okay.
Yes, that's a great idea. Anyone else?
Uh yes. So, so what was your name?
>> Skyler. Okay. But I think it's quite
important for you to remember your sins
or like remember your mistakes and
remember your moral missteps because
that way it teaches you what is wrong
and how that hurt other people so you
remember not to do that in the future.
If you forget all of your sins, won't
you like maybe accidentally do them
again?
>> Okay. So, so, so, okay. Um, um, Anna,
>> I want to respond to Scarlet that
>> um because you have already done that.
You have already repented on your sins
for a million years in purgatory. You
know, it's enough is enough. You know
what I mean? But if you keep repenting,
then you feel like you're unworthy of
heaven and then you are stuck at the
lowest level in heaven again. And then
that's you loses the whole point of
going to heaven.
>> Okay. Yes. Uh Fred,
>> I Yeah, I
I think um I really like the two rivers
because I think that Dante is preempting
the phrase etinarcadia ego where it's
like was a common thing in romanticism
where the poets would complain that even
when they were in paradise their ego
would still be there and that would
still be the source of problems. So in
this case, the forgetting river is super
crucial because it's the only way to
cleanse the ego. So and also that it's
important and we've just seen that
they've been through purgatory, but I
don't think you could commit more sins
in heaven. So it's not that important to
remember,
>> you know, like there's not even a
possibility that you could redo them.
>> Uh yes. Um uh
>> again about the river I thought it's
very interesting in all cultures in
Chinese culture when you reincarnate you
go to the the hell and drink which is a
portion that makes you forget everything
in your past life so that you're ready
for rebirth and so I think it's a
similar you know universal idea that you
need to forget. Yes, exactly. Uh David,
>> I think this is u a very um you know
insightful uh you know paragraph into
Chinese you know into uh character
uh because um you know uh it also
mentioned you know you have to remember
what you what you did right because that
will give you a structure of how to
behave. Uh so this is a very well
balanced uh you know structure where you
have to both uh or you have to yeah and
you have to both forget but also have to
remember
>> yeah this like positive psychology right
like be positive that's what they want
in heaven uh do did you want to say
something
>> to say what Anna said you have to like
forget I think like forgetting your sin
uh symbolizes that you have now uh you
have now like reborn yourself then
you're ready for heaven and you're ready
to drop out to drop out the like uh past
behind and totally forgive yourself.
Yes.
>> Yes. Exactly right. Okay. Yeah. And I
would also point out it's free will
right where um everything is governed by
free will. You choose to be in
purgatory. You choose to do penance but
you cannot actually choose to forget
things. Okay. And so this is um Oh yeah.
Yes. Edward,
>> is it also a blessing to to the to the
soul as well? Because uh through some
lens doing these sins is like a trauma
to yourself.
>> Yes.
>> So it finally allows the soul to be
free.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Andy,
>> I wonder if memory is um a process of of
time and you're going to a place outside
of time.
>> Yes.
>> In paradise.
>> Yes. Exactly. Um yeah, your memories
aren't really relevant in in paradise.
Yes. Uh Franis,
>> there's a physical aspect where if you
forget your sin, then you're super light
and you can physically reach heaven.
Whereas like the little amount of sin
would just create heaviness inside you.
>> Exactly. You're right. Yes. So the sin,
the member of the sin is the last vest
vestage of your physical body, right? Um
and they are they are corrupting your
soul or or they are tainting your soul.
Okay. Yes. Anyone else? Uh, Skyler,
>> I just want to ask a question. So, if
forgetting your sin is makes you lighter
and I guess better, would it be a good
idea to forget your sins on earth? Like,
if we're on earth and then if we forget
all of our sins, would that make us
better?
>> Okay. Does anyone want want to respond
to this?
>> Uh, Bruce.
>> Yeah. Actually, I I always think like
like you said because uh when I was
young, I thought I can do anything I
want. I don't care about what saying or
what kind of god or what is I'm me. I'm
just myself, right? I can do whatever I
want. But after, you know, for a while,
especially when you just experience a
lot of things and you you can see that
greedy, this sexual desire, the torture
you in the night, you even cannot find
sleep and you can just have date with
many more boyfriends or girlfriend even
have sex with them all of them. For what
you just try to have such kind of desire
you want to be better than other you're
saying you can be more competitive than
other but actually is not you still have
to go back to to to the heaven to to go
to the god the god is still there and
just keep watching you all the time and
you have to face the truth to face your
sin this is this cannot be escape from
it you want to be yourself but actually
you're not
>> okay
>> thank you uh Damian
>> I I don't think you should forget your
sin on earth or there would be no
reflection.
>> Okay. So, um uh David
>> uh you know in real world unlike in the
dentist uh you know uh literary world I
don't think there is any water you can
drink just to cleanse yourself of memory
of things.
>> Yeah.
>> You really have to do a lot of good
deeds and to replenish yourself of uh of
good memories in order to flush out the
the few things you have done.
>> Okay. Um so yesterday we discussed um
the idea of the soul right and we how
and how we said that what the soul is is
you have a physical body and the soul is
really um
something that exists in the spiritual
realm. Okay. So it is um like energy
fields or whatever. Okay. So that's why
and that's how memory works because when
you do something it may not change your
physical body but it does change your
spiritual body your soul. Okay. So and
you know Fran used the word trauma.
That's what that's what sin literally
is. It's trauma. It's traumatizing your
soul. Okay. So so when you uh get hit
you might bleed and that hurts your
physical body. But when you do evil,
when you commit sin, you are
traumatizing your own soul. Okay? Uh and
your soul becomes distorted. So another
saying this is like you remember
everything that you do. You you may not
be conscious of it, but you remember it
at some level. And this is going to
change the nature of your soul. And this
is going to change how you relate relate
to yourself and relate to others as
well. And the more traumatized you are,
the more
um the more your soul uh looks downward
and the more good you do, the more
virtue you do, the more the more you are
to look upwards. Okay? So what this is
saying is what the rivers are doing is
they recognize that uh these sins they
are physical in some way, right? And
that's why you actually need to wash
yourself because they are they stay in
your soul and it's like you just can't
like oh imagine them disappearing. You
just you you just can't forget them. You
have to wash them away, right? You have
to take a shower before you you attain
to heaven. Does that make sense? Okay.
All right. Great. Any more questions? Uh
Anna
>> like baptism too, right? You have to
>> go into the river and baptize yourself
to wash away your sins.
>> This is literally baptism. This is
literally baptism. Okay. So, Matilda is
the Garden of Eden. And what she's going
to do is she's going to baptize all the
souls in in these two rivers before they
actually ascend to heaven. Okay. So,
this is the process. Any more
um questions or comments?
All right guys, let's continue to KTO
29. Um, and I want to apologize that my
mic wasn't on for three minutes. So, um,
anyway, we're in Kanto 29. Her words
were done, but without interruption, she
sang like an enamored woman. Thus,
teto picata. And just as nymphs who used
to walk alone among the woodland
shadows, some desiring to see and some
to flee to flee the sun. So she moved
countercurren as she walked along the
riverbank and following her short
footsteps with my own steps. I matched
her pace. Her steps of mine together did
not sum 100 when the bank still parallel
so curved about that I was facing east.
Nor had we gone much farther on that
path. And when she turned fully round
toward me and said, "My brother, look
and listen." And I saw a sudden radiance
that swept across the mighty forest on
all sides. And I was wondering if
lightning had not struck. But since when
lightning strikes it stopped at once,
while that light lingering increased its
force, within my mind I asked, "What
thing is this?" And through the
incandescent air there ran sweet melody
at which just indignation made me rebuke
the arrogance of Eve. Because where
earth and heaven were obedient, a
solitary woman just created found any
veil at at all beyond endurance. If she
had been devout beneath her veil, I
should have savored those ineffable
delights before and for a longer time.
While I moved on, completely wrapped
among so many first fruits of eternal
pleasure and longing for still greater
joys, the air before us altered
underneath the green branches, becoming
like an ardent fire. And now the sweet
sound was distinctly sung. Oh virgin
sacks, if I have ever for your sake
suffered vigil, cold, and hunger, great
need makes me and treat my recompense.
Now Helon must pour its fountains for
me. Uranium must help me with her choir
to put in versus things hard to
conceive. Not far beyond we made out
seven trees of gold, though long stretch
of air between those trees and us had
falsified their semblance. But when I
drawn so close that things perceived
through mingled senses which delude did
not, now they were nearer lose their
real features. The power that offers
reason matter judged those trees to be
what they were candalabra. And what
those voices sang to be hosana.
The upper part of those fair candles
flamed more radiantly than the midmon
moon shines at wit midnight in an
untroubled sky. Well full of
astonishment
I turned to my good Virgil. But he only
answered me with eyes that were no less
amazed than mine. Then I looked at the
extraordinary things that were moving
toward us, but so slowly that even
brides just wed would move more quickly.
The woman chided me. Why are you only so
eager to behold the living lights and
not in seeing what comes after them?
Then I saw people following those
candles as if behind their guides and
they wore white whiteness that in this
world has never been to the water to my
left reflected flames and it reflected
to my left hand side by gaze into it as
in a mirror. When I was at a point along
my shore, where all that thundered me
from them was water, I stayed my steps
in order to see better, and I could see
the candle flames move forward, leaving
the air behind them colored like the
strokes a painters brush might have
described, so that the air above that
retinue was streaked with seven bands in
every hue of which the rainbows made and
Dillius girdled. These penants stretched
far back beyond my vision. As for the
width they filled, I judged the distance
between the outer ones to be 10 paces.
Beneath the handsome sky have described
24 eldest elders moved on two by two and
they had wreaths of lilies on their
heads and all were singing. You among
the daughters of Adam, Benedicta are and
may your beauties blessed be eternally.
After the flowers and the other fresh
plants facing me along the farther shore
had seen those chosen people disappear.
Then as in heaven star will follow star.
The elders gone four animals came on and
each of them had green leaves as its his
crown. Each had six wings as plumage and
those plumes were full of eyes. They
would be very like the eyes of Argus
were his eyes alive. Reader, I'm not
squandering more rhymes in order to
describe their forms since I must spend
elsewhere. But I can't be l lavish here.
But read Ezek Ezekiel, for he has drawn
those animals approaching from the north
with wings and cloud and fire, he
painted them. And just as you will find
them in his pages, such were they were
except that John's with me as to their
wings. With him Jon disagrees. The space
between the four of them contained a
chariot triumphal in two wheels tied to
a griffin's neck and drawn by hip. His
wings stretched upward framed the middle
band with three bands on each outer side
so that though he cleaved air he left
the band intact. His wings so high that
they were lost to sight. His limbs were
gold as far as he was burred the rest of
him was white mixed with blood red. Not
only did no chariot so handsome glad in
Rome's Africanis or Augustus himself,
even the son's own cannot match it, the
sons which gone astray was burned to
cinders because earth offered up her p
pious prayers when Job in ways not known
to us was just. Three circling women
then advancing danced at the right
wheel. The first of them so red that
even in flame she'd not be noted. The
second seemed as if her flesh and bone
were fashioned out of emerald. The third
seemed to be nearly fallen snow. And now
the white ones seemed to lead them. Now
the red, and from the way in which the
leader chanted, the others took their
pace, now slow, now rapid.
Upon the left, four other women dressed
in crimson danced, depending on the
cadence of one of them with three eyes
in her head. Behind all the group I have
described, I saw two elders, different
in their dress, but like in manner,
Grafe and Doras. The first seemed to be
one of the disciples of great
Hypocrates, whom nature made for those
who are her dearest living beings. The
other showed an opposite concern. His
sword was bright and sharp, and even on
this near side of the river, I felt
fear. Then I saw four of humble aspect.
And when all the rest had passed, a lone
old man, his features keen advanced as
if in sleep. The clothes these seven
wore were like the elders in the first
file, except that these had no garlands
of liies around their brow. Instead,
roses and other red flowers wreath their
heads. One seeing them less closely
would have sworn that all of them had
flames above their eyebrows. And when
the chariot stood facing me, I heard a
bolt of thunder and it seemed to block
the path of that good company which
halted there its emblems in the lead.
>> Okay, so now Beatus has arrived and with
arrival there is a parade. Okay, what we
call a triumph. Okay, model of Rome, the
Roman triumph. And um so Beatus is
coming and uh when we come back from the
break we will we'll see if these
predictions are correct and spoiler
alert none of them are correct. Okay.
All right. So uh so so we'll take a
break and come back. Okay.
>> Okay. Good afternoon. So we have a
special guest and Carol will introduce
him.
So, um, I'm delighted to have Renee
Newman from Yening Academy here with us
today. Um, I've never met him, but he
has so kindly agreed to come here to
read the Italian um, part of the of
Dante to us um, as a friend of Melania,
who is my um, second son Damian's um,
Latin teacher. And so, thank you to
Melania as well, who is on a flight
right now. Um Renee um is a on full
scholarship to do Yenching Academy and
is a graduate of King's College in
London in international affairs. He's
also president for European Guanhi which
is um a youth think tank on EU Chinese
issues which he's passionate about and I
know um he also speaks um multiple
languages is from multiple parts of the
world and very much a reflection of our
class here. Um I I would just I I'm just
so curious to hear how Italians and you
you're tus
Tuskan. How do tuskkins and Italians
study Dante? Just tell us a little bit
about it and later um we'll we'll have
you read some passages so that we can
get into the zone with um an Italian
reading. Dante, thank you.
>> Thank you so so much, Carol. Um so yeah,
I mean Dante is maybe if
it's the highlight of our syllabus of
Italian literature and we start studying
it when we're very young. So starting
from like our when we're nine or 10 and
uh and it really makes well make up
makes up a huge part of the syllabus
until we're like until we graduate
actually in for you know in in high
school. So um for almost 10 years we
studied it for almost 10 years and we go
through all of it multiple times. Wow.
>> And uh and yeah and especially in
Tuscanany I think we also attribute even
more importance to it than in other
regions of course
>> because we feel even closer to it. Um,
and yeah, um, it's always a pleasure to
read in. So, thank you so much for being
invited.
>> How's the language of Dante similar or
different to how Tuscans speak today?
>> So, um, it is interesting because it's
not definitely not the language that we
speak today. It's a bit different. Uh,
there's some words that we would
wouldn't use today. It's like we can
understand them and maybe some old
people might use words that are a bit
more similar to some sometimes a bit
more uh what we consider formal
>> uh but they're actually you know um in
some way more similar to to to the
language that Dante uses but at the same
time
>> um you know uh there's also many words
that we need to look up sometimes
because they're really different from
from the Italian that we speak today but
at the same time it's also very
important to remember that the Italian
that we speak today in Italy. So,
Italian really is is a construct. It's
not really um a language that always
existed, right? So, it's um the Italian
that we know today is only the like an
extension of the Tuscan dialect. Oh,
wow. That was imposed onto all the other
regions because every Italy was divided
until very late in history compared to
other European countries until 1861. So
um uh it was then that because of
unification they had to choose one
dialect to kind of dominate over all the
other.
>> So it's like pongua in
>> it's like basically pretty much like
ponua and and they chose the the
language of Dante actually they Dante
was the reason like the fact that Dante
had written in that language in Tuscan
>> uh was the reason that and also actually
because there's different types of task.
So it was actually the type that the
Dante brought in that they picked as the
the reason why they picked our dialect
as the like as Italian pretty much to be
the language of the country.
>> Amazing.
>> Yeah. Uh so [laughter]
>> and definitely there are some words that
I think we as Tuscans understand are
like more uh it's easier for us to
understand than other regions for sure
because there are some words in even our
more than like some there's some still
um regional words that we only in Tuscan
we use and that Dante also uses that in
other regions maybe they're a bit less
common. Yeah.
>> Okay. Wonderful.
>> Yeah. I have a lot of questions uh Renee
but my first question is how do you feel
about Dante? Do you like the divine
comedy?
>> Oh, I love it. I love it. Yeah.
>> Why?
>> Well, because it is um
regardless of one's religion, because of
course we know it's a very religious
text, but regardless of one religion, it
has so much historical significance and
it it encapsulates so many important uh
episodes of like Italian history, but
also European history. uh and um I
believe really it is it is uh it should
be taken for much much beyond you know
it's just a religious significance like
also yeah historical but also it's um I
I think it's it's it's it transcends so
many fields and disciplines I think and
it's it's so important
>> um so when you say religious
significance do you mean that this is
primarily a Christian text is that what
you mean
>> well I mean the I think the vision of
you know hell purgatory free and heaven
is definitely I think more it can be
more associated more with Christianity
than maybe other religions like Buddhism
we're like that also maybe like we can
also of course draw some comparisons
with other religions but the way certain
environments in the afterlife are you
know described so accurately in the
divine comedy I think like um they are
they do feature a lot of um you know
characteristics of Christianity
definitely
>> um So in school, how is divine comedy
taught? So you do 10 years of it and
then is there a final examination where
you're tested on certain aspects of of
divine comedy or
>> So um it sometimes is in the final exam.
So every every year the uh Ministry of
Education chooses certain topics for the
final examination and sometimes they do
choose to feature some parts of course
not all of it because you know how long
it is but um they do uh choose to
feature them and and you know have some
parts where they test students about
their knowledge of it. Um but not always
not always but we do have uh like oral
examination written examination
throughout the year about that not
necessarily the final one. Um, do you
read the entire poem or just aspects of
it?
>> We read the entire poem. At least that's
what the syllabus
um what wants us to do. But then um well
sometimes they the syllabus is also very
long in Italian literature. Uh and but
but yes we we read uh at least like 70
or 80% of it if if
>> so for in you you all read.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We we do read
all of it. Yeah. Um and are you asked to
memorize the the poem or do you just
read it?
>> Uh we sometimes really the thing is like
even this and also relating to your
previous question it depends sometimes
on the teacher's own method. So there is
there is some part of the syllabus that
is like um compulsory for the whole
country but at the same time for example
this kind of whether we have to learn it
by heart or not depends on on each
teacher's method. Uh in my case um our
teachers wanted us to read to memorize
the most important parts. So like at the
beginning uh you know like the start
like the the starting the ending and
then some some of what what we we
consider to be like some of the most
important passages and um and yeah but
now I wouldn't be able to it's been a
long time I wouldn't be able to to
>> and what is your favorite part of the
vine comedy? Do you have a section you
you particularly enjoy?
Well, h is it too like cliche to say the
like heaven perfumey or like actually
I think even like the he like hell also
has like a lot of parts that I really
enjoyed. That's a good question. I'm not
I'm not sure. I think there's there's
there's many parts that I really really
enjoyed. Um but also it's it's been a
while now. So like it's been many years
since
>> Okay. Um this is going to be a hard
question but I'm really curious. Um, are
there any outstanding questions or
controversies
um that have plagued educators about the
divine comedy? Are there any like
outstanding theological or literary
questions? And Italian just argue about
this all the time.
>> Mhm. Well, I believe I mean some people
think that like that they were always
struck since since it was composed by
how specific it is on certain very very
tiny details that you know usually um
there's like all types of theories on
how he man like Dante managed to um come
up with or like even like you know s
such specific you know like uh
nitty-gritty like details and and Um so
some people think that it was a dream so
that and the dream that he like
remembers very vividly when he wakes up.
So to such an extent that he can
actually describe s you know so so so
well other people I mean think that he
actually did this uh this this journey
uh that he actually he actually he
actually went there
>> um and other people of course they say
of course it's all an invention but it
is I think there is a consensus that it
is incredible how specific uh it is
sometimes and and how you know and it's
really hard Because sometimes you're
like, you know, when you have to make up
a story, um, you know, it's like, oh,
it's like, I mean, it's so easy to just
invent like to make up anything, right?
But it's not when it comes to details,
right? Actually, to make up a story with
so many details is not an easy feat.
>> Yeah.
>> And he managed to do this.
>> So, so I'll tell you this where uh for
most of my life, I'm 50. for I think
like for 45 years of my life 46 I was a
very ardent atheist I refused to believe
in God an explanation for everything and
I read Divine Comedy I'm like God exists
because without God there's just no way
he could have written this so Divine
Comedy brought me to God because again I
can't explain what's going on without
the idea of God. Okay. But so that's one
um controversy like like how did he
create this and something that we
struggle also in this class? What what
are some other controversies or
questions?
Well, um I believe that what one one
aspect that is also very important that
failed to me uh they failed to mention
uh earlier was is that is the
psychological aspect as well because
this is not just significant for um in
in terms of history and in terms of
events because we we have other sources
for for that right we have historical
sources uh that are even I mean more
reliable sometimes than you know some
something that many people believe to be
a completely madeup
uh you know story. But what what is
striking and what is uh you know like
inequivocably like a um you know like a
super variable source in the sense uh is
that the divine comedy shows what the
mentality of that uh you know that age
was and um and also between all these
like factions you know the gui the
gelini
>> uh and the hate of like and also set the
values really because the fact that I
mean of course these are Dantis values
But they do serve as an embodiment of
think of like of like the the the the um
what what later we would be called the
zeitgeist, right? like the sort of like
that of that that time
>> and like the um you know the that
embodiment of the values of of that of
that of that moment in history and with
all of the different factions uh and and
um and and the fact that it's ranked in
such a specific way, right? Like the who
goes into like which circle of hell.
Yeah. And it's it's really like a
ranking of like what's the least the
least worst thing and the like the worst
thing
>> and then and then then and then in in
heaven it's like the from like the
they're all saints of course and they're
all but but then uh you know there's
also a ranking very specific ranking we
have so many drawings as well with the
with all the layers and everything
>> right um what do you think is the main
message of the vine comedy?
Well, um the main the message might
sound I think well about it's about
judgment everything like right it's like
I think uh judgment is such an important
part of it because and it's is it's not
you know it's not um a type of judgment
that is temporary like in maybe Buddhism
uh it is a judgment that is permanent um
or except in in the case of purgatory I
guess because and the one the one that
we read today that's the only non
non-permanent and one but in hell and in
heaven you know the souls are going to
be there forever for eternity. Um
so um it is it is striking and it is a
strong message. Um at the same time
though uh if we think about um well it
it is definitely about um and many
historians also agree on this uh a way
of certainly or at least at that time to
um have to to persuade people to behave
better
>> um because it would and and um beside
like really I think and it definitely
transcends just the Christian beliefs
you know it's like it contains many
Christian beliefs but it is so you know
uh all encapsulating that that it it is
it definitely transcends this
>> um so today we're we're going to read uh
kantos 30 31 32 33 of purgatory these
are the last four kantos of purgatory
how familiar are you with these four
kantos
>> I studied them but like a lot long ago
so I'll try my best to read them as as
best I can
>> okay and and I mean um I don't want to
be presumptuous But these four counts
are pretty confusing, right?
>> Mhm.
>> Like they are like really troubling,
confusing. It doesn't really fit into
the larger framework vine comedy.
>> Uh is that fair to say?
>> Well, uh the purgatory is we actually
know this in uh in in you know, we we
say in high school and when we study it
that it is the purgatory is actually the
trickiest one. that is it's it's
trickier than both hell and heaven
>> um because of all its nuances and um and
definitely yeah the hardest one to
understand and the hardest one to read
as well in terms of language that he
uses.
>> Okay. So um this is one one of four
hardest cantos of Divine Comedy. Is that
fair to say?
>> Well yeah sure for sure.
>> Okay. Well then that we'll do it guys.
Okay. this afternoon, collectively,
we're gonna figure out what these four
candles are saying. Okay? All right. So,
and you can tell us if we're just crazy
or not. Okay? [laughter] But we're gonna
do it. Okay? Have faith, guys. We're
going to try it. We're going to try to
figure out what these four cantos are
doing. All right? So, um let's start.
Okay. So, to start, I want to
um explain what's going on. So, remember
that Dante has climbed up the Mount
Perator. He has not
And the Garden of Eden, Beatric is
coming. And Beatrice comes with a
parade, right? This is something called
the tri church triumphant.
Church
triumphant.
And this is opposed to the church
militant. Okay. So the church triumphant
is heaven.
Okay. The victory of the church to come.
The church militant is the church on
earth. The victory that must be fought.
Okay. The victory that must be achieved
in order achieve heaven. And the basic
structure for the um um triumph uh sorry
the parade is something called the Roman
triumph. Okay. A Roman triumph is what
happens is like a great conqueror like
Julius Caesar or Cypio or Pompei they go
overseas and they con cover a great deal
of territory and to celebrate they come
to the streets of Rome and this is like
the biggest thing in Rome okay this is
this is like bigger than the Super Bowl
in America it's bigger than the World
Cup and so the idea is through the
streets of Rome they're going to parade
all the way to the temple of Jupiter
And uh the point of the triumph is to
show the greatness of the victory. So um
and they also provide some his history
as to the place what the people are
like. Um so it's a celebration of the
victory and that's that's exactly what's
happening here when Petus comes. She's
coming with the with the church
triumphant. It's a huge parade and it's
to highlight the glory of Christianity.
Um, so Beatatrice comes in a chariot, a
two- wheel chariot.
Okay, that's Beatatrice. And this is so
at the end of at the at the very end of
this procession of the triumph, the
great conqueror, uh, the general is on a
chariot being pulled and the griffin,
the griffin is what pulls
uh, Beatatric. The griffin uh as you
know it is basically a lion and an eagle
joined together. Okay, basically a head
is an eagle, the body is a lion. And a
lot of scholars because like what's what
what we what we'll be reading is
something that's very allegorical,
right? A lot of scholars believe that
the griffin it represents Jesus
because Jesus is considered to be both
lion and eagle. Um, and the cherid is
meant is um meant to represent the
church. Okay? And I don't know better,
so I I will assume they're correct.
Okay? So, keep this in mind. The griffin
is supposed to represent the Jesus. The
church is supposed to represent the
church. Um, and um, these four candles
are extremely troubling. And I had to do
some research before teaching this. And
one really important one really good
source for Dante, his name is Robert
Hollander. I'm sure there are better
sources in Italian. I don't speak
Italian so I don't I don't I'm not able
to understand what what what they're
saying. Okay. But Robert Hollander used
to be at Princeton. He's probably
America's most famous Dante scholar, but
he was at Princeton and then he started
this website uh called Dante Lab at
Dark, the Dark Dante project that gives
you insight into all the scholarship of
Dante. And we're going to read a couple
of actually uh footnotes from Robert
Hollander. Okay.
>> Okay. So So let's read a couple couple
footnotes.
>> Okay.
Sorry about that.
>> No worries.
>> Okay. All right. this one or the other
one first?
>> Yeah. So, so, so let's let's read this
first, okay? And it shows you the depth
>> of scholarship as well as the intricacy
of um Don's craftsmanship. Okay? So,
>> Beatatrice died in June of 1290. It is
now either the end of March or early
April of 1300 and thus about 2 months
fewer than 10 years since she died. If
the act
>> Okay. So, so he, so this is this is
scholars talking about the day that
Dante climbs up Mount Burgatory and
meets Beatatrice. Okay. At what day does
this happen? Keep on going.
>> If the action of the poem indeed did
begin in Dante's mind on Friday
25th of March 1300, this day is
Wednesday 30th of March 1300. Literally
a perfect day, a 10 composed of three
threes.
for a recent study of the numer
numerological aspects of Beatric Se
Carlo Vete D.
>> Yeah. So, so do you see how perfectly
this is constructed? Okay. Dante is
conscious of numbers. He thinks that
numbers are divine in nature. Three is
as we know a particularly divine number.
There are three 33 kantos in um and um
these three different sections and he
uses turs right. Okay. So three is
particularly divine number and you can
see that the meeting with Beatatrice is
a divine day. Okay. Um
>> and um just I guess this is um Beatric's
number in Vita Nova Dante's other poem
and her number is nine or 3 squared.
>> That's right. That's right. So so Donnie
is very mathematical he's very conscious
of numerology. Okay let's go to to the
next um
>> note. Okay. So this is a procession of
the church triumphant and and it's
structured in a certain way. Um c can
you just read it?
>> Sure. Um the first 24 books of the old
testament. The second the four gospels
Matthew, Mark, Luke and John. The third
one griffin. The fourth three
theological virtues faith, hope and
love.
Fifth four cardinal virtues prudence,
fortitude, temperance and justice. The
sixth, two authors of book of acts and
major epistles Luke and Paul. Seventh,
four authors of lesser epistles, Peter,
James, John, Jude. The eighth one
apocalypse, John. A total of 43.
>> Okay, so um it's 43, but remember
there's Beatatrice, right? So that's
one. So that's one that's 44. And then
overhead um over them are 100 angels.
You have 144. Does anyone know why 144
is a very special number in
Christianity?
>> Tribes in Israel?
>> Yes. Right.
>> 12* 12.
>> Yes.
>> What else? I forgot.
>> Yes. But that's that's exactly correct.
Okay. Okay.
>> So, um they say at the end of days
144,000 will ascend to heaven. Okay.
These these are the 12 tribes of of
Israel.
>> All right. So again, you see how
meticulous and precise Dante is with
numbers. This is not accidental by the
way, okay? You can't possibly just, you
know, make this up and then oops, it it
aligns. No, no, he is intentional about
this. And there and there are these
numbers um for scattered throughout the
divine comedy. Okay? So you can
literally just spend your entire life
just analyzing the numerology of the
divine comedy. We're not going to do
that uh because this is this is an angel
class and we're much more concerned
about the themes. Yeah. Yes, Edward.
>> It's just a very small comment but also
the 4 + 3 is seven and seven in
numerology is a very like completion
number.
>> Yeah, exactly. I mean like um you can
make entire diagrams um on this. Okay.
And and so when so there are these all
these uh literary paradoxes in Divine
Comedy, but there also all these
mathematical puzzles in Divine Comedy.
If you just assemble them together, it
reveals a greater truth. Again, uh we're
not going to do that because it's quite
exhausting. Um but it just shows you the
depth of um the level construction in
Divine Comedy. And again, um this class,
it's meant to be the beginning of a long
journey. And I hope that uh in the
future you guys will refer to scholars
like Robert Hollander uh in your
journey. Okay. So I'm providing you one
textual reading but others will provide
you with others and it's up to you to
come up with your own appreciation. So
let's go back to um Kanto 29. Okay. And
I want to go go look at the lines 22 to
30. Okay. So um um
uh Carol, could you read uh 22 to 30?
>> Okay.
And through the incandescent air there
ran sweet melody at which just
indignation made me rebuke the arrogance
of Eve. Because where earth and heaven
were obedient, a solitary woman just
created found any veil at all beyond
endurance. If she had been devout
beneath her veil, I should have savored
those ineffable delights before and for
a longer time.
>> Okay. What is paradoxical about these
lines? Why am I Why am I singling this
section out? What's a paradox here?
Where are they?
>> They're in the Garden of Eden.
>> In the Garden of Eden. Yes. Uh Damen,
>> Eve was banished from the Garden of
Eden. So why is she here?
>> She's not here. Yeah. But what is Donnie
doing right now?
>> Imagining her. Imagining a woman that is
there.
>> What is his emotional state?
>> Super excited and happy to see about to
see their teacher. But
>> what's the word in here?
That tells us how he feels.
>> I should have savored or like
>> No, the emotion.
>> Indignation. Yeah, just indignation.
Okay. Indignation. He's angry. Why is
this a paradox?
Indignation.
Yeah. Why? Why are you angry? Right. You
should be happy. You should just focus
on the here and now. You just focus on
enjoying yourself. Why are you
complaining about what Eve did? I mean,
isn't all forgiven?
Right? This is a paradox here.
Why should he not be angry? Uh Anna
>> angry. Maybe he finally went to the
Garden of Eden to see how beautiful it
is and to be mad at Eve. Like why would
you forsaken all this? That's why he has
the just Indian nation.
>> That's what he says. But I'm trying to
figure out why he's
>> shouldn't
>> Well, he shouldn't be angry because he's
just been through the terrorists, right?
He's been for the terrorists of wrath.
He his his anger should be purged from
him. But he goes to the Garden of Eden
and he's looking around. He says this
angry at what we've lost.
>> He's rebuking arrogance, which is hope
and free will in a way or I don't know
there there's a paradox here. I don't
know if I can.
>> Yeah. Yeah. There there's lots of
paradoxes here, right? Okay. Does that
make sense? Okay. And and so what what I
will argue is to unpack this paradox,
you need to figure out what these four
candles are. Okay? So so remember this
paradox. It makes absolutely no sense
that he's been in the Garden of Eden.
He's about to meet Beatric and now he's
pissed off about Eve eating the um fruit
which has which caused him to be
banished from the Garden of Eden. Okay.
What why is it like at at your happiest
time you're still angry, right? I mean,
isn't the point of being happy to let go
of your anger and just embrace
um your your your joy? Okay. All right.
>> Oh, I I I don't know if I'm skipping
ahead. Um but there's this um
a concept of Felix Koopa,
which is um it is essential for this
fall to happen, for us to get to
Jesus, [laughter]
>> right? But in the other case, he should
be he shouldn't be angry at all. Right?
He just thinks, well, you know, we were
redeemed at the end. We we're in the
Garden of Eden now. Anyone can come. So
Allah is forgiven. So why is he angry,
right? It's all part of the divine plan.
Um Eve had to eat that fruit Jesus so
that Jesus could come so that we could
all be redeemed. And now all has
happened. So instead of like being angry
at Eve, why don't you celebrate Eve,
right? and just like forgive Eve. But
instead, he is angry. But not only that,
but what is his indation? What type is
it? What what's the word he uses to
describe his anger?
>> Just.
>> It's just. Okay. It's righteous.
It is justice. I should be angry. I am
right to be angry at Eve.
This is a paradox for us. Yes. I think
it's also that um if Betrice had died in
childbirth, it was Eve's punishment is
that all women should feel pain during
child birth and it's especially that
that made her die. I think he's angry as
well because she found any veil beyond
endurance and life is one of the veil.
>> So, it's that he's almost angry that Bri
is dead. Even though I'm meeting her
now, it's such a pain that it's not in
the real world.
>> That's a great point. Yeah, I completely
forgot that. But Beatric did die in
childbirth and Eve was punished uh by
God. Um and the punishment was to have
painful child birth, right? And it is
you know um the greatest pain in the
world. Okay. It is hell on earth. Um so
um but uh Rene I want to ask you that
the translation just ination is this a
correct translation?
Um I am yeah I was actually surprised
that they translated one because just is
would be more like juto or um used back
then I guess it could also be said but
uh one is like is like a good it's more
like
>> okay
>> a good type of a good type of
indignation
>> right
>> uh zo for example is also like um I mean
I think back then definitely it meant
indignation now it has a bit of a
different meaning is less negative than
indignation.
>> It's it's more like Yeah, that's
actually that's actually what it is.
>> Um but but but back then of course
certain words that we could still use
now have had a different meaning of
course.
>> Okay. So I I want to confirm. Okay.
>> Menobal. Alan Menobal. And he's one of
like dozens of translators of like
Dante. Okay. Um but what he's what what
he's saying is that um uh Dante
thinks that it is just for him to think
that Eve was arrogant and to rebuke her
arrogance. Is this a correct
translation?
Um
I I would yeah I would say so like um on
like on at which
one it's just as we said indignation
yeah made me rebuke yeah um I uh is also
an interesting like word for us to hear
in Italian is like when when someone is
well adito now has also different
meaning But alimementoto um definitely
sounds like I mean back then it would be
more closer to arrogance for sure or or
>> and and so the tone and the language it
uh conveys anger as an emotion. Is that
correct?
>> Yes. Uh it's it's it's it's some some
kind of I think maybe passionate anger
like as in dementoto uh it's it it has
the same ardent
>> ardent it has the same emotion as fire
basically right
>> uh so it is it it this definitely
conveys passion it conveys a strong
feeling
>> like a you know fiery feeling
>> all right okay so so again like so the
there's the paradox there okay like why
are you so angry now now you're the
garden of Eden okay isn't this all part
of the vine plan, right? Shouldn't you
be thankful uh for for and plus you're
not a woman, right? You're a guy. So, so
what are you complaining about? I mean,
like um so so there's lots of paradoxes
here. All right, let's go to count 30.
Okay. Um and uh again um these next four
canours are just really troubling for
scholars as well students of Dante.
>> I'll do 12 maybe and then you'll do 12.
Okay.
When the first heaven seven stars had
halted, those stars that never rise or
set, that are not veiled, except when
sin be clouds our vision. Those stars
that there made everyone aware of what
his duty was, just as the bear below
brings helmsmen home to harbor. Then the
truthful band that had come first
between the griffin and the seven stars
turned toward that chariot as toward
their peace. And one of them as if sent
down from heaven him aloud veni sponsor
de liibano three times and all the
others echoed him.
Turn it up. Yes.
for
sponsor.
Just as the blessed at the final summons
will rise up ready each out of his grave
singing with new clothed voices
allelujah. So from the godly chariot
eternal life's messengers and ministers
arose 100 stood advoc
Advocenis
all of them cried Benedictus quenis and
scattering flowers upward and around
Benedict.
I have at times seen all the eastern sky
becoming rose as day began and seen
adorned in lovely blue the rest of
heaven and seen the sun's face rise so
veiled that it was tempered by the mist
and could permit the eye to look at
length upon it. Though within a cloud of
flowers that were cast by the angelic
hands and then rose up and then fell
back outside and in the chariot, a woman
showed herself to me above a white whale
veil. She was crowned with olive boughs.
Her cape was green, her dress beneath
flame red.
within her presence I had once been used
to feeling trembling wonder dissolution
but that was long ago still though my
soul now she was veiled could not see
her directly by way of hidden force that
she could move I felt the mighty power
of old love As soon as that deep force
had struck my vision, the power that
when I had not yet left my boyhood, had
already transfixed me, I turned around
and to my left, just as a little child,
afraid or in distress, will hurry to his
mother anxiously to say to Virgil, "I am
left with less than one drop of my blood
that does not tremble. I recognize the
signs of the old flame.
presents.
Okay, stop. Okay, so um Beatrice is
revealing her herself. She's still
veiled, but she is now in the presence
of Dante. And it's been many years since
Dante last saw Beatatrice. Uh 20 years
maybe. And but his soul still shakes.
Okay. He's not shaking, but his show his
soul is still shaking. Um Rene, let me
ask you while you're reading this. Okay.
Uh and the the climax of course is like
when Dante sees Beatus again for the
first time, and this is the moment we've
been waiting for the entire time. Okay.
We've been through hell. We've been for
proator and this is the moment that
Dante's been waiting for. We've all been
waiting for. How did you feel while
you're reading this? What emotions were
you were in you when you were reading
this?
>> Well, I think Oh, sorry. Yeah. I
>> Yeah, it's I think
well it's he spends you know um like so
many lines talking about just that like
the emotion of when when he sees her and
is it is um I think there would be no
other way of making it convey such a
strong
um feeling that is not just you know
sheer
it's more than just sheer joy or sheer
you know surprise or I think there is no
single were like not even just a set of
uh short set of words to convey it. And
that's why so many lines are spent on
it. And even like some um you know like
analogies um you know when when uh like
when when when he compares it with like
boyhood for example
um and uh and like
uh and then he he says he also talks
about a little like just as a little
child afraid or in distress, right?
It's it's it's so strong and it's Yeah.
Yeah.
>> Okay. So, this is really when all his
emotions converge together, right? His
greatest fear, his greatest excitement,
his greatest um happiness,
uh his greatest sadness, they all
converge together and it is such an
overwhelming emotion. He's never felt
like this before. Uh his entire soul,
it's vibrating. It's shaking to its
core. And what's the first thing he
wants to do? Turn to Virgil.
>> He wants you to turn to Virgil. You
understand? That's that's how much he
loves Virgil. Okay? He loves Virgil. I
know I've been talking to trash about
Virgil this entire time, but he still
Dante still loves Virgil as a father.
Okay. So, he wants to turn to Virgil.
And what should Virgil do in response?
>> Comfort him.
>> Right. hug him and says, "Dante, I'm
with you. Go ahead. We came all the way
here, right, for health, for purgatory,
and now I want to be with you in your
moment of your greatest triumph."
>> And I will be with you.
Um, okay. So, so, so, so, so, so maybe
we won't translate until certain
section. Okay. Um, yeah, sounds good.
Line 49. But Virgil had deprived us of
himself. Virgil the gentlest father.
Virgil he to whom I gave myself for my
salvation. And even all our ancient
mother lost was not enough to keep my
cheeks though washed with dew from
darkening again with tears.
>> Okay. So so stop. Okay. So Rene, could
you translate for us the these next six
lines and tell us these when you when
you speak it, what emotions do you feel?
>> Mhm.
for
it's it's it's like as if he was like
it's more than like um praising him.
It's more it's it's like as if he was
talking about like yeah the person he
loves the most actually. It's almost as
if he was talking to him as if he was
Beatric.
>> Yeah. No, I mean, yeah, that's exactly
it. I I I think the words, the emotions
is Dante loves Virgil. Okay. There's
actually no doubt about it.
Where is Virgil? Where is he?
Uh Fred,
>> I was just doing a sign for like self
integration where
Dante, he's left uh Virgil has left
Dante completely and Dante has
integrated him as completely as he can.
>> But I mean like I mean we were expecting
some sort of resolution, right? Some
sort of confrontation between Virgil and
Beatrice. some sort of conflict where
Don has to choose between Virgil and
Beatatrice or even maybe a happy ending
where Beatatrice
um welcomes Virgil to the heavens and
Virgil's given a choice but he's just
completely disappeared. He's run away.
That's not bad writing, right? What's
going on here?
>> Who's talking then?
>> Donnie is talking.
Yes.
Right. Dante felt Virgil beside him. So
he turns to Virgil to say, "I'm I've
never been sover nervous in my life,
Virgil." And Virgil's gone. He just
disappeared.
Well, first of all, why is Virgil gone?
He has accomplished his mission to bring
Dante to Beatric. So now he has like no
purpose to be here.
>> Yeah. But if you've accomplished your
your mission, what what's the least
thing you would expect?
>> He wants someone to thank him.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you, Virgo, for taking Donnie
through heaven and hell. Yes.
>> Um, so previously we were hypothesizing
that he might be a little bit jealous. I
feel like some of the times if you're
jealous, you don't actually want to be
in a scene and then you just choose to
leave it behind and then just not see
the scene.
>> Dante loves Virgil. Does Virgil love
Dante?
I I I think he loves Dante.
I think he does.
>> Okay.
>> They climbed on Satan.
>> Yeah. They've been through a lot, man.
They climb on Satan. They've uh been
through purgatory. It's been a lot. Once
that happens to you, two people love
each other. Yes.
I think of like the wedding scenario
where the father brings the bride to the
groom and then he has to go he's like I
hand you over and you know so I feel
like maybe it's that kind of scene too
where he kind of give birth to Dante and
now
>> there's no handover though.
>> Oh okay.
>> He just disappears. He just runs away.
Yes.
>> Yeah. Maybe because uh you know as men
they don't want to say a goodbye. Maybe
they would love to give you a hug. But
actually Virgil I saying he on the one
hand he want to give it a high maybe but
>> let's do the counter factor. Okay let's
just say Virgil stays. What would happen
next?
>> What would happen next? Yeah. Yes. Anna
>> a confrontation with do you want to come
to heaven? No. Oh awkward. Like so then
he just avoids that conversation and
goes away.
>> Yeah. I think what happened is that
Beatrice would say to Virgil, "Virgil, I
want to thank you so much for this. I
came down to limbo and I asked you for a
favor and you so generously and so
selfishly guided Dante through hell and
purgatory and I can't thank you enough
and Virgil was like h right you're kind
of stuck right because now what is going
to say come with us to heaven and and
V's like so he's made the conscious
decision I don't want to go anywhere
near heaven
I
what? Yeah. Yes.
>> I I this reminds me actually of a of a
of a Greek myth of
or Fos and Uridis or yes. you know, when
when like he's uh not supposed to turn
and like when there's actually no like
it is kind of a there's no well in in in
the myth of course he turns and he sees
and and and and she disappears because
the
pact was that for him not to like you
know the deal was for him not to turn uh
and they would live uh you know happily
together after and and uh and uh but but
then he turns he doesn't resist and he's
just about to get out of the cave and Uh
but here actually it is as if um I don't
know I I kind of see a bit of this of
this like kind of like leaving him
without like disappearing with no
goodbye or no like and and and that he's
not even supposed to say to to to to
turn back to him and to to turn behind
once you're in well you you know you're
um like in ascending to to heaven.
You're not supposed to go back and like
heaven is so pure that you're not
supposed to. Right.
>> Okay. I I understand. I understand.
You're saying that Donnie should have
turned his head back and talk to Virgil,
but I'm still trying to figure out why.
>> Shouldn't have. He shouldn't. I think it
was supposed to be like this.
>> Right. I'm trying to figure out why
Virgil's disappeared.
>> Yes. I think it's a reflection of
Denty's um acknowledgement that uh
Virgil is indeed a very thoroughly manly
fatherly figure because a real father uh
effective father is eventually has to
make a very very clean cut in the
father-son relationship in order to send
a son to some some greatness and I think
uh even uh Adant's own father
who kind of uh disappeared from Danty's
life also relatively early in Danty life
I think also gave Danty a kind of
paradigm that his mentor um would send
him onto his journey but you know won't
accompany him all the way down.
>> This is like your father not show up at
your college graduation. Okay, you gradu
from Yale. It's the biggest thing you've
ever accomplished. And your father's
like, I don't want to go because I I
don't want to burden you with uh I I
don't want to make you more dependent on
me. No. No. He No, Virgil just run away,
I guess.
>> Well, I mean, my is like a little bit
similar with him because I believe maybe
Virgil will make Dante feel hesitant.
>> Okay. Okay, guys, stop this. Okay, this
is the wrong direction. Okay,
Edward.
>> It's almost that this moment is so
divine and so beautiful that Virgil but
Virgil's soul is still too dark to be
able to be included in this moment.
>> Yes. Okay. So, it's almost like Virgil's
afraid of the encounter between Dante
and Beatatrice, right? Because remember
how he feels about love is it's one of
control, one of possession, right? He
doesn't actually believe in true love.
He only believes in control. So he
doesn't want to see Beatatrice and
Donnie together because then he
recognizes that true love exists and
it's divine. Uh Anna
>> the one who hates love in a way like so
it will be awkward for him to stand.
>> Yeah. He wrote the Iniad in order to
love right love is a disease. Love can
only lead you to hell.
>> And now Dell
>> And now he's in hell but Donnie is going
to heaven. Love is leading Donnie to
heaven. All right. So, this is
convicting to him. Right. So, rather
than phase the fact that he could be
wrong, he's like, "Screw this. I'm I I'm
I'm going to run away." Okay.
>> All right. What else? So, so that that's
one theory. Yes.
>> How about the you know, I think Betray
stands for love. So, I think that Virgil
stands for reason. Maybe Virgil just so
so fierce. They are just being so scared
by being controlled by love. So, that's
the reason they live. So, so maybe V, as
you point out, Virgil and Beatatric just
like like it's it's like magnets, right?
Like like polarities, right? They just
repel each other. Okay. Um,
but at the same time, Virgil did help be
out, right? So, I think one possible
explanation is like Virgil does not want
to see true love because it just negates
his entire worldview. Okay, that that I
think is a very I I think that that's
the best explanation. Does Virgil want
to go to he want to go to heaven?
We know he doesn't want to go because he
could go at any time and now Beatus is
here and Beatus owes you a favor, right?
So now's the best opportunity in your
life to go to heaven. He's like, "Screw
this. I'm going to go home. I I'm going
to go I'm going to go to hell." Why
would he do that? Why would anyone do
that?
>> Yes, Damian.
>> Because heaven's where true love is. And
Virgil doesn't doesn't want to see that.
>> Who is Virgil most afraid of?
He's afraid of God, right? Why?
>> He wrote the Iniad.
>> Okay, so think about this, okay? God
gave the gift of poetry to Iniad. God
chose you, Virgil. No one else chose
you. And then Virgil was like, I'm gonna
go make a billion dollars doing this.
Okay. So, the last person he wants to
see right now is God. Yes,
>> I want to say I think that the
explanation that we study in Italy or at
least I mean maybe it depends also on
the teacher sometimes interpretations
can also vary but I think it's
complimentary to what we've just said
that um uh Virgil cannot we we at least
we learn that Virgil cannot enter heaven
because heaven is only for the pure and
um and Virgil because I mean as we said
I mean he's he's not only not exter like
people from the outside who who had
already who have already um how do you
say um been judged um cannot cannot
access it. That's what that's at least
the way we learn.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It it's wrong then. Okay.
I'm telling you what you learn what you
learn is wrong because what we learn in
this in this class is there's there's a
man named Rifus, right?
>> Rifus.
He's in heaven. Not only is he in
heaven, but he's one one of the great of
heavens, okay? He's up there with David
and all the great leaders of human
history.
He was born he he was a warrior of the
children empire, right? He was there
during the children war. Therefore, he
could not have been possibly been a
Christian, right? He was not baptized.
He was born about a thousand years
before Jesus.
So, how did he get to heaven?
That that that's that's an interesting
point. Um I also might omit or like not
like fail to remember some some other
parts of our teaching. Um
uh but um I guess he also had uh his own
uh role in in in heaven or like there
might be some reason why he is allowed
and and other people but usually or at
least what they teaches is that yeah
because uh Virgil had no reason to be in
heaven when when uh there was already
someone accompanying because technically
I mean he was not even supposed to be in
purgatory but then he
>> Right. Okay. All right. So um um yeah.
So um what what what we learned in this
class is that Donny's is very clear
about this. What takes you to heaven is
not your belief. It is your actions.
Okay? And it's your actions that reveal
your belief. Right? Because you live a
life of hope um love and faith. Then
that's Christian. It doesn't matter if
you were born before Jesus. And because
you live this life, it means you have
faith in Jesus. Then that faith pathes
you automatically. Okay. Uh um yes,
Edward and Fred.
>> Could it also be like the ultimate
feeling of jealousy for Virgil? Because
I don't know, but I don't think in his
life he had a Beatrice. Did he have a a
true love in his life?
>> Um if he wrote the Inad, obviously not.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Yes. Uh Fred,
>> I think another thing that um is
blocking him from heaven or blocking him
from being at this ceremony was that for
Virgil like the extremes of good and
evil, the extreme of good is about
following the destiny set out by the
gods and piety. And I think for him
there's no piety in heaven because it's
the story is over. The game is over. The
the race is run. So for him it's
impossible for him to conceive of
goodness that can never be not good
because his whole thing with the anid is
fluctuating between following your
destiny and being lazy and following
your destiny and being lazy.
>> Yes. Exactly. So you that's a great
point. Yes. So Virgil can't even
conceive of the idea of heaven. If he
conceives it as heaven, he would he can
basically invert it, right? For him,
heaven would be hell. So he's like, "Why
do I want to go to hell? I'm perfectly
happy in in limbo. That's my heaven
because I'm master of hell. Right? Okay.
So there are many reasons but but but
this is again um a a very important I
like paradox for us. Why does Virgil run
away? Okay. And obviously there are many
different um interpretations. Okay. Uh
let's let let's let's continue.
>> Okay. Line 55. Dante, though Virgil's
leaving you, do not yet weep. Do not
weep yet. You'll need your tears for
what another sword must yet inflict.
Just like an admiral who goes to stern
and proud to see the officers who guide
the other ships, encouraging their
tasks. So on the left side of the
chariot, I turned around when I had
heard my name, which of necessity I
transcribe here. I saw the lady who had
first appeared to me beneath the veils
of the angelic flowers look at me across
the stream.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So Dante is
obviously heartbroken that his father
has run away at the moment of his
greatest happiness. Okay. And now
Beatatrice has come and she's basically
like, "Forget him. He's not important.
Um, you will need everything for the
next challenge." Okay.
How does Dante feel about Beatric right
now?
Uh yes,
>> he might think Beatatrice is very mean.
>> I think so. That's exactly how it feels.
Why? What metaphor tells us that uh
just think that Beatrice is just being
too stern or too mean.
>> Just like an admiral who goes to stern
and
>> Exactly. Right. Right. That's that
that's the out that's a simile, right?
She's just being a boss, right? She's
just being imperious. She she she's she
she's just ordering me about. Okay?
That's how much he loves Virgil. Do you
understand this idea? He loves Virgil so
much that the moment that anyone says
anything bad about Virgil, he gets
really angry. E even if it's coming from
the love of his life, Beatatrice.
Okay. So again, this is meant to be a
tragic moment for Dante.
What Dante wanted more than anything
else is to ascend to heaven with Virgil.
And now Virgil has made his decision to
leave him. Okay. And so
um I I I don't speculate too much, but
um just think of of like what Donn is
trying to do, right? He's trying to
create a new
um paradigm for for for the world. He's
trying to create a new poem for the
world. And to do that, he must displace
Virgil. Does that make sense? Because at
this time in history, everyone's
memorizing the Iniad as today like
everyone in Italy studying the divine
comedy, right? But for him to do that,
he must show you what the problem is
with with the Iniad. But he can't
convince you because it's like the end
is like your mother, your father. Okay?
And so uh he has to construct this
elaborate journey and this elaborate
relationship with Virgil u in order to
show you that at some point um Virgil
must leave you if you are to ascend to
heaven. Okay, does that make sense guys?
All right. Uh let's keep on reading.
>> Line 67. Although the veil she wore down
from her head, which was encircled by
mannervous leaves, did not allow her to
be seen distinctly, her stance, still
regal and disdainful, she continued,
just as one who speaks but keeps until
the end the fiercest parts of speech.
Look here, for I am beatress, I am. How
are you able to ascend the mountain? Did
you not know that man is happy here? My
lowered eyes caught sight of the clear
stream. But when I saw myself reflected
there, such shame weighed on my brow. My
eyes drew back and toward the grass.
Just as a mother seems harsh to her
child. So did she seem to me. How bitter
is the savor of stern pity. Her words
were done. The angel suddenly sang in
domini.
But their singing did not go past Perez
Mayos.
>> Okay. So how is Johnny feeling at this
moment?
Shame.
>> Shame, right? Regret. All he cares about
is the fact that he's lost um Virgil.
Okay. Even Peter saying like, "Focus on
me, Dante." He still can't look at her.
Okay. Um he is just so sad that his
friend Virgil has abandoned him. Okay.
Uh keep on going.
>> Even line 85. Even as snow among the
sapfield trees along the spine of Italy
will freeze when gripped by gusts of the
Slovenian winds. Then as it melts will
trickle through itself. That is if winds
breathe north from shadeless lands. Just
as beneath the flame the candle melts.
So I before I'd heard the song of those
whose notes always accompanied the notes
of eternal spheres was but without tears
and size. But when I heard the sympathy
for me within their gentle harmonies, as
if they'd said, "Lady, why shame him
so?" Then did the ice that had
restrained my heart become water and
breath, and from my breast and through
my lips and eyes they issued, anguished,
still standing motionless upon the left
side of the chariot. She then addressed
the angels who had been compassionate.
"You're awake and never ending day, and
neither night nor sleep can steal from
you one step the world would take along
its way. Therefore, I'm more concerned
that my reply be understood by him who
weeps beyond so that his sorrows measure
matches him. Not only through the work
of the great spheres which guide each
seed to a determined end, depending on
what stars are its companions, but
through the bounty of the godly graces
which showered down from clouds so high
that we cannot approach them with our
vision. He when young was such
potentially that any propensity and any
propensity innate in him would have
prediciously succeeded had he acted. But
where the soil has finer vigor there
precisely when untilled or badly seated
will that terrain grow wilder and more
noxious. My countenance sustain him for
a while. Showing my youthful eyes to
him. I'll let him with me toward the way
of righteousness. As soon as I upon the
threshold of my second age had changed
my life, he took himself away from me
and followed after another. When from
flesh to spirit I had risen and my
goodness and my beauty had grown. I was
less dear to him, less welcome. He
turned his footsteps toward an untrue
path. He followed counterfeits of
goodness which will never pay in full
what they have promised. Nor did the
inspirations I received with which in
dream and otherwise I called him back
help me. He paid so little heed. He fell
so far there were no other means to lead
him to salvation except this to let him
see the people who were lost. For this I
visited the gateway of the dead to him
who guided him above. My prayers were
offered even as I wept. The deep design
of God would have been broken if leaf
had been crossed and he had drunk such
waters but had not discharged the debt
of penitence that's paid when tears are
shed. Okay, so imagine Dante's emotional
state. Okay, he's been thinking that
this is a great wedding feast between
him and Beatric, right? He had to work
so hard to get through Inferno and
through purgatory. And now
um he thinks that Petri will shower
praise on him, right? He's like, "Wow,
you got an A+ on your test. Great job,
man." What is Petric doing instead?
Yes, Damian.
>> Scolding him.
>> Why?
>> Um because after Beatatric died, Dante
married another woman.
>> Um
well, I mean, true.
But would Beatric be angry about that?
What's he angry about?
He's just upset that Dante that Virgil
left. He's crying and like,
>> "Sure, sure." Dante is upset that Virgil
has left. And then Beatric is say, "Hey,
let's get going, man." And then Dante is
kind of shocked because he's expecting
this praise, this love, this adulation
from Beatatrice.
And instead,
um, and and so he falls, he's confused,
he's in shame. The angels fly to Beatric
and says, "Relax, Beatrice." Okay. D's
been through hell. Literally been
through hell. Like, let's give him a
break. And B is like, "You guys shut up,
too." [laughter]
Like,
why is she pissed? Like, like she's
pissed. Why is she pissed?
Because it was her love that caused all
of this that brought him here that got
Virgil in the first place involved with
Dante. So that's not what she's saying
though. That's that's that's not what
she's saying. What's she saying? She's
saying that um when we knew each other,
your love for me stared you on the right
path, but then after I died, you went on
the wrong path.
And that forced me to come to all the
way down to hell to seek Virgil to set
you on the right path. Okay? And I had
to make you go through hell to see the
consequences of your sins. Right. So
what what did Donnie do wrong?
Yes. Julian.
>> Uh I guess trust Virgil that much or
love because I mean in this speech she
is talking about Virgil, right?
>> No no she no like like okay what she
said in the speech is this right? Okay.
When we knew each other, you loved me so
much and I put you on the right path.
Then I died and then you went on the
wrong path. You went the wrong You went
on the path so wrongly had to come down
and ask Virgil to help you put to to set
you on the right path and you had to go
through hell to see the consequences of
what it means to go on the wrong path.
What did you do wrong?
>> And meshed in the wealth and gibs and
all the politics and all of that.
>> Yeah. So that's one possibility, right?
Uh so there are different possibilities.
He married, but then but then like that
makes Beatric seem really petty, right?
Because Petri married someone else. So
what's Donnie going to do? Just like be
chased all his life,
>> right? So I think he's angry about that.
It's possible. Okay. Uh Donnie
participated in internal politics, but
that's just the times. Okay. Yeah. Fred.
So she's I guess she's complaining about
the double standard that he seems to
have set with his love for her that it
was her goodness and beauty while she
was alive that gave him the a good
spark. And she's saying, "Well, I died
and if Dante knew I'd gone to heaven,
how come I'm not even an even bigger
inspiration than before?" Like she's
saying, "My goodness and beauty had
grown and yet I was less dear to him,
less worth." Like I should have been an
even stronger star now that I died. But
it seemed that he needed his hero to to
do it instead.
>> Okay. So So let's continue this. Okay.
This is correct. Okay. But but I I want
I want to elaborate on this. So um when
Beers were alive, what did Donnie write
poetry?
Why?
>> To seduce her or prove his artistic
merit.
>> This is according love tradition, right?
So he's trying to express his love,
forever her love to Beatrice.
After she died, why did he write poetry?
To save himself.
>> To save himself. How?
>> By
channeling all of the spirits of his
hero and his love in order to instruct
the rest of the world,
>> right? In which case, he wouldn't have
to go to hell. In which case, Beatric
wouldn't have to come down to uh hell
and and get Virgin to help him. Right?
Problem solved.
So obviously he did something wrong,
right? So when Beatric was alive, he
wrote poetry to express his love for
Beatatric after she died. Why did he
write poetry? Yes.
>> Probably for fame and power.
>> Exactly. Okay. That's where he went
wrong. He forgot what the point of
poetry was. It's not for fame and power
because you if you did that, who would
you end up who would you end up being?
>> Virgil.
>> Virgil. Okay. Does that make sense,
guys? Okay. And we know because in the
beginning of purgatory,
Dante bec fell in love with his own
shadow, right? And he fell in love with
his shadow so much that uh whenever he
saw his shadow, he was really happy and
he walked really slowly so that the
other shades could see his shadow. Do
you understand this this idea? This is
where Dante went wrong. When you when
she was alive, he could focus all his
attention on her and that's what made
his poetry divine. she died then all he
thought about was competing against his
um fellow poets and proving that he was
the best right and so he started to uh
write poetry in order to prove he's
superior to everyone else and that's
where he went wrong and that's why come
get Virgil to lead him through hell yet
yes
>> no no no I'm finished yeah
>> I I I was I was going to say I think it
was very struck by the fact that he
retakes this analogy of like the mom and
the child.
>> Yes.
>> And I think this analogy precisely I
think um corroborates your point that
>> of this transition from like when when
uh Beatatrice was still alive, they were
kind of equal, right? in the way still
both human beings alive now like
Beatatrice is kind of in a different
sphere and it's as if she was his mom
and uh you know and in the first part
when he's sad about Virgil disappearing
he's like oh like going to like as if go
as as a as a child going to his mom like
crying um because he's afraid but
actually his mom as and so in in that
first analogy the his mom is actually
Virgil But then but then in the second
like when he retakes the analogy it's
it's Beatatrice that hits his mom and so
he's like I am you know like I'm like
your muse and um and and and you lost me
when I died but I you know the fact that
I died and you know and and your faith
shouldn't prevent you from using me
having me as a muse even after my death.
Right.
>> Right.
>> So he lost his faith in some
>> That's right. Exactly. Yes. Okay. Um so
now let me ask you this question.
Why is she doing this,
right?
I mean, wouldn't a better better
strategy
be like to first praise him, right? And
then point out that, oh, you could
improve in this way, right? That that
that's how you how like we're taught to
criticize people, right? Don't do it
directly. Don't scull people. Don't be
angry at that person. first criticize
this person and then maybe towards the
end you're like oh but you know there's
this one little thing
right
why is she just pissed it's like
yes
yes Bruce
>> yeah maybe because you know uh if people
die and they have been prayed by the
family so I think that the Danty just
cannot lie the uh you know uh you can
call it uh I think Danty is try to to
drag drag her legs. Do not let her to go
to heaven because uh yeah because I have
to pick up right she have she has to
pick up
>> why is she pissed at Dante what was she
doing this yes
>> so linked to free will where there's two
option it could like break him and so he
would just take another path or then by
his love for Beatrice he would listen to
her and try to improve on himself
whereas if she would come and just like
loving him there wouldn't be no choice
he would just like love her back whereas
he's conflicted.
>> I I I agree with that, but I'm just
saying like he's been through Inferno
and he's through purgatory already, man.
Why how why does he need to improve
himself? How else can he he improve
himself? Why does he need to improve
himself?
>> Also, like before it was he was seeking
a fake image of Beatric. So now he's
here, he needs a choice again. Whereas
I'm Beatrice now. Do you want to go with
me or do you want to just like because
I'm not the Beatric you thought I was
just go away?
>> Yes. Okay. Exactly. Yes. Yes, Andy.
>> Could it be because he's maybe treating
the the peak of purgatory like the
finish line when the finish line is
gone?
>> Yes, that's what Beatric is saying to
Dante is like this is the beginning,
man. The real challenge is up there. So,
get your head in the in in the right
order. Okay, if you're still stuck on
fame, uh you're not going to be able to
do anything in heaven. Okay, remember
what matters, what brings you, what
brought you here is your love for me. So
focus on that, Dante.
Does that make sense?
But like again, it's it's one of
tactics, right? Like you would I mean
like why why take this tone? Why take
this approach? I mean, you could have
chosen a much more gentle, diplomatic,
softer approach, right? Why choose this
scolding approach like this anger
approach,
right? Yes, Brad, maybe two suggestions
maybe. One to test him and that this is
he's still not completely out of
purgatory. So, he's actually still in
the circle of lust and so he needs to
still feel the heat. And so if she gave
him balm from this heat already before
he had entered the gates of heaven,
she'd be ruining purgatory for him in
this sense.
>> So she can't let up even a tiny bit. And
also, I'm
my mind's not working fast enough, but
I'm thinking there has to be something
of the Rachel and Leia dream in this
interaction where she's saying, "Look,
don't get your like don't get your
knickers in a twist now that you've had
sex with Leia. You know, there's still
seven more years or
>> Yeah. Okay. Anyone else? Yoo.
>> Yeah. Maybe just like asking a friend
out, a girlfriend out and if you get
date and the girl just always
complaining you why you just don't pick
up me earlier and why you always you
know maybe just try to show up.
>> Okay, so so let's think about this.
Okay, so Beatric is scolding Dante and
the angels around her saying like
Beatric Beatric calm down and Beatric is
like shut up man. Why does she do that?
[gasps]
>> Excuse me. She's mad.
>> Yeah. And not only that, but like what?
But why is she mad?
>> She's mad. And it's like I'm right to be
mad. Do you understand? Just in the
nation, right? [laughter]
Just in a nation.
>> Okay.
Yes.
I could be off base here. I wonder um a
poet has a muse and they pour they spend
years and years, don't they? spent so
many years writing uh his love to
Beatric. Beatric in real life. This
moment is their third time of ever
meeting.
>> Yeah. Basically. Yeah.
>> And so does a muse
I I understand she's in heaven. God is
love. She loves him. But does a muse
often love their poets back or are they
just objects of love? And so is it
possible that he's coming up and he's
like, "I love you." And she's like,
"It's third time we went, man." Like got
a long way to go [laughter] till there's
love.
Um,
I I think uh there are multiple factors
at work here, but I I think Beatrice
thinks she deserves Dante's love because
if you're the muse, right, you're the
one who gave Dante this poetry in the
first place. Okay. All right. Uh, yes,
Anna.
>> I wonder if a few reasons. Like, first
of all, like Dante couldn't let go of
the fact that Virgil has left is one
thing. So like basically if I'm the wife
and my husband is mourning over his best
pal guy bro you know homie who kind of
took over like the joy of our wedding
then I'll be pretty pissed because then
I'll be like well I'm the bride and why
is Virgil the homie the center of my
husband's you know heart and then yeah
and then the other one about like going
God is the ultimate one but he's like
the wedding day seems to be hit for him
the end of the thing that will piss me
off too. But oh that's it like the
wedding day is going to be the best day
of my life and now from now on you're
going to go downhill instead of up like
you know then I'll be pretty pissed.
>> Okay. So the fact that Beatatric is
angry at Dante suggests what about
Beatatrice? How does Beatric feel about
Dante
>> all that she cares in a way?
>> She loves him.
>> Yeah. dearly and he's not rep uh yeah
returning that same amount of love. So,
so, so I I know this is hard for us to
appreciate. Okay, what Don is saying
here is that just ination comes from a
place of love.
>> You understand? This is really important
guys. You understand these next four
counts, you need to understand this
idea.
>> Right? Righteous ination comes from a
place of love. Only because you have
love that you get angry. Right?
>> If you're beat, you're like, I don't
really care about this guy. Right?
You're just doing your job. Why are you
angry? And you should hear this.
>> Yeah. I feel like
>> if I'm angry at you, that's because I
love you.
>> Exactly. I think coming from mom and
teachers, you're like, you have such
expectation for your students. And when
they are bright and then they make
stupid mistakes,
>> you get more mad than ever because you
have so much expectation. Like if I
don't care a about you, like just
>> go to community college, you know,
>> Yeah. So you're harsh because you love
>> like I get angry a lot, right? Cuz
[laughter] like I'm expecting you guys
to perform and to learn. Yes, Bruce.
>> Because I've heard there's some girl
student just said if you just want to
test the boy love you or not. You just
piss piss him off. [laughter] Let him
let him get anger and try to find out if
he can comfort you back or he just like
to give you the reason tell you some
reason stuff then get rid of him. He's
not really the person that fall in love
with you. But she just comfort you like
I'm sorry it's my fault. It's my my
fault. Forgive me. Then I think she
cares about you. So maybe that is girl
we're trying to test the people by if
you're loving him or her.
>> Okay. All right. So uh let let's
continue. Okay.
>> KTO 31.
Oh you upon the holy streams far shore.
So she turning her speeches point
against me even its edge had seemed too
sharp began again without allowing
interruption. Tell
>> So did did we finish the last panel?
>> What line what line were we at? Sorry.
>> Oh, really? Sorry.
>> Okay. All right. Sorry.
>> Sorry. Sorry. [clears throat]
>> So sorry about it.
>> Okay.
>> No, no, we didn't.
>> Okay. All right. Yeah. Okay. All right.
[laughter]
Okay. No worries, man. Let's Let's go.
Yeah.
Okay. Count to 31.
Wait. 31. Okay.
Oh, you upon the holy streams far shore.
So she, turning her speeches point
against me, even its edge had seemed too
sharp, began again without allowing
interruption. Tell, tell if this is
true, for your confession must be
entwined with such self accusation. My
power of speech was so confounded that
my voice would move and yet was spent
before its organs had released it. She
forebore a moment. Then she said, "What
are you thinking? Reply to me. The water
has not yet obliterated your sad
memories." Confusion mixed with fear
compelled a yes out of my mouth. And yet
that yes was such one needed eyes to
make out what it was. Just as a crossbow
that is drawn too taut snaps both its
cord and bow when it is shot an arrow
meets its mark with feeble force. So
caught beneath that heavy weight I burst
and I let tears and size pour forth. My
voice had lost its life along its
passage out. At this she said in the
desire for me that was directing you you
to love the good beyond which there is
no thing to draw our longing. What
chains were strung? What ditches dug
across your path that once you'd come
upon them caused your loss of any hope
of moving forward? What benefits and
what allurements were so evident upon
the brow of others that you had need to
prominade before them? After I had
withheld a bitter sigh, I scarcely had
the voice for my reply, but laboring my
lips gave my words form. Weeping I
answered. Mere appearances turned me
aside with their false loveliness. as
soon as I had lost your countenance.
>> Okay. So, Donnie, so Peter is saying to
Dante, before you loved me, this love
led you to the goodness to God, right?
And then I after I left, you betrayed me
and start to love other things. And then
and then Darn says, "Yes, um I was
fooled by shadows.
Um I was fooled by the loveliness of
shadows." Okay. Uh and you can interpret
this many ways. You it could include
different woman but you but I think the
best way to interpret this is fame.
Okay. That that's really that's real
obsession. Fame. Okay. Keep on going.
>> Line 37. And she had you been silent or
denied would you confess your guilt
would not be less an evidence. It's
known by such a judge. But when the
charge of sinfulness has burst from
one's own cheek than in our court the
wet stone turns and blunts our blad's
own cutting edge. Nevertheless, that you
may feel more shame for your mistake,
and that in time to come, hearing the
sirens you may be more strong, have done
with all the tears you swed, and listen,
so shall you hear, how unto other ends
my buried flesh should have directed
you. Nature or art had never showed you
any beauty that matched the lovely limbs
in which I was enclosed. Limbs scattered
now in dust, and if the highest beauty
failed you through my death, what mortal
thing could then induce you to desire
it? For when the first arrow of things
deceptive struck you, then you surely
should have lifted up your wings to
follow me. No longer such a thing. No
green young girl or other novelty such
brief delight should have weight down
your wings. Awaiting further shafts, the
fledgling bird must meet two or three
blows before he learns. But any
full-fledged bird is proved against the
net that has been spread or arrow aimed.
>> So what's she saying here? She's saying
that yes, she died, but then what has
Donnie done?
She dies. And what should Donnie do now?
>> Yeah. Why?
>> Like Romeo and Juliet. Like that's true
love she's saying.
>> So So is she is she saying D should have
killed himself?
>> He should have probably gone to a
monastery.
>> Something like that. Yeah. Right. But
why?
because he knew he would probably get
distracted and if he really loved her,
he would try and set himself up that he
would never lose.
>> No. No. So, so she's being very explicit
here. Okay. After I died, you should
have kept on loving me. Why? Yes. To
pray for her.
>> Well, I mean, you could still do that if
you're married to someone else or if you
are writing poetry. I mean, it's hard to
pray for a woman if you're married to
someone else. I guess it's like to link
it to purgatory where the more you think
about someone, the faster is the way for
and I think he didn't enough think of
Beatatrice after her death.
>> Okay. No, no, she's being very explicit
here. You should have kept on loving me
because
>> to stay focused on your mission.
>> No,
you should. No. Okay. What she says
explicit, okay, we're running out of
time, but like she she's explicit about
this. You should have kept on loving me
because I am the most beautiful thing in
the whole universe. Dante
joking, but she actually literally says
this. Okay,
>> nature art had never showed you any
beauty that matched.
>> She's like literally about this like I
am good in the universe. Dante, what are
you doing, man? Have you no taste?
[laughter]
Okay.
All right. So again, this is shocking
because this is not what we're
expecting, right? All right. Um, yeah,
keep keep on going.
>> Line 64. As children when ashamed will
stand their eyes upon the ground, they
listen silently, acknowledging their
fault repentantly. So did I stand and
she enjoined me. Since hearing alone
makes you grief, so lift up your beard,
and sight will bring you greater tears.
There's less resistance in the sturdy
oak to its uprooting by a wind from
lands of ours of or lands of um Yarmbus
than I showed in lifting up my chin at
her command. I knew quite well when she
said beard but meant my face the poison
in her argument. When I had raised my
face upright, my eyes were able to
perceive that the first creatures had
paused and were no longer scattering
flowers. and still uncertain of itself.
My vision saw Beatrice turned toward the
animal that is with its two natures but
one person.
>> Okay, so this is a griffin, right? Two
natures, one person, that's Jesus. So
that's why people think the Griffith is
Jesus.
>> Beneath her veil beyond the stream, she
seemed so to surpass her former self and
beauty, as here on earth she had
surpassed all others. The nettle of
remorse so stung me than then that those
among all others, things that once most
lured my love, became most hateful to
me. Such self-indictment seized my heart
that I collapsed. My senses lack. What I
became is known to her who was the cause
of it. Then when my heart restored my
outer sense, I saw the woman whom I'd
found alone standing above me, saying,
"Hold, hold me."
>> Okay, so Beatatrice scolds him, right?
and basically says, "I'm the most
beautiful thing in the world, Dante."
And what happens to Dante? How does
Stanton feel about this?
What's what's his response? Yes. I guess
he's probably he feels like immediately
pretty bad, ashamed, and repentant. But
I guess he's kind of getting a the hint
of happiness because he realizes if
she's so mad at me, it's okay. She's
embracing me, but slowly. She's like
rebuking me in preparation for an
embrace. How does he feel about her
saying I am the most beautiful thing in
the world?
>> Yes.
>> So he looked around like oh wait she's
right. She's so beautiful that
everything that I hold dear to is like
dirt to me. It's like what's to me
>> she's right. Okay. And this shows that
>> what really matters. Okay. Who he is is
his love for Beatatrice. Okay. And this
is where he's purged now. This is the
completion of purgatory. He has now
completely purged of all sin. And and
what has purged from all sin? His love
for Beatatric. Okay. And remember how in
paradise it's his love for Beatric
that's going to carry him all the way to
to God.
Did you want to comment?
>> No. Um I mean uh No, I was there was
something earlier I wanted to say as
well. Um I forgot my point.
Yeah, maybe I can add.
>> Yeah. So, the the comment about how mad
she is about stuff makes me think about
Shakira that she got so mad that her
husband cheated on her with a very ugly
woman. She wrote a song that you trade
Rolex for cas uh casino. Yeah. So, I
think it's kind of the same indignation
that is showing.
>> Yeah. And like so like what D is saying
and it's really interesting is that true
love leads to just ination but just
ination leads to also creativity. Right?
It leads to poetry and creativity.
Okay. Right. And that's a Shakara
example. She's angry because like she
actually does love her husband and and
this just ination leads her to create a
beautiful art of uh a beautiful song.
Okay. Yes.
>> Yeah. I remember my point. I was going
to say that um it's especially uh
striking to compare
what Beatatrice is is feeling now to
what her usual status in in in in heaven
is which is I mean she's in the uh what
I don't know the English word but
>> yeah the red rose yeah exactly and there
I mean people are described to be like
so in such a high sphere of of of heaven
that they don't even should should even
experience this kind of emotion. That's
right. That's right.
>> And because they're so overwhelmed with
uh in a in a good way, of course, with
of uh like God's light
>> that they are kind of in a in a in a
different dimension, let's say, of of
being, of of of emotions and of of
feeling. And now she's kind of she I
think she's being stained not in
necessarily negative way by more like uh
human uh emotions again when the moment
that she you know sees Dante and and as
you said um this feeling it only shows
that actually she does like this this
feeling of anger shows that she actually
feels love for Dante because otherwise
she would feel indifferent.
>> That's right. Okay. So this is really
interesting. Okay. So we are in
purgatory and her first speech is one of
anger. Do you remember remember uh in
paradise her last speech? Do you
remember her last speech in paradise?
Was it what what what emotion was was
was that speech? Do you guys remember?
Anger. Okay. Remember how in her last
speech she's like uh you Italians are
hopeless. you Italians, uh, we send you
Henry VIIth to redeem you and you guys
turn away from him and you guys are
hopeless. Well, I'm going to tell you
right now,
divine judgment is coming. Okay? So,
it's one of anger. Okay? So, this
inverts our understanding of heaven,
right? Because we think of heaven as as
Rene says, one of bliss, one of
happiness. But there's a lot of angry
people in heaven. Okay? Right? Peter's
angry of the Catholic Church and Beatric
is angry about the the Italians. Okay?
So, it's idea of just ination,
right? It it it goes against our
traditional understanding of
Christianity where you're supposed to
like love and forgive and be merciful.
And nope, if you're angry, you should be
angry. Okay. All right. Uh let's keep on
going.
>> Line 91. Then when my heart restored my
outer sense, I saw the woman whom I
found alone standing above me, saying,
"Hold, hold me." She plunged me up to my
throat in the river, and draw me,
drawing me behind her, she now crossed,
light as a gondola along the surface.
When I was near the blessed shore, I
heard as spares may so sweetly sung that
I cannot remember, or much less
transcribe it. The lovely woman opened
wide her arms. She collapsed my head and
then she thrust me under to that point
where I had to swallow water. That done
she drew me out and let me bathed into
the dance of the four lovely women and
each one placed her arm above my head.
Here we're nymphs in heaven stars.
Before she had descended to the world we
were assigned as her handmmaids to
Beatress. We'll be your guides unto her
eyes, but it will be the three beyond
who see me deeply who help you penetrate
her joyous light. So singing they began.
Then leading me together with them to
the griffin's breast where Beatrice
turned toward us stood. They said, "So
that you're not sparing of your gaze,
before you we have set those emeralds
from which love once had aimed his
shafts at you. A thousand longings
burning more than flames compelled my
eyes to watch the radiant eyes that
motionless were still fixed on the
griffin. Just like the sun within a
mirror, so the double- naturatured
creature gleamed within, now showing me,
and now the other guys. Consider,
reader, if I did not wonder when I saw
something that displayed no movement,
though its reflected image kept on
changing, and while full of astonishment
and gladness, my soul tasted that food,
which even as it quenches hunger, burst
the appetite. The other three whose
dance showed me to be the members of a
higher troop advanced and to their chant
they danced angelically. Turn
Beatatrice, oh turn your holy eyes upon
your faithful one, their song besieged.
Who that he might see you has come so
far. Out of your grace do this grace.
Unveil your lips to him so that he may
discern the second beauty you have kept
concealed. Oh splendor of eternal living
light, who's ever grown so pale beneath
Pernaris's shade and has drunk so deeply
from its fountain that he'd not seem to
have his mind confounded, trying to
render you, as you appeared, where
heaven's harmony was your pale likeness.
Your face seen through the air unveiled
completely.
>> Okay, so remember the idea here is that
what redeems Dante at the end of the
day, it's not going through inferno and
purgatory. That is part of the process.
It's not going through those seven
terraces of uh purgatory. What redeems
him is
remembering his complete and utter love
for Beatatrice. It's love that redeems
him. Okay, this is really important. But
he had to go through this process in
order for Beatatrice to awaken this love
in him. Okay, so now we go to Kanto 32.
And here um uh I want Carol to read all
of it and then Renee will translate for
us. Okay. And this is very important
Kanto because this is a rewriting of the
book of Revelation. Okay.
>> This is a rewriting of the book of
Revelation by Dante. Thank you.
>> All right. And so um this is the
apocalypse.
>> Okay.
My eyes were so insistent, so intent on
finding satisfaction for their 10-year
thirst that every other sense was spent.
And to each side, my eyes were walled in
by indifference to all else with its old
net. The holy smile so drew them to
itself. When I was forced to turn my
eyes leftward by those three goddesses,
because I heard them warning me, "You
stir too fixedly." and the condition
that afflicts the sight when eyes have
just been struck by the sun's force left
me without my vision for a time. But
when my sight became accustomed to
lesser sensations, that is lesser than
the mighty force that made my eyes
retreat. I saw the glorious army. It had
wheeled around and to the right. It had
turned east. It faced the seven flames
and face the sun just as protected by
its shields. A squadron will wield to
save itself around its standard until
all of its men have changed direction.
So here all troops of the celestial
kingdom within the vanguard passed in
front of us before the chariot swung
around the pole shaft back to the
wheels. The ladies then returned and
though the griffin moved the blessed
burden when he did that none of his
feathers stirred. The lovely lady who'd
helped me ford leaf and I and Stacy is
following the wheel that turned right
round the inner smaller ark. Were slowly
passing through the tall woods empty
because one who had believed the
serpent. Our pace was measured by
angelic song. The space we covered could
be matched perhaps by three flights of
an unleashed arrow shafts. When beatrus
descended from the chariot. Adam, I
heard all of them murmuring. And then
they drew around a tree whose every
branch had been stripped of flowers and
of leaves. As it grows higher, so its
branches spread wider, it reached a
height that even in their forest would
amaze the Indians.
Blessed are you whose beak does not, oh
griffin, pluck the sweet tasting fruit
that is forbidden, and then afflicts the
belly that has eaten. So round the
robust tree, the others shouted, and the
two-natured animal, thus is the seed of
every righteous man preserved. and
turning to the pole shaft he had pulled
he drew it to the foot of the stripped
tree and with a branch of that tree tied
the two just like our plants that when
the great light falls on earth mixed
with the light that shines behind the
stars of the celestial fishes swell with
blood buds each plant renews its
coloring before the sun has yolked its
deeds beneath another constellation so
the tree whose boughs before had been so
solitary was now renewed showing a tint
that was less than rose more than the
violet. I do not understand the hymn
that they they that they then sang. It
is not sung here on this earth, nor
drowsy did I listen to the end. Could I
describe just how the ruthless eyes
whose long wakefulness caused them so
dear, hearing the tale of surrenx fell
asleep? Then like a painter painting
from a model, I draw the way in which I
fell asleep, but I refrain. Let one more
skillful paint. I move therefore
straight to my waking time, I say that
radiance rent the veil of sleep, and so
as did a voice, rise up. What are you
doing? Even as Peter, John, and James,
when brought to see the blossoms of the
apple tree, whose fruit abetss the
angels hungering,
providing endless wedding feasts in
heaven, were overwhelmed by what they
saw. But then, hearing the word that
shattered deeper sleeps, arose, and saw
their fellowship was smaller, since
Moses and Elijah now had left, and saw a
difference in their teacher's dress. And
I woke and I woke and saw standing above
me, she who before, compassionate, had
guided my steps along the riverbank.
Completely bewildered, I asked, "Where
is Beatrice?" And she, beneath the
boughs that were renewed, she seated on
the root of that tree. see the company
surrounding her. The rest have left
behind the griffin. They have climbed on
high with song that is more sweet, more
deep. I do not know if she said more
than that, because by now I had in sight
one who excluded all things other from
my view. She sat alone upon simple
ground, left there as guardian of the
chariot, I'd seen the two form animal
tie fast. The seven nymphs encircled her
as garland, and in their hands they held
the lamps that cannot be distinguished
by the north or south winds. Here you
shall be a while a visitor, but you
shall be with me and without end, Rome
citizen, the Rome in which Christ is
Roman, and thus to profit that world
which lives badly. Watch the chariot
steadfastly, and when you have returned
beyond, transcribe what you have seen.
Thus Beatatrice and I devoutly at the
feet of her commandments set mind and
eyes where she had wished me to.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, so this is now the
book of Revelation. Okay, D is rewriting
the book of Revol Revelation starting at
lines 109. Okay.
>> Okay.
Never has lightning fallen with never
has lightning fallen with such swift
motion from a thick cloud when it
descends from the most distant limit in
the heavens. as to the bird of Jove that
I saw swoop down through the tree,
carrying the bark as well as the new
leaves and the new flowering. It struck
the chariot chariot with all its force.
The chariot twisted like a ship that's
crossed by seas that now stormed
starboard and now port. I then saw as it
leapt into the body of that triumphal
chariot, a fox that seemed to lack all
honest nourishment. But as she railed
against its squalid sins, my lady forced
the fox to flight as quick as stripped
of flesh, its bones permitted it, then I
could see the eagle plunge again down
through the tree into the chariot and
leave it feathered with its plumage. And
just like a voice from an embittered
heart, a voice issued from heaven saying
this, "Oh my small bark, your freight is
wickedness." Then did the ground between
the two wheels seemed to me to open from
the earth. A dragon emerged. It drove
its tail up through the chariot, and
like a wasp. When it retracts its sting,
drawing its venom tail back to itself,
it dragged part of the bottom off and
went its way undulating. And what was
left was covered with the eagle's
plumes, perhaps offered with sound and
kind intent. much as grass covers
fertile ground and the pole shaft and
both wheels were recovered in less time
than mouth must be kept open when one
size transfigured so the saintly
instrument grew heads which sprouted
from its parts. Three grew upon the pole
shaft and one at each corner. The three
were horned like oxen, but the four had
just a single horn upon their foreheads.
Such monsters never have been seen
before. Just like a fortress set on a
steep slope, securely seated there and
gert, a whose eyes were quick to
rove appeared to me. And I saw her at
her I saw at her side erect a giant who
seemed to serve as her custodian, and
they again embraced each other. But when
she turned her wandering wanted eyes to
me, then that ferocious amidor beat her
from head to foot. Then swollen with
suspicion, fierce with anger, he untied
the chariot made monster, dragging it
into the wood so that I could not see
either the or the strange chariot
beast.
>> Okay. So could could you start from line
109? Uh Renee. Okay. So this is the book
of Revelation. Okay.
>> Yeah.
for
my delight. Foreign
speech. Foreign speech. Foreign speech.
for
Fore
speech.
for
Okay. So, Renee, have you guys studied
this um the section uh what is this
section saying?
>> Uh I don't remember if this not but
yeah.
>> Okay. So, this is the book of
revelation. Okay. And so Beatatrice is
telling Dante observe what's happening
because this is your this this is the
past the present and the future. And so
if we believe that the griffin is Jesus
the griffin is what takes a chariot to
earth. Okay the chariot is now the
church right the beings of the Catholic
church and all these imagery it's
showing us the history of the Catholic
church. So starting in line uh 109
um uh sorry 112 the bird of Joel sweeps
in and attacks the church. Okay so this
is uh the Christian church early church
under Roman persecution.
Uh then what happens is that uh there is
a fox
um that uh and the fox represents early
Christian heresy. Okay. Then you have
the eagle plunged into the chariot and
become part of the chariot and that of
course represents the Roman Empire as uh
Constantine's donation to the Catholic
church. So now empire and church are one
in the same and that distorts the
character of the church. Then you have a
dragon emerge. What is a dragon in the
book of revelation? Do you guys know?
>> Satan.
>> The antichrist. Okay. The antichrist.
The dragon is the antichrist. It's Satan
basically, but it's it's a pope that
pretends to fight for the church, but
which corrupts the church. Okay. So, so
now the church is being corrupted from
within. And the history keeps on going
and it shows the constant corruption of
the church. And then towards the end, we
have a emerge. This is of course a
of Babylon. And emerging with the
is a giant that ultimately beats
her out. Beats her up. Okay. And what
scholars agree on is this
represents Florence, the sea of Florence
which exiled Dante. The giant represents
the Holy Roman Empire. So in the
beginning it seems that the Holy Roman
Empire has allied with Florence against
the um Pope and and this of course are
the Giblines. But then later on the Holy
Roman Empire will betray and destroy
Florence. Um, okay. So, this is the the
vision and it is one again of just
anger, fear, and hatred. And this is not
what we're expecting. We're expecting
like a happy wedding. Okay, this is not
at all what we expected. Why? What's
going on here? Why do I Why do Why do
the book of Revelation in the Divine
Comedy? And this is like right before
they go to heaven, guys.
What's going on here?
Because revelation essentially is about
prophecy of the future before the second
coming of Christ sort of. And so it's
like before heaven on earth or before we
go to heaven. It's revelations. It's all
these war and fights and battles and all
these purging and cleansing and claiming
of authorities between the antichrist
and Christ.
>> But what does anger do in a place of
love? Do you understand? It totally
makes sense because Jesus uh got really
angry all the time in the Bible, but
most of the time was because he went
into the temple with the Jewish people
that he's yelling at them because he's
like, "You have turned my temple into a
place of a market."
>> So, he like goes into a rampage and
throws stuff. So, it's kind of like
what's retribution to the church is what
Jesus is doing to like
>> Okay. Okay. Let's imagine, let's do a
thought experiment. Okay. Let's imagine
Dante
uh writes this and a Buddhist monk,
okay, a Buddhist monk reads this and
he's disturbed by the anger
in
this divine comedy. And so they have tea
together [snorts] and the Buddhist monk
says, "Why can't you show compassion to
the people on this planet, these kings,
these queens?
Ultimately, it's for not. It doesn't
really matter, right? Because all this
is is an illusion. So show sympathy,
show compassion to these people. And it
is your mercy, your forgiveness, your
love that is divine,
right? Is that what Buddhist say?
I I'm not a Buddhist. I don't know.
That's what I think they say.
>> Yes. Everything is an illusion. But then
you have to go to the consequence of it.
If there's no just indignation or
retribution, then people will keep
acting that way.
>> Uh uh Anna,
>> God is ultimately compassion and love.
But yet God is mad all the time in Old
Testament. So like anger, wrath,
retribution does not conflict with love
because it is exactly like a father
punishing or disciplining his kid. It's
out of love.
>> Okay. Okay. But then the Buddhist monk
is like wrath, anger is poison, right?
The more anger, wrath you have, the more
poison you become. So what good can come
from your anger and your wrath? Yes,
>> it's cleansing again because there's
wrath in hell obviously as we know,
right? And the way to not engage with
wrath is walk around it otherwise you
add to it. But it almost seems to be an
exception when it comes to God himself
that's having wrath all the time. Right.
So then the question paradox is why is
God mad? Right.
>> Right. No, but but but then the point is
don't be mad. God will be mad. Let God
handle it. Right.
>> So just cleanse yourself of your anger.
Don't get angry. Focus on compassion.
Yes. Because Dante essentially in exile
is he's mad at Florentine and all the
church is doing and he he probably heard
this from a lot of people but like leave
God like retribution to God and he will
be do the justice but like we've
discussed before he's so mad at people
who so heavenly bond that they're not
earthly good. So then like he's mad that
no consequence is coming to the Catholic
Church at this point and so he wants it
to you know do something about the
president.
>> Well that just shows Don as a very petty
person then right it's like he wants
vengeance. Yeah. Yeah. Carol
>> if there's no just indignation then
Dante wouldn't have written the divine.
>> Exactly. Okay. Exactly. It is this just
indignation that propelled his
creativity. It's what led him to write
divine comedy.
love leads to just Indonesian. His love
for Florence leads to his anger that he
was exiled by Florence. And now he's
like, I want God to punish the
Florentines. And this anger is what
leads him to write the Divine Comedy.
But then we have a paradox which is
like, okay, but then why is there wrath
in hell and why is there wrath in
purgatory? Clearly, it's a sin,
right? That's confusing though. Wrath
leads you to creativity. It's coming
It's coming from a place of love, but at
the same time, you're being punished for
it.
Uh uh Julian, then Edward, then Fred.
>> I feel like anger would just be an
expression of yourself, but it wouldn't
really
lead to change of other people, just
change for yourself. Because Jesus
anger, for example, for the Jewish
people didn't really change the Jewish
people, right? It only expressed his
anger for the for the people. But and
maybe um um like made the his disciples
maybe more believe in him, but it didn't
change anything for the people he was
angry about.
>> So I feel like anger wouldn't really be
the solution.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So you're
agreeing with the Buddhist monk. Anger
is not the solution. Yes. Uh Edward,
>> is it that wrath is wrong but wrath can
be justified if it's divinely aligned?
>> Okay. What do you mean by that?
>> Like in regular ordinary life, wrath for
I know cuz I'm annoyed and frustrated
about something.
This is a problem of me projecting on
someone else. If it is truly and I
suppose only God can judge this. If it
is truly from a place of pure love and
therefore divinely aligned then wrath
wrath in this context can be justified.
>> Okay. All right. Sure. Fred,
>> I have to say that I don't think there's
any wrath in paradise. Like I think to
human minds divine justice and
just the action of the just to human
mind seems like anger and probably if
you were God and really powerful you'd
think how should I come across such that
my message has an effect but I really
don't think God or in fact bee is like
that angry they just are trying to take
the path of greatest efficacy. So like
there's wrath in purgatory, wrath in
hell, but the wrath in heaven is just
what Dante perceives as anger. Like this
all seems like violent to Dante, but is
really just metaphorical violence.
>> Okay. So again, the thing about the vine
comedy that's very important for us to
remember is that we have the intuition
to understand everything. Okay? So if
we're not able to express our ourselves
clearly, if the if it's if it's not
outcomes razor elegant, then we're not
approaching the truth enough. Okay. So,
I understand. Yes. Maybe when I when I
interpreting uh it properly, but no, I I
think there's something else going on.
Uh Damian,
>> the the anger in heaven might have come
from a place of love, but the wrath and
like hell and purg purgatory might be
coming from a like your temper.
Uh Andy,
>> I've been wrestling about this idea of
like if the world around us is poor, has
as a is unjust. Um a lot of Dante's
individuality would be like just be
aligned with God and stuff like that.
But Dante's wrath seems to be in this
same scenario of like the Catholic
Church is led by the Antichrist
>> and that's an unjust situation on earth.
>> Yes. and where we're like, um, hey, I
don't like this president or there's
this bad social situation going on.
Dante's taking that for the most
ultimate cause, which is the antichrist
is leading the flock astray. And so I
need to not just get myself aligned with
Christ, but I need or with God, but I
need to fix this social situation as
well.
>> Yes. Exactly. Okay. That's exactly
right. Did Did you do Do you want to add
something?
>> Yeah. I I was just going to say that at
least the way we're told it's a in par
or at least in heaven in paradise there
is no anger then of course like souls
are able to feel anger like beatatric
for example but there is no there is no
need for anger in paradise and like and
paradise is kind of the destination the
ultimate destination of what all
everyone should aspire to and my
understanding of this is that anger is
only good in so far it is a means to set
people on the right path towards a
destination of no anger. So like this
like anger is only in good in so far as
that it's a means to the place with no
anger.
>> Okay. So again there's a lot of anger in
paradise. Okay. So I I want to elaborate
on Andy's point because Eddie got it
completely right. Look compare and
contrast. Okay. Back in Donnie Donny's
time the corruption of the church were
like the antichrist. Let's go and do
something about it. Right? Today look at
the world around us. Right? Blatant
corruption, blatant inequality. Donald
Trump is president for God's sake. And
we're like, "Let's go watch porn, guys.
Yeah, let's go play watch porn. Oh,
let's play video games. Let's uh you
know, like like that's literally what
we're doing." Okay. So, the issue not is
not anger. The issue is how we choose to
channel anger. Okay. You mean
>> I I would just like to ask that who was
the antichrist at that time?
>> The pope.
Donnie thought the antichrist was the
pope. Pope Bonafice. Okay. Um it look uh
yeah David
>> I I think uh by putting uh the uh the
church militant uh behind uh church
triumphant
and putting uh you know the uh conflict
and anger and chaos uh right at the end
of uh purgatory
uh reveals Dante's um you know eventual
uh pessimistic n uh you know attitude
toward uh human society. Although he
believed in um in in the harmonious
development eventually salvation of
individual maybe he has um still a quite
a you know and call calling his work
comedia he still think that human
society is not able to
save his okay all right okay so let's
talk about wrath okay this is really
important for us to understand so wrath
is punished in hell right anger is
punished in hell by what boiling Right?
So you you are being boil boiled in a
lake. Now there are two types of angry
people. There are people who are just
angry. But there are people who hide
their anger. They suppress their anger.
And the worst are those who suppress
anger because they are drowning. They're
suffocating inside this lake that's
boiling. Okay. Okay. That's hell. Then
you have purgatory and and it's black
smoke which blinds you. Right. Okay. So
that's what D is saying here. Anger is
not channel correctly. If it's not
directed towards justice, it blinds you.
It fers and it uh corrupts you and you
suffocate under it. But if anger is
directed towards justice, towards as
Edward says, towards a divine align
alignment, towards love, then that's a
good thing. Do you understand? There's
nothing wrong with anger. It's how anger
is used. How anger is channeled. Right?
Dante is angry at the church. Donn is
angry at Florence. So Don D is angry at
his enemies and that's what leads him
right to divine comedy, right? Because
where do his enemies go? They go in
hell. Where do his friends go? They go
in purgatory. What does he do to the
Catholic Church? He basically condemns
them to um to a prophecy and then
Florence, you know, will be a that
will be destroyed by the giant. Okay,
that's how you should use your anger.
Don't watch porn, guys. Go write poetry.
Is is that a revelation? Are are you
[laughter]
okay?
Right.
Yes, Brad.
>> I'm just thinking about the future. Um,
anger is super useful, but I find that
because young people today are getting
more and more sensitive, anger makes
them disassociate. So, I'm thinking that
in my mission for the future,
>> I probably want to try and scops people
into being better and not be angry at
them.
>> You're taking action. That's right.
That's what we should all be doing.
Okay. Don't be like, there's nothing I
can do about it and I don't be angry
because angry makes me look bad and and
people say, "Oh, don't be angry." You
know, go see a therapist, right? Like,
oh, are you angry? You should be on
Valium. Oh, are you angry? Oh, yeah. I'm
more asking how would you advise people
in my generation to present their anger
because I feel like being angry now
drives people away even more. So I'm
thinking that even if I'm angry inside I
don't want to hide my anger but like I
have to be so seductive to people to
change them now because any condemnation
immediately shuts people off. Uh sure.
Okay.
>> Yeah. continuing of his I uh question is
what I hear a lot is the how dare you
meim like is how people now show anger
uh and I think that's not a you know the
right way to channel so it's follow up
to his question
>> look um clearly I'm an angry young man
okay I'm not young anymore but I'm
clearly an angry person and I'm angry
because I have three kids uh who are
growing up in this screwed up world
right we're led by idiots um There's so
much corruption, inequality in this
world and all they're doing is is
screwing things up even more, right? And
so I'm angry. I have three young kids
and I'm like, you know, I need to
channel this anger in creating a better
world for my three young kids. And the
only thing I can do is teach, right? I
need to take action. I can't be at home
uh making YouTube videos all day and
complaining about it, right? I could
make a lot of money doing this, guys.
Okay? Seriously, I could be doing tupal
analysis and bitching about the world
and I I would have a huge audience. But
I'm like, no, I need to take action. So
I rather than like go about it,
let me do something about it and teach
Dante to the world so that you could be
inspired to take action yourself to
expand your imagination to learn the
power of love to show compassion,
empathy to others, and take action for
yourself. And that's why I tell that's
why I tell you what I want from you in
this class is to leave this class and
teach it to someone else, right? It
could be you you you could become a
teacher, which would be great, but you
can also just, you know, like Carol
teach it to Damian, right? Or Damian
could could teach it to, you know, your
your brother, right? And if you just do
it this way, over time, the world is
going to change for the better. And I I
already see it because I see all the
changes in you guys.
Okay? Did Did you wanna [applause]
>> I know, I know, I know, I know. We'll
finish at four. Okay. Okay. But that's
what Donn is saying here. Be angry.
Anger comes from a place of love, but
channel your anger into action that
benefits humanity. Okay. And that's why
he wrote the Divine Comedy.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I think something that we
need to be particularly aware about
especially today for youth is that there
is a tendency at least in my opinion at
least as far as I've noticed there is a
tendency that is becoming more and more
widespread to make it make extremes look
good or like to think that it's fine and
okay and uh even wise and reasonable to
pursue extremes
um and or that it's a cool thing um and
I think we should if there's something
that
we should at least try to go back to is
to appreciate nuance always and um you I
don't know personally a lot of the anger
I see in youth today because like as we
said like the world is so screwed up
right and there's there are so many
problems arguably more than in the past
few decades um we need to like resist
the temptation to you know just just
because we are so angry to to just be
radical. You know, if we should resist
that temptation and and stay in nuance
and in, you know, always seeing both
sides
and and there's still ways of channeling
that anger without always shouting
because like I feel like there's like
it's such a fashion now to like shout to
to shout in metaphorical way of course.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you for that.
Okay. So, this is the last candle, guys.
Okay, we've come to it. We've come to
the very last kanto. We've done it.
We've read the entire Divine Comedy. All
right, but here we go. The the the very
last Kanto of Purgatory.
Okay.
Weeping the women then began, now three,
now four, alternately to psalm gently
deuse venaroon genties. And at this
sighing and full of pity, Beatatrice was
changed. She listened, grieving little
less than Mary when beneath the cross
she wept. But when the seven virgins had
completed their psalm, and she was free
to speak, erect her coloring like ardent
fire, she answered, "Modicum at nonveris
may at sisters delightful to me
at verites may." Then she set all the
seven nymphs in front of her and
signaled me, the lady and the sage who
had remained to move behind her. So she
advanced, and I do not believe that she
had taken her 10th step upon the ground
before her eyes had struck my eyes, and
gazing tranquily, "Pray, come more
quickly," she said to me, "So that
you're more ready to listen to me,
should I speak to you." As soon as I,
responding to my duty, had joined her,
she said, "Brother, why not try? since
now you're at my side to query me. Like
those who speaking to superiors too
reverently do not speak distinctly, not
drawing their clear voice up to their
teeth, so did I speak with sound too
incomplete when I began. Lady, you know
my need to know and know how it can be
appeased. And she to me, I'd have you
disentangle yourself from this point on
from fear and shame that you no longer
speak like one who dreams. Know that the
vessel which the serpent broke was and
is not. But he whose fault it is may
rest assured. God's vengeance fears no
hindrance. The eagle that had left its
plumes within the chariot which then
became a monster and then a prey will
not forever be without an air. For I can
plainly see, and thus I tell it, stars
already close at hand, which can't be
blocked or checked, will bring a time in
which dispatched by God of 510 and five
will slay the together with that
giant who sins with her. And what I tell
as dark as fins and theis may leave you
less convinced because like these it
tires the intellect with quanderies. But
soon events themselves will be the niads
that clarify its obstinate enigma but
without injury to grain or herds. Take
note and even as I speak these words do
not transmit them in your turn to those
who live the life that is a race to
death. And you when you write them, keep
in mind that you must not conceal what
you've seen of the tree that now has
been desoiled twice over here. Whoever
robs or rens that tree offends with his
blaspheming action God for he created it
for his soul use holy for tasting of
that tree. The first soul waited 5,000
years and mourned grief and longing for
him who on himself avenged that taste.
Your intellects asleep if it can't see
how singular is the cause that makes
that tree so tall and makes it grow
invertedly. And if like waters of the
Elsa, your vain thoughts did not encrust
your mind. If your delight in them were
not like pamas staining the malbury,
you'd recognize in that trees form and
height the moral sense God's justice had
when he forbade trespass. But since I
see your intellect is made of stone and
petrified, grown so opaque, the light of
what I say has left you dazed, I'd also
have you bear my words within you, if
not inscribed, at least outlined, just
as the pilgrim staff is brought back
wreathed with palm.
And I, even as wax, the seals impressed,
where there's no alteration of form, so
does my brain now bear what you have
stamped. But why does your desired word
ascend so high above my understanding
that the more I try the more am I
denied? That you may recognize, she
said, the school that you have followed
and may see. If what it taught can
comprehend what I have said, and see
that as the earth is distant from the
highest and the swiftest of the heavens,
so distant is your way from the divine.
And I replied to her, I don't remember
making myself a stranger to you, nor
does conscience gnaw at me because of
that. And if you can't remember that,
she answered, smiling, then call to mind
how you today have drunk of leaf. And if
smoke is proof of fire, then it is clear
we can conclude from this forgetfulness
that in your will there was a fault.
Your will had turned elsewhere. But from
now on, the words I speak will be naked.
That is appropriate if they would lay
bare before your still crude sight. More
incandescent now with slower steps the
sun was pacing the meridian which alters
with the place from which it seen. When
just as one who serves as escort for a
group will halt if he has come upon
things strange or even traces of
strangeness. The seven ladies halted at
the edge of a dense shadow such as
mountains cast beneath green leaves and
black boughs on cold banks. In front of
them
I seem to see Euphrates and tigers
issuing from one same spring and then as
friends do separating slowly. Oh light,
oh glory of the human race, what water
is this flowing from one source and then
becoming distant from itself? Her answer
to what I had asked was, "Ask Matilda to
explain this." And the lovely lady, as
one who frees herself from blame,
replied, "He's heard of this in other
matters from me, and I'm sure that leads
waters have not obscured his memory of
this." And Beatatrice, perhaps some
greater care, which often weakens memory
has made his mind in things regarding
sight grow dark. But see, Yoe, as it
flows from there, lead him to it. And as
you're used to doing, revive the power
that is faint in him.
As with the noble soul, which offers no
excuse, but makes another's will its
own. As soon as signs reveal that will,
just so when she had taken me, the
lovely lady moves forward. And she said
with womenly courtesy to Stacius, "Come
with him. If reader I had ampler space
in which to write, I'd sing, though
incompletely, that sweet draw from which
my thirst was limitless. But since all
of the pages predisposed for this, the
second canacle are full. The curb of art
will not let me continue. From that most
holy wave, I now return to Beatus
remade. As new trees are renewed, when
they bring forth new boughs, I was pure
and prepared to climb unto the stars.
Okay. So now Dante has been completely
purified
and purged of all sin, of all doubt. He
has fully committed to his love for
Beatatrice
and now they will climb to the stars. Um
they talk about the tree of knowledge.
Why did
God
let us eat
the fruit from the tree?
Yes. Because the gift was free will to
Adam and Eve. And I think that the
there's only one real choice you can
make in life freely, and that's whether
you want to know whether things are good
or bad or not. Otherwise, you're just
like a a a monkey or a cattle or
whatever.
>> That's right. Yeah. Thank you. Okay. All
right. So, that is it, guys. We have
done the complete divine comedy. Any
questions about today?
Are we clear about what DA's message is?
I I know this is what you were taught in
school, but but
um you know, we we we do things
differently here. Um
um any questions or thoughts?
Did do you have any questions because
it's completely counter to what you
learned in uh in in school, right?
>> Maybe um if you could like reiterate
explaining like what what what what what
is the sense of like uh because first
you read uh heaven first or hell.
>> We read paradise first. Paradise then
inferno and then pugator.
>> We finished with purgatory. Yes.
>> Yes. So uh maybe I was just if you could
like explain uh briefly about that.
>> Yeah. So for us what's really important
is for us to appreciate u the cosmology
of Dante. And to do that you have to go
actually read go to paradise first
because then he tells you everything
about how he believes the cosmos works.
Right? You start off in hell. uh you're
confused because you think the teacher
is Virgil and a lot of things that
Virgil says are actually not true. If
you end up in paradise first then then
you can see that Virgil is not a
reliable um guide. Okay. And then uh
Yep. Uh Bruce
>> Yeah. Uh because in as you know in this
chapter we can know from this chapter
about revelation but revelation actually
is also kind of prediction. Uh it's kind
of a predict to human beings. So I think
maybe it's your time for you try to
predict the future according to this
chapter
>> just like revelation deaths. Yeah,
>> right. Okay. Um so I I want to finish
with one final remark and that is how
Donnie designs divine comedy. So um
we've been to purgatory. Now now I hope
by yourself you go to heaven. Okay. At
the at the end of heaven
where do you go after heaven?
You go to hell. Okay. I guess
>> and you become like very close to God
>> and that's it, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Yeah. That's what most people are
taught. But again, Dante is
revolutionary because he doesn't believe
that. Okay. So, let's look at the last
two words of purgatory.
What are the last two words?
the stars, right? And Italian is the
same, right?
>> As al also the inferno and everything.
>> Okay. So, here in purgatory, it's a
stars, right?
And in uh inferno, what's the last two
words? The stars, right? In paradise,
what's the last two words?
Why would it be like that?
Yes, Damian.
Because there are a lot of stars.
>> Yeah. There's infinite, right? The
journey never ends.
One destination only leads to another
journey.
Then when you finish that journey, then
a new a journey starts. Okay? So another
reason why I want to do paradise first
is to show you um this journey will
never end. Okay? Hopefully you'll go
home, go back and read paradise again.
Uh, and then you'll you'll see when you
repeat paradise again, you'll see it
completely differently. Okay. So, it's
meant to be a loop. It's meant to be
eternity, but it's also meant to be
infinity. Okay. Yes, Damian.
>> I'd just like to ask, what did the pope
do to make Dante hate him so much?
>> Um, so at this time in history, uh, the
Catholic Church is divided into many
different factions, and they're fighting
over, um, who should be the legitimate
pope. And right now there are two major
centers of Catholic power. There's one
in the in Rome of course where the
Catholic Church is based but there's
also one based in Avanon which is
sponsored by the Holy Roman Emperor.
Okay. And this is leading to wars
throughout the entire of Italy. Um and
so Don is concerned about the factional
struggles in within the Catholic Church.
But also at this point in history, the
Catholic Church is extremely corrupt. Uh
you can you can buy indulgences and this
will get you access to purgatory. Even
though you could be the worst person in
the world, if you just have enough
money, you you can always buy your way
into heaven. And Donnie just finds this
appalling. Um and then there's there's
there's like a million things that
Donnie is pissed about. Yes. Uh Fred,
>> so I'm drawn to action definitely by the
study and reading of this of the Divine
Comedy. Um my action is basically
directed towards increasing the free
will of everybody in the world trying to
fight against wrong ideas, biases that
are forcefully spread on people and that
they pick up. What would your tips and
short advice be to me and other people
who are trying to act towards this end?
So if I want to increase the free will
of other people, there's teaching, which
you do amazingly, but I don't know if
I'm a teacher. But if I'm trying to
invent something or create something,
what principle should I keep in mind?
>> Okay, so this is a great segue to our
next section. Okay, the final section,
which is self-reflection and um so so so
maybe uh um yeah, we can engage in a
process of self-reflection and if if you
need to um run or something. Okay. All
right. Okay. All right. So, um, we are
finished Divine Comedy and, um, I just
want to hear
how you think you've changed or,
um, felt these past two weeks. Okay. So,
does would anyone like to start? And and
I I'll answer your question eventually,
Fred. Okay. But, but first first I I
want to go through this reflection
circle and then and then we'll discuss
um
what's next.
Okay.
Uh who would like to start? Uh yes
>> say what how learning is this two week
so I have to say that before I attend
this program I really like regard those
like literary works uh right and long
times ago it's like a may recall that's
quite distant for me and after joining
this program I think um I know the
reason why those works are masterpiece
and can like be really famous and well
spread to the world because I quite
understand about their wisdom. It's like
for example, I know some kind of
motivation that truly come from my heart
that can lead me to do something in the
world rather than like being manipulated
by some like other social factors. Uh
and also for me for I mean this pro
program for me like in the future is
also kind of kind of important because
uh honestly speaking uh my intended
major is probably artificial
intelligence and some data science
major. So uh yeah yeah yeah
>> it's a dead end what
>> it's a dead end like like I'm telling
you right now it's a dead end. Oh. Oh,
really? Let's say let's say and like uh
I know that like maybe like few days ago
we have talk about that AI is might be
alchemy. Uh and I will try my best to
let do not let this come true in the
future like that. Okay. All right. Thank
you. Uh who's next? Who would like to
if you don't speak I'm just going to
call on you. Okay. Uh let's let's start
with Francois.
I think this course I did uh lost the
sense of time. It went like super fast
and I our attention was really focused
into uh knowledge self-improvement. So
like we didn't think about like oh I'm
on vacation or I have other things to
do. I do feel a bit lighter. But a thing
about me in this book I feel like I
didn't start from zero. There are still
some topics I understood before starting
reading this book. uh especially about
uh love I feel like and so even though
I'm new to the whole spirituality I mean
especially the Christian aspect of this
book um it didn't transform me that much
um but it is also um a nice sensation of
hope just to see this class come
together uh people from different ages
different cultures to see that everyone
shows up every day and try to
participate and make this class better
um is really rewarding and like this not
only about the book but also the class
just was was uh very interesting also
about um dreaming uh I wasn't the only
guy that dreamt a lot especially the
last few days which like surprised me
>> by the way I I had a dream yesterday
night I don't know if we have time to
share it but um
>> go ahead share it
>> um I I found it quite interesting and it
is uh at first I thought was uh quite
limited But uh it is interesting. So uh
it started from me meeting a very good
friend of mine in primary school. So
it's been like almost seven or eight
years I didn't see him. Uh and it was a
good friend. So a positive um energy and
also uh nostalgic.
So I go to his house and we start
talking just like yeah like catching the
time. and he started talking about his
uh girlfriend he had and he got a bit
emotional
and um and yeah, it didn't quite end
well for him. So, I was a bit here for
him. And then we went on a walk outside
in the neighborhood uh close to my house
and I really recognized this like the
spot even though it changed a lot and um
I don't know why I started smoking a
joint. So, this is a bit the aspect I
thought wasn't useful. So, I started
smoking and then we walk a bit. We go to
a park and in the entry of the park.
There is like three spots. It's a bit
chaotic and there's uh a spot with like
water, fountains, uh a bit like a farm.
Um so, pretty beautiful. And then other
spot like just like 5 meters away of
stuff burning. So, like some trash
burning. So, I could see this a bit as
inferno like chaotic. And then in front
of me a big pile of dirt. And so we
first uh go together on this big pile of
dirt. And I start like just looking
around in the park. There was like
family people playing around. So like it
didn't seem like anything was going on.
There was just like this water stuff,
this fire stuff, and this pile of dirt,
but everyone just like walking around
playing. And um and then my my joint
like didn't wasn't like lit anymore. And
so I thought, okay, maybe I should go
into the fire to lit it. And it was like
this big fire of like 5 meters and I was
like, "Okay, maybe not a good idea, you
know, like I don't care." And then my
friend tells me, "Yeah, no, look, it's
actually lit." And so I start smoking
again. And then I look at my hands and
there's actually two joints now. And uh
I told him, "Yeah, like is it is it
yours or like do you want to smoke?" And
he tells me, "I I I don't smoke." So I'm
like, "Okay, right. I got like two
joints now. It's not that bad."
[laughter]
And so we continue walking in the park
and it really gets like bigger. So the
entry was quite small with like this
like water, fire and dirt figure. And
then now the park is like just bigger.
We walk around, continue talking. And at
the end we need to go back home. And my
thought was like uh okay now I need to
go back home. Um I'm quite high. Should
I be worried about seeing my parents?
And I thought like actually I don't
care. I had this very nice moment with
my friend. So, like, who cares if I'm
just like, "Hi, in my home." And then we
say goodbye.
>> Okay. Right. Okay. Thank you. Uh, it's
very interesting. Okay.
>> Yeah, it is.
>> Okay. All right. Uh, anyone who's next,
Skyler? Yes.
>> Um, yeah. So, uh, so before my uh,
understanding of Divine Comedy and Dante
is, you know, it's something that you
have to learn in history class. It's
very important. That's all I knew about
it. But after reading it, I think I have
four main takeaways. First of all is
that is, you know, love is the answer to
all. And if you let like love guide your
actions, it's kind of like your
intuition where that way it's always
going to leave you in a path that your
heart desires. So for example, when
we're reading divine comedy and some
things you don't understand, you think
of it from the perspective of, you know,
your mother or your wife or your
children. So now when I'm reading a book
that I don't understand, I I know that
the tool is to try to use love to
understand it. That's my first takeaway.
>> My second takeaway is I really think
that reading Dante because it's so
foundational in Western thinking,
especially after the Renaissance, it's
helped me as a Chinese person gain more
thorough understanding of Western
culture. It's kind of like if you are a
westerner and you read uh Lu, you know,
that way you understand Chinese culture
more and the things that it values. for
example, the emphasis on on free will
and really using your free will. You
know, in in Kivine comedy, if you don't
use your free will, you are literally
going to hell. So, you know, this idea
of it being democratic, it being
accessible, of um love thy neighbor. And
so, uh a lot of those values very really
deep in Western culture and how it
manifests in the real world and how it
manifests and how I interact with
Westerners. I've gained a more thorough
understanding through reading this. My
third takeaway is like we are lost
because of fear. That's uh that's
something that you said that really like
stuck stuck with me, you know. Um Dante
like the reason why this book was really
revolutionary was because back then
people were really afraid of God. People
were afraid of the unknown. They didn't
know what heaven looked like, what the
afterlife looked like. So a lot of so a
lot of things that they were doing on
earth were um fearful or they were very
scared to do anything. And that was
because, you know, they're lost because
of fear. So, you know, I'm going to be
entering college. It's a different life.
Uh I don't really know what I want to
major in. I don't know what my future is
looks like. So, in a way, I am also lost
because of fear. But I know that that's
okay, you know, and you know, reading
good books can can show you a path. My
fourth takeaway is the value of art. I
remember you said this line, um, poetry
is aimed to put you in awe, not to put
you in fear. And divine comedy is meant
to inspire you to reach um higher
heights. You also said, you know, poetry
embeds itself into the collective
conscious and embeds itself into how you
see the world. So reading Dante,
especially listening to it in Italian,
it's it's something that's a little bit
more emotional and you like um art. It
it like you said, it embeds into how you
see the world. It lets you rise beyond
the material world, beyond grades and
tests and the mundane. And it's a it's a
reflective experience. And so those are
my four takeaways.
>> That's wonderful. Thank you so much,
Skyler. Okay. Uh uh Damen,
>> I I think personally reading the Divine
Comedy helps gave it gave me more faith
in God.
>> Okay. Wonderful. Great. Uh David
>> um so I just created this uh just a few
minutes ago. So I think there are so
many layers of um you know
[clears throat] um understanding the
lecture theory. I think on the
fundamental level
there this lecture gave me uh experience
that's is uh and basically the first
induction into the the world of
literature because before going into
this lectures I thought um divine comedy
is just a traditional um moralistic
allegorical
uh uh installation where you have very
uh well structured universe of uh
different um figures that will give you
very clear idea about the medieval or
late uh uh early men
uh um you know a great wise man's uh
admonition as to how to lead life
righteous life but then I realized that
um you know below this surface of the
structure uh each uh individual, each
actor or each um protagonist have their
own life and their own uh complexity. Uh
which is I think um you know give me the
initial idea of about how uh uh
literature work is created. It is the
creation of individual living feature uh
living figure in this uh magna opus. So,
so I I began to appreciate Danty as a
poem.
But then I realized that um
uh uh Danty is not just a poem but a
poet but actually it's channeling u some
supernatural power um that uh you have
uh you know alluded to in many many
places. I think what behind this um um
this divine uh message is um is is inf
infinite. So I for I can uh derive many
pragmatic uh knowledge about for example
relationship
um um how to how to be a parent although
I'm not a parent and how to um how to
understand uh uh love human life for
example uh I uh just today I learned uh
that uh a woman's love could take uh
infinite um um uh forms forms uh anger
or hate could al all be form of love. uh
and it's not uh just regard as uh you
know uh onedimensional
harmony that uh always pleasing always
uh you know cherry and so it's it's very
complex and secondly
so I so on the second level I learned
that um how to be a teacher you know I
don't I I'm not teacher but I observed
how you teach I think this is the this
class is also a performative experience
where uh you let uh the student to
co-create with you and I learned that
you are probably I I I speculate that
you are probably also try to draw
inspiration for a next book uh from the
uh from the interaction with the
students. So I I observe try to
understand how [snorts] to co-create
something uh out of uh the learning
process not just that to to to uh spread
knowledge but to create new knowledge
and on on the third level I think um
I'm also learning um
uh how to um uh how to understand uh
these um uh dentist text uh in in the
context of culture. So I have uh many
question marks about this but it's it's
just uh you know it's just very complex
questions and is not you know we don't
have time for that but for example um uh
I I it it did give me a you know some
impression about uh the different
between Italian literature and English
literature. For me uh you know uh
Italian literature is much more colorful
is more romant uh romant has more
element of romantism you know has more
tendency to to uh to present things in a
very color compared to English
literature where it is more black and uh
white uh almost like the weather in
England.
Anyway, um so
but uh yeah and but but then uh I um
yeah that that makes Danty's work uh
very very unique because uh Danty uh is
not does not have the luxury of writing
on the so-called uh code tale of the
English empire British Empire which
makes it uh much more difficult for
people outside Italy to appreciate
Dante. But if you if you um if you read
the original the the Italian version,
you can see that it is um it is has
multi-dimensional elements. It's not
it's not even uh it's not even colorful,
but it it has it has the cadence and the
the you know the the the the tonality of
this literature is is is immense. So and
and on the last level I think uh from
the Chinese perspect perspective
uh um you know the uh the the message
every message uh whether it's from God
or from from from a poem poet uh it is
uh conditioned on the language. So uh
fundamentally uh we are viewing or
reading this text uh you know uh in the
context of of a culture that is um uh
that that was formed by uh or s by
Christianity every person's name
uh at least in today's world from the
reader point of view every reader's name
I'm David or we have also Fred and we
are already put within the drama of
Christianity, you know, we don't have we
we cannot call oursel uh some strange uh
uh African name or Chinese name if we
want to uh be in the classroom in the
first place. So this is uh this is uh
this ra raises some very challenging
question about how to uh transpose uh dy
into Chinese consciousness. Well, I do
recognize that as a Chinese person, I do
derive a lot of value from Danty even if
I'm looking at purely from the uh
perspective of confusionism or to toism
or or Buddha because I do think that
Danti in many uh in many perspective is
already going beyond Christianity in in
in his in his messages. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. Okay. Yes.
Okay. Great. Uh who's next?
Uh, Julian.
Um, yeah. So, I'm going to make it. So,
I have three points, so not so long. Um,
one thing I really appreciate about
Dante and that you always pointed out is
his paradoxes, the use of paradoxes in
his language. Like, every time
>> we talked about something he wrote, it
was always a paradox. And that's really
interesting because that's how you can
combine different truths. That's how you
can combine differences. That's you can
remove differences that we have in
today's world. And um you will see past
like you can use your imagination to see
past um these differences that you have
with other people and and through and so
yeah they become paradoxes that you have
to basically overcome and think about.
Um then also for me
uh the point of [snorts] being able to
resonate with Dante himself a lot. Um I
felt like when I was younger I went
through some kind of phase of inferno
maybe or hell. Um when when I was yeah
when I had a phase of yeah you could say
depression. And um now it's maybe like
purgatory for me. And I'm able to climb
up the stairs a bit. And it was really
my love I think for for knowledge that
brought me this far which is probably
similar to Dante as well. Um yeah that I
just want to keep on learning about
stuff. And um then the last point would
be about yeah hope as you
say as well is a really important factor
obviously that you convey hope when when
you talk you convey hope when you when
you act and I feel like he Dante gives a
lot of hope for people at his time and
obviously for now he can give hope um
yeah that's I think thank you. Okay.
>> Very important.
>> Um Edward,
>> uh yeah, there's there's probably a lot
a lot to say. Um I think one of one of
the main things I've appreciated uh from
from this study is obviously having the
chance to uh go through uh the whole
divine comedy and reflect, you know, on
my own life. uh you know normally in
life you might do some like one thing
wrong or one thing good and you might
reflect on it whereas this uh going
through the journey with Dante obviously
almost if you do reflect forces you to
look at uh yeah your own life in a lot
more detail. Um so and almost that
process in itself reflects the divine
comedy in the sense that when when you
first start looking at say the sins
you've committed before uh that maybe
align with uh the divine comedy uh you
can kind of feel bad about it and think
you know I've done this but then you can
also go through your own uh inferno
purgatory and into paradise you know
because there is
>> there is that feeling of hope and that
>> you know you can relate to Dante. He's
he's made mistakes. Virgil's made
mistakes. You know, a lot of people uh
in the book have made mistakes, but but
there is always hope. So, I suppose
that's applying the divine comedy on
myself.
Then the second stage would be then you
also look at the world differently. Uh
it probably makes you even though even
though we already know makes you realize
uh I would say we live in quite a sick
society in that you know there's a lot
of sins that we see in the piece but
they just just happen every single day
whether it's in uh politics, business or
general entertainment. Uh so I think
after reading it I would conclude that
uh the world would probably be a better
place if everyone read Dante. I agree. I
agree. And that's my mission to make
sure everyone does read Dante. Um Andy,
could we have some uh um thoughts from
you?
>> Sure. Um we use um we use metaphor to
comprehend and discuss um concepts that
are maybe too big for us to fully
understand. So we say things like life
is a baseball game or the universe is
like the ocean and we we connect them to
things that are small enough that we can
see, touch and understand. Um, most all
of literature is a metaphor for like the
human condition and they usually just
deal with like one single aspect of it.
This is love. This is a book on loss or
redemption. We've discussed a lot about
like paradise loss here. Um, and that's
what what Dante's doing is we're all
using metaphors to discuss or every
single great author has used a metaphor
to discuss what Dante is just describing
matterofactly. And Paradise Lost is what
we've kept bringing up the most often,
but it's just one part. It's just the
fall. Um, and what led up to that. And
so when we admire books like Lord of the
Rings or Crime and Punishment or Joyce's
Ulyses,
um, we're admiring it from a secondhand
nature where we could just go straight
to the source and Dante and the Divine
Comedy just cover it all. So, I told
Carol that as we come in here at the
start of this building, um I saw there's
a structure outside in our little that
little square and it's a little
purgatory and I saw kids walking up the
purgatory this morning
>> and Carol had mentioned
Carol mentioned that that's a good um a
good metaphor for what we do in here
because we're not in hell.
>> We're not in paradise. And so we come
here and we do the hard work um of
every year I give myself big challenges
for mind, body and spirit and Dante gets
to cover two of them.
>> Great. Thank you. Uh Ivy, I would like
to hear from you. Okay. What what is
your feelings after taking this course?
I wish just I wish to study classics in
university and before this I always
believe that the Greek civilization is
like basically the foundation of urban
um where like people respect the gods
and they fear the gods and everything is
at the mercy of external forces that we
cannot control. So like the Greek
civilization is basically a world of um
fear and like um
yeah just fear. Um but I um I also
remember like before this course started
I watched your videos on YouTube and in
one of the videos you mentioned that um
both Homer and Dante their works are
focused and based on love. But when I
was reading Homer, I didn't really get
that message. Like I didn't really
realize that what has driven Odysius or
what has um driven Achilles is love. Um
but I think like for Dante, it is really
easy for me to perceive the the the
message of love and um to perceive what
love means. Um so I think the reason why
I cannot perceive love in Homer but can
in Dante is because um Homer's world is
one that is more that is closer to the
initial goodness or like um the initial
perfection of the world like his world
is purer than Dante's and ours and
that's why like people believe in gods
like I think the gods are manifestations
of um people's inner um intu intuitions.
So um but for Dante, his world and our
world are both
um like we are we're constantly blinded
by everything floating around us. So it
is quite difficult for us to um gain
access to our intuitions. So that's why
things become less external and we need
to like look inside to see what's real.
Um
so I think like within such chaos of the
world um this course or Dante um and
professor Dung achieved like some sort
of separation within my own mind like
the separation of chaos into earth into
sky into hell into love quite similar to
the separation like in the Greek
mythology I think that's what this force
achieved within me. And so I think this
is really a beginning for my journey to
the future. And um I am also always
conscious of the importance of faith.
And while we were reading the infernal
and purgatory, I was horrified by the
fact that I I don't know who to pray to.
Like I don't know how to pray, like what
names should I utter? And I was really
afraid that I'm going to end up in hell
or purgatory. But then um I think as as
we delve deeper into the the major
beliefs of Dante, I think it actually
offer more comfort than fear because
Dante's thoughts is that it's okay if
you're not Christian or um if you don't
believe in a God or if you don't believe
in the gods. um
love, faith and hope are the fundamental
things that exist within ourselves. And
so um yeah, I think I I just need to try
and um believe in my intuition so um I
will have less fear in the future. And
last of all, if there's one faith that I
really adopted in this course, it's the
faith for poetry. Um I think I'm
convinced that poetry has the greatest
power in the world and it can actually
change the world. So I think in the
future I will before trying to teach
Dante to others I will keep reading
Dante and keep reading other great
poetries so that yeah we can make the
world a better place.
>> Thank you. Um great. Um, Carol,
let's um Sorry, sorry, we're just
running out of time, but but uh Okay,
Anna
really makes me more religious in a
sense, like more pious I guess. Um to
reconcile all the theologies in
Catholicism.
Um and also it makes me think about like
you know um that poet society where the
teacher says you know like science and
law and medicine it's how we live but
music, literature, poetry all these are
what we live for as humans and it really
makes me feel like yeah poetry is what
would do it all. So yeah thank you.
>> Okay great. Uh do
So uh one of things that amazed me
amazed me the most during this seminar
is that like um your ability to get into
the author's mind right uh what you call
close reading I mean I mean I I think
like this is like a high level
demonstration of close reading right and
that and I always wondered like how
could you
uh how could you find all those hidden
details in history and and then connect
the dots together, right? Like for
example, when you're reading uh you you
mentioned before like when you're
reading Frank Jacob, right? And you
understand the the mentality of of uh of
his of uh philosophy. And so and Sio can
uh speculate a you can propose a certain
theories that it enables you to to to
to
um to make good predictions, right? and
and during this course we went through
Dante's mind uh Beatrice Virgil and
it's just it's just amazing like I think
this is your superpower to to uh bring
their narrative to yourself and explain
it to us. And um
um other thing is that like and and
another thing is through reading divine
comedy I feel like it helped me to see
myself like more clearly. Um,
you know, like, uh, since I was young,
like since I was young, I mean, I grew
up in China, right? Like, like, uh,
everyone around you just kept telling
you that, oh, he's got to, uh, make a
bunch of money and it's it's all about
social status and,
um,
uh, and, uh, institutional achievement.
But uh like since I was young, I always
knew that I always felt like there's
something wrong about it and I always
had faith in my intuition, but I just
couldn't articulate it uh why I
I
should not think or live that way,
right?
And uh through this course I came to
understand more clearly that this divine
spark has always been within me and um
uh like just like the the email that I
wrote you wrote it to you right it
helped to it helped me to
it helped me to more determined to be
myself and yeah that's it.
>> Thank you. Okay. uh OA
>> um so before I come here I have already
uh read divine comedy but but it's in
Chinese and I feel like I'm very
confused especially for for the
paradoxio
uh but but I feel like even if I can't
understand it I feel like the the image
um you you you have in your head is very
beautiful and it's is divine. Um and
when I come here um I feel like the
learning journey of divine comedy is is
just like Dante. Uh at the first I'm I'm
very afraid to ask any questions or um
to express my opinions. But um over time
I feel like I I've gradually gained a
deeper understanding on divine comedy
and the the connections between these
ideas and my own life and how should I
um be become in the future.
Um
uh for example like like our parents
always tell us to um be a moral person,
be virtuous and do good things but but I
I don't actually like I I I want to know
the the logic not the logic the the the
framework why why actually you you need
to do good things and I have I think I
have gained a um systematic and thorough
understanding um on on this. And I feel
like towards the end all of all of our
uh classmates have formed a a bond
between us like um yeah and
um and I I have a question. So like many
others they have their dreams, right? I
have my dreams but I feel like my dreams
are very very um strange and different
from from like their their dreams they
it's is feel like it's a they has a
story line right I feel like in my
dreams they are fractions and it's like
watching a movie behind a curtain and I
try to understand all of the the the
bizarre things in my dream but I I I can
just I It's like I don't understand it.
It's like watching a cloud.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Thank you. Okay. Anyone else? Uh
Crystal, then then Bruce.
>> Okay. So I'll try to be quick here but
then like basically I think this is a
very rewarding experience for me to be
able to engage in such a diverse cohort
with people from different backgrounds
different age groups from different
career path and whatever to discuss the
same work and then like before I came
here like my perception on Dante of all
comedy is basically like it's a fiction
and it's very imaginative basically like
Dante's going on this imaginative
journey where he goes through these
three different regions and whatever.
But then I was kind of impressed to see
that there are a lot of real life
connections that still applies today.
For example, we can use like very common
logic to interpret some of the words of
Dante. I think that is very amazing. And
I feel like what I feel well this might
not align with Dante's cosmology is that
even the most divine has like these like
human features or like human nature
within it. So it's like okay for us to
be flawed and then also like I feel
pretty mentally and physically like um
stressed throughout this journey because
I think this is such a masterpiece and I
feel like at the same time through this
seminar I kind of feel the greatness of
art like how it's capable to unite all
of us together and how for example we
cannot understand Italian but we can
still feel like all the emotions within
those languages and I cannot understand
my handwriting. But I think this is also
like a great opportunity for me to get
to know like western culture and
literature a lot more. I feel like it
kind of connected all of the works I
read in literature class together. For
example, like I don't know the Odyssey
and also Paradise Lost and etc. I really
appreciate that and I feel like I would
really want to reread the divine comedy
and then try to understand more of it in
the future. And also despite that I
study a major that is completely the
opposite of classics. I think I will
want to spend some time to read other
relevant works and I feel like it's
pretty worth it and then yeah I just
want to say thanks for this opportunity
and for everyone.
>> Yeah. Thank you Bruce.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, I've been reading a lot
uh I've been written uh many more words
but I don't want to read it because uh I
think there are two things. The first
one is collectivism because as we're
know that as been told in China and all
of things about colle collectivism which
means you have to love your country you
have to love your family have love your
company and all of things good is really
good it really can help me a lot by uh
you know being good person right but
there's another kind of things like
individualism which is I think is maybe
we need to more in China because uh
after so many people just uh get lost
about lost their job about you know drop
out from the who they they they
sometimes just feel hopeless. Uh just
why just because individualism which
cannot let them to know more about
themselves. So if there's you know if
there are no authority who will
guarantee you that you can be perfect
then you just been hopeless. But
individualism which can really let you
to know who you really are and really
can make you feel peace and comfort even
though you've been denied by this a
whole system you know like school or
whatever but if you do believe yourself
you can be better and I think that is
really impressive and I I think this
very good opportunity for me to be here
to be taught uh by John and I think she
she's hero you're hero sorry you're hero
and uh yeah you're all heroes and you
just give us the way to see ourel in
oursel. Yeah. Not deny yourself by by
other kind of things like be rich, be
powerful, be famous. No, not of lot of
thing. But you have to believe yourself.
That is what really Yeah. important.
>> Thank you. Okay. Um uh Fred
>> um I haven't been here for a very long
time.
>> Okay. Um,
[sighs]
I guess the question was how has it
changed you? Well, it's made me realize
you have to do things in the real world
and it's important just to get to places
and do things and speak to people. Like
a lot of theorizing is useless. And I'm
very glad that I got to sit in this room
because I guess people who started from
the beginning weren't really watching
the live streams. But I was watching the
live streams and I just had a vision of
what it would be like to sit at the
desks and I just really really really
wanted it to happen and then I it
happened. So on the first day I thought
I'd be really really nervous and my
heart would be racing but then for some
reason the uh the in tuness of this
group made it feel natural immediately.
It was really strange. Like I'm a really
big fan of you. I've been I've watched
like every one of your videos from when
you're only writing on a whiteboard when
you had no screen.
>> Okay.
>> And so I thought I would feel so nervous
even answering a question, but it was it
felt so natural and I it's difficult to
explain that um other than
love and learning and all these good
things make
what would otherwise have been nervous
situations feel natural. Hey,
>> thank you. Okay. Uh Carol. Yeah.
Um, so I love the star metaphor because
I believe in Latin and perhaps in
Italian as well, the word for desire
>> is deedar.
>> Oh,
>> and um actually the short form of it is
decided which means from the stars. And
I think this whole journey has reminded
me and possibly more of you that we're
all from the stars and that desire is
that calling to go back and I really
love Francois's imagery
of and and and you putting the web in
Indra's web in my mind and actually um
for me my vision is actually to catch
fish
and to build community.
>> Um, which actually was also something
inspired by um, videos I watched from
you and and catching fish. Um, it's
almost the imagery of um, the endress
net. There seems to be a lot of souls
caught in the web and in the nets and
some are freer, some are less free. And
um, I want to help free people. you you
can go freely in [laughter] and out, but
you know hopefully retrieving your route
back to the stars
>> and that's um my vision and it was
actually a lucid dream.
>> Wow. Okay.
>> So, thank you. Thank you very much for
this experience.
>> All right. So, um first of all, I want
to express tremendous gratitude. Um this
is the last day and I'm feeling nothing
but gratitude for everything uh to
everyone. Um so my intention for
organizing this seminar um and having uh
and you know working with Carol is I
want to read Dante in full and I want to
understand Dante because I've taught
Dante for the past four years but I've
always cheated. you know, I've always
skipped around and looking for patches
that conform to my particular um
perspective. And I said to myself,
that's not really fair. What I want to
do is I want to read Dante in full. But
I also knew that you can actually you
cannot actually read Dante unless you
read it from a place of love. So, how do
I create a situation where I'm motivated
to read Dante? Because it's hard to read
Dante. Okay. You think Dante is hard? I
also think it's hard. It's not it's
never been an it was never an easy uh
journey. So I thought that if I read it
with students and I'm I'm able to uh
inspire them to love Dante then that
would inspire me to truly understand
Dante and that's exactly what has
happened. Okay? because um I came in not
knowing what these 12 days would be like
and I had some conceptions of where of
what Dante would be. But um I knew that
only if I went deep into Dante and put
my faith in the poetry and put my faith
in this class because I truly appreciate
Dante. And so what would happen is we
would have these great discussions
during the day. I go home and I spend
all my time just replaying in my head
what we discussed and looking for
problems, looking for areas in which I
could expand. Then I go to bed. Then I
would have actually no idea what I would
teach in the morning. But because I knew
that when I came to class, you guys
wanted expecting me to like be heroic
and teach Dante in the most engaging way
possible. I'm like, okay. So like I
don't have any ideas on how to teach and
like let me pray and hope that I have
something to something and so so I get
up and then some I visions ideas would
start coming in my head and like a
framework would come to my head and I
come to class and I would start and then
your energy your enthusiasm your love
would compel me to further expand my my
visions. Right? So for example um you
know yesterday we had a very interesting
class where we had this experiment right
where Francois and Edward were doing
this experiment and that was not planned
in any way. Okay. What happened was that
I was teaching uh about the s systems of
um in of Dante. Then Franis came up to
me and said hey um uh so let's I I've
drawn up some notes and like great show
it. Okay. And then um professor was
presenting and then I was inspired at
that moment. It's like oh wow you know
what I can do this this experiment right
and like I hope it works if it doesn't
work then oh well but I hope it works
and it worked out really really well.
Okay so this entire class has been one
of a leap of faith. I didn't really
expect uh anything from this class. I
thought I'd be challenged to
um read the line comedy but I really
didn't expect the effect on me. I didn't
expect the effect on you guys and just
having spending the past 12 days with
you. I've seen myself transform
tremendously. I've seen you transform
tremendously as well. So my major
transformation is um I've left teaching
at my school and now I'm looking for a
new path forward. So like Dante, I'm
sort of lost in the woods and I'm like
well you know I'll teach a seminar to
just pass a time right to just hope hope
for the best. And having taught this
seminar, I'm like, I now know what I
must do. Okay? I now must share Dante
with the world. I because I see Dante's
impact on each and every one of you.
Maybe maybe it's something that you
can't articulate yourself, but the fact
that you're dreaming lucidly, the fact
that you're willing to share these
dreams with every one of us, and the
fact that you're willing to help, you're
willing to um discuss the meaning of
these dreams, it's an act of love, it's
an act of faith, it's an act of hope.
And I realize that if we really want to
change the world for the better, then
Dante
um could be an answer. It's one of the
answers. And so I'm committed to uh
teaching Dante around the world now. So
thank you for that. But also I recognize
that teaching Dante is not enough. I
need to summon Dante back to this world.
And what surprised me is I'm not sure if
you guys know the occult or rituals, but
you know these 12 days it was an oult
ritual. You know how these billionaires,
they spend a lot of time trying to
summon demons into this world, right?
Well, through our reading of Dante
together, we all engage in our
imagination that brought Dante back to
this earth. I really feel that. I really
feel that there's an essence of Dante in
each of us now. Okay? And we've brought
Dante back to this world. And if we can
bring more people into this community,
if we can spread Dante more to people,
then there'll be more of Dante in this
world. But not only do I want to bring
Dante back, I also want to bring back uh
Plato, Homer, Jesus. Okay? Everyone
everyone wants to bring back Jesus, but
like in the right way. Okay? Like in the
right way, like don't start wars. Okay?
And and so I see now that is my mission.
I see tremendous hope because I see uh
the the impact of this teaching on on
you. So I'm just coming from a place of
tremendous gratitude um a place of
tremendous hope. So thank you so much uh
for that. Um, I mean, first I mean, like
I would like to thank above all Carol,
okay? Because this is our first time
working together and um I can't show
enough appreciation for you and your
team because um it's actually hard to
put these things together. All right.
The idea that we can come to uh this
class, I can teach what I teach and we
can live stream it and the live stream
is able to go very smoothly and you guys
are able to engage uh and the fact that
I didn't do any work before class. Uh
you know, Carol is the one who brought
everyone together. So I can't um so I I
can't appreciate Carol enough. So thank
you so much, Carol. [snorts]
Oh,
also like again um um
Thank you for having the will and the
idea thing.
>> Yeah. But again, I'm going to Carol and
our team are amazing. So, um, Carol,
could could you thank your team?
>> Yes. Um, I want to thank, um, our IT and
AV staff and because we do realize that
there are issues every day. Um, but
they've really tried their very best and
it's around the clock because there's
also uploading and we know where we are.
The networks are slow here. I want to
thank Yanglio Peter Su uh and uh
the person who cleaned the whiteboard.
Just every single person. And you know,
she was the one who cleaned up all your
water bottles and replenished all your
water bottles every day and set
everything up. But um I I I do want to
thank um Jang uh for summoning and you
know actually um if this were an
occultist experience you're the priest
and you helped to summon this for us and
you helped to lead us on this
pilgrimage. So I know you have put in
your heart and soul to it as if we were
children on your backs and you've
shouldered a lot of responsibility.
So really a heartfelt thanks to you.
>> So um you know it seems like I did a lot
of work but let me tell you I am not
exhausted. I am not at all exhausted. I
feel so energized. I feel so hopeful.
Um, I feel a deep sense of gratitude.
Uh, so Fred asks, um, so what's next?
Um, what can we do? And I mean, we're
already doing a lot. Okay, so I I know,
okay, uh, we're just a classroom, but
you know, there are a lot of people
watching this online and
they are going to be inspired by our
example. Um the the love of Divine
Comedy is already implanted in your
heart. And maybe you don't know this
now, but your life has changed because
of Divine Comedy. You won't know this
now. 20 years from now when you look
back, you will see it yourself because
your entire life trajectory will be
different now. many of you um for
example Ivy is going to read more and
more poetry and uh you're going to keep
on studying divine comedy uh like like
Crystal and
um this is going to just blossom in you
and then eventually when the time is
right you're going to want to share this
with other people you're going to sh
want to share with your children with
your friends with your students and
there's going to be a chain reaction.
Okay. So, um I have complete faith that
this will happen that this is the
beginning of something wonderful. It
will take time but it will happen and
already we are making a huge difference
in the world. So what I want to do okay
so let let me present to you my grand
vision for the world.
Um
I want to start
a network of schools around the world.
Okay. And this network of schools will
teach the great books um and even the
cult and game theory. And my ambition is
to educate the next global generation of
Dantes of intellectuals because I see
the the spark of Dante in all of you.
Okay? And I'm sure there's millions more
of young children who could be the next
Dante. But you have to reach out to
them. You have to give them the
opportunity. So I so my end goal is to
start a network of schools and it's not
a like a two-year project. I I plan next
to spend the rest of my life 50 years
developing this network of schools
around the world everywhere um so that
as many people can participate uh in
reading Dante as possible and
um my invitation is to all of you to
consider one day joining this network
schools. Okay. So you could go off on
your own path and um see the world
because as as ton would say life is a
journey and you have to go through hell
and p purgatory before you can reach
heaven. Okay so I'm not saying my
schools will be heaven but I'm saying
like you all have an open invitation to
come to the school and you can come come
as whoever you want. You you can come in
as a student, you can come as a teacher,
you can come as just maybe um a
volunteer but um I want to stay in touch
and and I feel that we came here for a
reason. It is the will of the universe
uh for us to come together and what that
is we don't know. Uh, but I hope we can
stay in touch and I'm going to build
these schools and my mission now is to
travel around the world, spread the
message of Dante,
um, and teach more classes and I think
eventually
um, these schools will will naturally
blossom because I think that um, I've
seen the future
um, these visions keep keep on coming in
my head. and the universe did not will
it then we will not be here today. Okay.
So, thank you to everyone for giving me
hope and um this is just the first step
in a long long process. Uh yes,
>> are we the first generation of neo
dentists
>> if you want to be? Yes. Yes. Okay. All
right. So, thank you so much. Okay. And
uh let's stay in touch. And again, this
is this is just the beginning of
something wonderful. Okay. All right.
Bye-bye.
>> [applause]